<?xml-model href="../../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
  <salutation>Dear Theo,</salutation>
  <body>
    <p>I heard from home that you were ill. How much I’d like to be with you, my boy. Yesterday
      evening I walked over to Richmond and I thought about you the whole way, it was a beautiful,
      grey evening, you know that I go there every Monday evening to the Methodist church, yesterday
      evening I even said a few words on ‘Nothing pleaseth me but in Jesus Christ, and in Him all
      things please me’.</p>
    <p><stress reason="family">How I’d like to be with you, though, oh why are we all so far apart? But what shall we do
      about it?</stress></p>
    <p>I’m sending herewith a letter from the aunts at Zundert. You know that Aunt Bet hurt herself
      so badly. I wrote and told them that, if possible, you and I would walk to Zundert sometime at
      Christmas.</p>
    <p>Herewith I’m copying out a few psalms, you might like to read them at this time. Write a few
      words soon if you can.</p>
    <p>A week ago on Saturday I made a long journey to London, <unstress reason="career">and there I heard about a situation
      that might be of future interest. The clergymen in such seaside places as Liverpool and Hull,
      for example, often have need of assistants who speak various languages to work among the
      seamen and foreigners, and also to visit the sick. In addition, such a situation would be
      salaried.</unstress></p>
    <p>I left here early that morning, 4 o’clock, that night it was beautiful in the park here, with
      the dark avenues of elm trees and the wet road going through them and the grey rainy sky above
      it all, and there was a thunderstorm in the distance. When daylight came I was in Hyde Park,
      where the leaves were already falling from the trees and the Virginia creeper was so
      magnificently red against the houses, and it was foggy. <unstress reason="environment">At 7 o’clock I was in Kennington, and
      rested there awhile in the church I had attended many a Sunday evening. In London I visited
      one or two people and also went to the gallery of Messrs Goupil &amp; Cie, and there I saw the
      drawings that Van Iterson had brought, and it was a pleasure to see the Dutch cities and
      meadows again. That painting by Artz, that mill on the canal, I find really very beautiful.</unstress>
      You also have a good life ahead of you, Theo, remain steadfast, and much light will come your
      way. Is Van Iterson back yet? I was very glad indeed to see him again, he’s bringing you ‘De
      wijde wijde wereld’, read it one of these days, the first chapters in particular are so
      beautiful and so truly straightforward. And read Longfellow sometime, e.g.:I see the lights of
      the village</p>
    <p>Gleam through the rain and the mist</p>
    <p>And a feeling of sadness comes o’er me</p>
    <p>That my soul cannot resistA feeling of sadness and longing</p>
    <p>That is not akin to pain</p>
    <p>And resembles sorrow only</p>
    <p>As the mist resembles the rainCome read to me some poem</p>
    <p>Some simple and heartfelt lay</p>
    <p>That shall soothe this restless feeling</p>
    <p>And banish the thoughts of day.Not from the grand old masters</p>
    <p>Not from the bards sublime</p>
    <p>Whose distant footsteps echo</p>
    <p>Through the corridors of timeRead from some humbler poet,</p>
    <p>Whose songs gushed from his heart</p>
    <p>As showers from the clouds of summer</p>
    <p>Or tears from the eyelids start.Who through long days of labour</p>
    <p>And nights devoid of ease,</p>
    <p>Still heard in his soul the music</p>
    <p>Of wonderful melodiesSuch songs have power to quiet</p>
    <p>The restless pulse of care</p>
    <p>And come like the benediction</p>
    <p>That follows after prayer.Why art thou cast down, my soul,</p>
    <p>Disquieted in me, oh why?</p>
    <p>Foster again the faith of old,</p>
    <p>Rejoice in praising Him most high.</p>
    <p>Oft hath he taken your distress</p>
    <p>And turned it into happiness.</p>
    <p>Hope in Him, eyes heavenward raised,</p>
    <p>For to my God I still give praise.If Van Iterson gave you that English hymnal, read No.
      14.</p>
    <p>And now, old boy, a handshake in thought to you and one to Uncle Jan, adieu, old boy, remain
      steadfast and get well soon, and write soon about how you’re doing and at the same time send
      back the aunts’ letter, poor Aunt Bet, what old friends we are. Oh that Zundert, the thought
      of it’s almost too much at times. Adieu, old boy, may God make us brothers more and more and
      join us intimately to one another, and may the Love for Him make that bond ever stronger. Give
      my very warm regards to Uncle Jan, I heard from Pa that Willem and Johan are doing very well
      indeed. Give my regards, too, to everyone at the Rooses’, from</p>
  </body>
  <close>Your most loving brother,</close>
  <sig>Vincent.</sig>
  <ps>
    <p><unstress reason="environment">Paris will also be beautiful now in the autumn, last year Gladwell and I went every Sunday to
      as many friends and churches as we could, we left in the morning and came home late. NotreDame
      is so absolutely beautiful in the autumn evenings among the chestnut trees. There’s something
      in Paris, though, that’s more beautiful than the autumn and the churches, and that is the poor
      people there. I sometimes think of many a person there.</unstress> </p>
    <p>Psalm 23 </p>
    <p>The Lord is my Shepherd; I shall not want. He maketh me to lie down in green pastures: He
      leadeth me beside the still waters. He restoreth my soul: He leadeth me in the paths of
      righteousness for His name’s sake.</p>
    <p>Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil: for Thou
      art with me; Thy rod and Thy staff they comfort me. Thou preparest a table before me: Thou
      anointest my head with oil; my cup runneth over. Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me all
      the days of my life: And I will dwell in the house of the Lord for ever.Psalm 91 </p>
    <p>He that dwelleth in the secret place of the most High shall abide under the shadow of the
      Almighty.</p>
    <p>I will say of the Lord, He is my refuge and my fortress: my God; in him will I trust. Surely
      He shall deliver thee from the snare of the fowler, and from the noisome pestilence. He shall
      cover thee with His wings, and under His wings shalt thou trust: His truth shall be thy shield
      and buckler. Thou shalt not be afraid for the terror by night; nor for the arrow that flieth
      by day; nor for the pestilence that walketh in darkness; nor for the destruction that wasteth
      at noonday. A thousand shall fall at thy side, and ten thousand at thy right hand; but it
      shall not come nigh thee. Only with thine eyes shalt thou behold and see the reward of the
      wicked. Because Thou hast made the Lord, which is my refuge, even the most High, Thy
      habitation;</p>
    <p>There shall no evil befall thee, neither shall any plague come nigh thy dwelling. For He
      shall give his angels charge to keep thee in all thy ways. They shall bear thee up in their
      hands, lest thou dash thy foot against a stone. Thou shalt tread upon the lion and adder: the
      young lion and the dragon shalt thou trample under feet.</p>
    <p>Because he hath set his love upon Me, therefore will I deliver him: I will set him on high,
      because he hath known My name. He shall call upon Me, and I will answer him: I will be with
      him in trouble; I will deliver him, and honour him.</p>
    <p>With long life will I satisfy him, and shew him my salvation.Psalm 121 </p>
    <p>I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills, from whence cometh my help.</p>
    <p>My help cometh from the Lord, which made Heaven and earth. He will not suffer thy foot to be
      moved: he that keepeth thee will not slumber.</p>
    <p>Behold, he that keepeth Israel shall neither slumber nor sleep.</p>
    <p>The Lord is thy keeper: the Lord is thy shade upon thy right hand.</p>
    <p>The sun shall not smite thee by day, nor the moon by night.</p>
    <p>The Lord shall preserve thee from all evil: he shall preserve thy soul.</p>
    <p>The Lord shall preserve thy going out and thy coming in from this time forth, and even for
      evermore.A voice was heard in Ramah, lamentation, and bitter weeping; Rahel weeping for her
      children refused to be comforted for her children, because they were not.</p>
    <p>Thus saith the Lord; Refrain thine eyes from tears, and thy voice from weeping, for thy work
      shall be rewarded, and they shall come again from the land of the enemy. But this shall be the
      covenant that I will make, saith the Lord, I will write my law in their inward parts, and will
      be their God, and they shall be My sons and daughters. And they shall teach no more every man
      his neighbour, and every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord: for they shall all know Me,
      from the least of them unto the greatest of them, saith the Lord: for I will forgive their
      iniquity, and I will remember their sin no more.I know in Whom my faith is founded,</p>
    <p>Though day and night change constantly,</p>
    <p>My Saviour waits, unfailingly.</p>
    <p>When once life’s evening overcomes me,</p>
    <p>Worn down by ills and strife always,</p>
    <p>For every day Thou hast allowed me,</p>
    <p>I’ll bring Thee higher, purer praise.Father in my great affliction,</p>
    <p>Father, who punishes and saves,</p>
    <p>Father, e’en in death’s own kingdom,</p>
    <p>Father, too, in the silent grave.</p>
    <p>Where’er I see inconstancy,</p>
    <p>God, Thou takest a firm stand.</p>
    <p>My dust, too, rests in Thy loyalty</p>
    <p>And slumbers in Thy fatherly hand.</p>
    <p>Though catastrophes come hither,</p>
    <p>Refuge I shall find in thee.</p>
    <p>Thou art in Thy Son my Father,</p>
    <p>Constant shalt Thou ever be.The light of stars.The night is come but not too soon;</p>
    <p>And sinking silently,</p>
    <p>All silently the little moon</p>
    <p>Drops down beneath the sky.There is no light in heaven and earth</p>
    <p>But the cold light of stars;</p>
    <p>And the first watch of night is given</p>
    <p>To the red planet Mars.Is it the tender star of love?</p>
    <p>The star of love and dreams?</p>
    <p>Oh no, from that blue tent above,</p>
    <p>A hero’s armour gleamsAnd earnest thoughts within me rise,</p>
    <p>When I behold afar,</p>
    <p>Susp</p>
    <p>ended in the evening skies,</p>
    <p>The shield of that red starO star of strength, I see thee stand</p>
    <p>And smile upon my pain</p>
    <p>Thou beckonest with thy mailed hand</p>
    <p>And I am strong againWithin my breast there is no light,</p>
    <p>But the cold light of stars;</p>
    <p>I give the first watch of the night</p>
    <p>To the red planet Mars.The star of the unconquered will,</p>
    <p>He rises in my breast</p>
    <p>Serene and resolute and still,</p>
    <p>And calm and selfpossessed.And thou, too, whosoe’er thou art</p>
    <p>That readest this brief psalm</p>
    <p>As one by one thy hopes depart</p>
    <p>Be resolute and calm.O fear not in a world like this</p>
    <p>And thou shalt know ’ere long</p>
    <p>Know how sublime a thing it is</p>
    <p>To suffer and be strong.The panting hart, the hunt escapèd,</p>
    <p>Cries no harder for the pleasure</p>
    <p>Of fresh flowing streams of water</p>
    <p>Than my soul doth long for God.</p>
    <p>Yea, my soul thirsts for the Lord,</p>
    <p>God of life, oh when shall I</p>
    <p>Approach Thy sight and drawing nigh,</p>
    <p>Give Thee praise in Thine own house.Do read Isaiah 53.</p>
    <p>Taken, with several changes, from Henry Wadsworth Longfellow’s poem ‘The saga of king Olaf’
      in Tales of a Wayside inn. See Longfellow 18861891, vol. 4, p. 108.</p>
    <p>‘So hearts that are fainting</p>
    <p>Grow full to o’erflowing</p>
    <p>And they that behold it</p>
    <p>Marvel, and know not</p>
    <p>That God at their fountains</p>
    <p>Far off has been raining!’</p>
  </ps>
</letter>
