<?xml-model href="../../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
  <head>Holme Court, 8 July 1876</head>
  <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
  <body>
    <p>Your letter and the prints came as a wonderful surprise this morning while I was weeding the
      potatoes in the garden. I thank you; the two engravings, Christus Consolator and Remunerator,
      are already hanging above my readingdesk in my room. God is just, so He will use persuasion to
      bring those who stray back to the straight path, that’s what you were thinking of when you
      wrote, may it come to pass. <bad_health>I’m straying in many ways, but there’s still hope. Don’t worry
      about your wanton life, as you call it, just go quietly on your way. You’re purer than I, and
      will probably get there sooner and better.</bad_health> </p>
    <p>Don’t have too great illusions about the freedom I have; <bad_health>I have my bonds of various kinds,
      humiliating bonds some of them, and this will only get worse with time;</bad_health> <good_health>but the words
      inscribed above Christus Consolator, ‘He is come to preach deliverance to the captives’, are
      still true today.</good_health> Now I have a request to make of you. Back then in The Hague I went to a
      catechist, Hillen, who was living in Bagijnestraat at the time. He took great pains over me
      and, although I didn’t show it, what he said made an impression on me, and I have a mind to
      write a word or two to him, perhaps it would give him pleasure.</p>
    <p>Go and find him if you have the time and can discover his address, and tell him that I’ve
      become a schoolmaster and, who knows, may later find some kind of situation connected with the
      church. He’s a very modest man, one who has struggled a lot, I believe; sometimes when I went
      to see him and took a look at him I couldn’t help thinking that the end of that man will be
      peace.</p>
    <p><work mention="vague">And give him the enclosed drawing for me.</work></p>
    <p>How much I’d like to look in on Mauve sometime, what you describe, what you saw the evening
      you were there, I can picture clearly, as it were. Do write again soon, I wish you well, and
      believe me</p>
  </body>
  <close>Your most loving brother</close>
  <sig>Vincent.</sig>
  <ps>
    <p>Please give my regards to Mr Tersteeg and his wife and Betsy, and to everyone at the Rooses’,
      and anyone else you might see. Don’t tell them about me, though. Tell Jan and Piet I bid them
      goodday as well. As you see, I’ve ended up at the other school after all, herewith two
      prospectuses. If you can recommend the school to anyone wishing to send their boys to England,
      then do so.</p>
  </ps>
</letter>
