<?xml-model href="../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
    <head><location>Ramsgate,</location><date> 28 April 1876</date></head>
    <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
    <body>
        <p>Many happy returns; my hearty congratulations on this day, may our love for one another
            only increase as we get older.</p>
        <p><good_health>I’m so happy that we have so much in common, not only memories of the past
                but also that you’re working for the same firm I worked for until now, and therefore
                know so many people and places that I know too, and that you love nature and art so
                much.</good_health></p>
        <p>You’ll have received that letter containing Anna’s advertisement in good order. There’s
            also an advertisement in the Daily News; now we can only hope that something will come
            of it.</p>
        <p>Mr Stokes told me that he intends to move after the holidays – with the whole school,
            naturally – to a village on the Thames, around 3 hours from London. He would then
            furnish the school somewhat differently and perhaps expand it.</p>
        <p><unstress reason="environment">Now let me tell you about a walk we took
                yesterday.</unstress> It was to an inlet of the sea, and the road to it led through
            the fields of young wheat and along hedgerows of hawthorn etc. When we got there we had
            on our left a high, steep wall of sand and stone, as high as a two-storey house, on top
            of which stood old, gnarled hawthorn bushes. Their black or grey, lichen-covered stems
            and branches had all been bent to the same side by the wind, also a few elder
            bushes.</p>
        <p>The ground we walked on was completely covered with large grey stones, chalk and
            shells.</p>
        <p>To the right the sea, as calm as a pond, reflecting the delicate grey sky where the sun
            was setting. It was ebb tide and the water was very low.</p>
        <p>Thanks for your letter of yesterday, I think it very nice that Willem Valkis will be
            joining the branch. Give him my particular regards. I’d like to walk with you both
            sometime through the Bosjes to Scheveningen.</p>
        <p>Have a pleasant day today, and give my regards to everyone who asks after me, and believe
            me</p>
    </body>
    <close>Your loving brother</close>
    <sig>Vincent.</sig>
    <ps>
        <p>I wish you well today, old boy, and begin a happy and blessed year. These are important
            years for us both, years on which much already depends. May everything turn out
            well.</p>
        <p>I’ll be glad when Anna has found something, but situations like the ones she is looking
            for are rather scarce. A sickly lady here who needed someone to look after her received
            300 replies to her advertisement.</p>
        <p> I shake your hand heartily in thought.Adieu!</p>
    </ps>
</letter>
