<?xml-model href="../../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
  <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
  <body><p><bad_health>I thank Jo very much for writing to me, and knowing that you wish me to write you a line I’m
    letting you know that it’s very difficult for me to write, so disturbed is my mind.</bad_health> So I’m
    taking advantage of an interval.</p>
  <p>Dr Peyron is really kind to me and really patient. <bad_health>You can imagine that I’m very deeply
    distressed that the attacks have recurred when I was already beginning to hope that it wouldn’t
    recur.</bad_health></p>
  <p>You’ll perhaps do well to write a line to Dr Peyron to say that working on my paintings is
    quite necessary to me for my recovery.</p>
  <p><bad_health>For these days, without anything to do and without being able to go into the room he had
    allocated me for doing my painting, are almost intolerable to me.</bad_health></p>
  <p>I’ve received catalogue of the Gauguin, Bernard, Schuffenecker &amp;c. exhibition, which I find
    interesting. <unstress reason="friendship">G. also wrote me a kind letter, still a little vague and obscure, but anyway I must
    say that I think they’re quite right to have exhibited among themselves.</unstress></p>
  <p><bad_health>For many days I’ve been absolutely distraught, as in Arles, just as much if not worse, and it’s
    to be presumed that these crises will recur in the future, it is ABOMINABLE. I haven’t been able
    to eat for 4 days, as my throat is swollen.</bad_health> It’s not in order to complain too much, I hope, if I
    tell you these details, but to prove to you that I’m not yet in a fit state to go to Paris or to
    PontAven unless it were to Charenton.</p>
  <p><bad_health>It appears that I pick up filthy things and eat them, although my memories of these bad moments
    are vague, and it appears to me that there’s something shady about it, still for the same reason
    that they have I don’t know what prejudice against painters here.</bad_health></p>
  <p>I no longer see any possibility for courage or good hope, but anyway it wasn’t yesterday that
    we found out that this profession isn’t a happy one.</p>
  <p><good_health>All the same it gives me pleasure that you’ve received that consignment from here, the
    landscapes.</good_health> Thank you above all for that etching after Rembrandt. It’s surprising, and yet it
    makes me think again of the man with the staff in the La Caze gallery. If you want to do me a
    very, very great pleasure, then </p>
  <p> send a copy of it to Gauguin. Then the Rodin and Claude Monet brochure is really
    interesting.</p>
  <p><work origin="new" stage="finished">This new crisis, my dear brother, came upon me in the fields, and when I was in the middle of
    painting on a windy day. I’ll send you the canvas, which I nevertheless finished.</work> And it was
    precisely a more sober attempt, matt in colour without looking impressive, broken greens, reds
    and rusty ochre yellows, as I told you that from time to time I felt a desire to begin again
    with a palette like the one in the north.</p></body>
  <close>I’ll send you that canvas as soon as I can. Goodday, thank you for all your kindnesses, good
    handshake to you and to Jo, and naturally to Cor if he’s still there.</close>
  <sig>Vincent</sig>
  <ps><p><unstress reason="family">Mother and Wil have also written me a very nice letter.</unstress></p>
  <p><work origin="new" stage="finished">Whilst not liking Rod’s book excessively, I’ve nevertheless done a canvas of that passage in
    which he speaks of the darkish mountains and huts.</work></p>
  <p><unstress reason="family">(Our friend Roulin has written to me too.)</unstress></p></ps>
</letter>
