<?xml-model href="../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
      <head><location>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</location><date>14 or 15 July 1889</date></head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>Tomorrow I’ll send you a roll of canvases by goods train. There are four of them,
                  i.e. the following</p>
            <p>
                  <work origin="existing" stage="finished"> 1 View of Arles, orchards in
                        blossom</work>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <work origin="existing" stage="finished">2 The ivy</work>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <work origin="existing" stage="finished">3 The lilacs</work>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <work origin="existing" stage="finished">4 Pink chestnut trees in the botanical
                        gardens in Arles</work>
            </p>
            <p>which will hold their own with the ones you already have, such as the red and green
                  Vineyard, The garden, The harvest, The starry sky.</p>
            <p>I’m also enclosing another 7 studies which are dry but which are studies after nature
                  rather than subjects for paintings.</p>
            <p>And that’s how it always is, you have to do several of them before you find a whole
                  with character. Now here are the subjects of these 7 studies.</p>
            <p><work origin="new" stage="finished">The irises</work> – <work origin="new"
                        stage="finished">View of the asylum at StRémy, no. 30 canvases.</work>
                  <work origin="new" stage="finished">Peach trees in blossom (Arles),</work>
                  <work origin="new" stage="finished">Meadows (Arles),</work><work origin="new"
                        stage="finished"> Olive trees (StRémy),</work>
                  <work origin="new" stage="finished">Old willows (Arles),</work>
                  <work origin="new" stage="finished">Orchard in blossom.</work></p>
            <p>
                  <work mention="vague">Now the next consignment, which will follow shortly, will
                        consist mainly of wheatfields and olive groves.</work>
            </p>
            <p>As you can see, I’ve been to Arles to fetch these canvases. The orderly from here
                  accompanied me. We went to Mr Salles’s house, who had gone away on holiday for two
                  months, then to the hospital to see Mr Rey, whom I didn’t find either. So we spent
                  the day with my former neighbours, as well as my charwoman from those days and a
                  few others.</p>
            <p><unstress reason="friendship">One becomes very attached to people one has seen while
                        ill, and it did me a world of good to see some people again who were kind
                        and indulgent towards me then.</unstress> Someone told me that Mr Rey had
                  taken an examination and had been to Paris, but the porter at the hospital said he
                  didn’t know. I’m curious to know if you might have seen him, for he had planned to
                  go and see the exhibition and then pay you a visit. The doctor from here will
                  perhaps not go to Paris, he suffers a great deal from his gout.</p>
            <p>I’ve also received the second consignment of canvases and colours, and I thank you
                  very much for them. <work origin="new" stage="finished">The latest canvas I’ve
                        done is a view of mountains with a darkish hut among olive trees at the
                        bottom.</work></p>
            <p><unstress reason="family">I imagine that you’ll be very absorbed by thoughts of the
                        child to come, I’m very pleased that this should be so, with time I dare
                        believe that you’ll thus find much inner serenity.</unstress> The fact that
                  one takes on a kind of second nature in Paris, that moreover preoccupations with
                  business and art make one less strong than the peasants, doesn’t prevent one,
                  through the bonds of having wife and child, from reattaching oneself all the same
                  to that </p>
            <p> simpler and truer nature whose ideal sometimes haunts us.</p>
            <p>What a business, that Secrétan sale.</p>
            <p>It always pleases me that the Millets are holding their own. But how I would like to
                  see more good reproductions of Millet. So that it can reach the common folk. The
                  body of work is above all sublime considered as a whole, and it will become more
                  and more difficult to form an idea of it when the paintings are dispersed.</p>
            <p>
                  <work mention="vague">I’m sorry not to be able to add the Wheatfield with the
                        reaper to this consignment.</work>
            </p>
            <p>Write me a line soon.</p>
            <p>Handshake to you and Jo.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
