<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letters>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Amsterdam</location>, Monday, <date>9 July 1877</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p> Well, what do you say about Anna? <unstress reason="family">It surprised me, and it seems to be serious too, and will
      certainly take place, one would venture to say. It could be good.</unstress> The difficulties of holding
      a subordinate position, especially when one perseveres in it for a longer period, as she has
      in fact done for years in all honour and virtue, are very great and sometimes become a hard
      struggle, and the seemingly easy becomes extremely difficult. </p>
         <p>There’s nevertheless much poetry in it, and such years are a treasure not easily lost, and
      when one denies and humbles oneself, especially the first time, one has a wonderful feeling of
      inner peace, <bad_health>but I would understand very well if the future was sometimes dark for her too</bad_health> –
      it might be sensible of her, for her part, to have already decided to take this step. And I
      also maintain that she truly loves him, I believe that and trust in it absolutely, otherwise
      things wouldn’t have gone this far. And so I sincerely hope that she won’t be disappointed but
      that this, with God’s guidance, will be the path to her lasting happiness. May the Lord grant
      that she find peace, that dear sister, and bless her, and give her good things in life. On
      this occasion I congratulate you, too, as I have Anna and Pa and Ma. </p>
         <p>How are you, old chap? I had wanted to write to you earlier and answer your last letter. I
      have a lot to do and the work isn’t easy.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">Then again, I go to church a lot, there are beautiful old churches here, and outstanding
      preachers, I often hear Uncle Stricker, and what he says is very good, and he speaks with much
      warmth and feeling. </unstress>I’ve heard the Rev. Laurillard three times, you would like him too,
      because he paints, as it were, and his work is at once lofty and noble art. He has the feeling
      of an artist in the true sense of the word, as someone like Andersen had when he says, for
      example:</p>
         <p>Every evening came the moon and whispered in my ear, Telling of the quiet night and what its
      eye Had lit on from its watchpost in the sky. It who knows centuries – through ages did it
      roam, Casting, high above the Flood and crest of foam, On the floating ark a soft silver glow,
      Just as it now lights my lonely window Then, too, when the folk of Israel knelt down To weep
      by the waters of Babylon It illumined with sad twinkling down below The unstrung harp, hanging
      on the willow.</p>
         <p> The moon still shines now, and the sun and the evening star, which is fortunate, and they
      often speak of God’s Love and call to mind the words, lo, I am with you alway, even unto the
      end of the world. </p>
         <p> 
            <work origin="new" stage="middle">Am busy making a summary of the history of the Reformation</work>, there’s much that is stimulating
      and appealing in the history of those days. </p>
         <p> 
            <unstress reason="environment">The room in the Trippenhuis where Rembrandt’s Syndics are hanging is open again; coming from
      church yesterday I walked over there for a while,</unstress> hanging right next to the Rembrandt is that
      portrait by Van der Helst. </p>
         <p> Adieu, Theo, a hearty handshake in thought, I wish you the very best, and believe that often
      thinking of you is</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your most loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Herewith a small contribution for your scrapbook, is it coming along? Give my regards to your
      housemates and if someone or other should ask after me.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Dordrecht,</location>
         <date> 23 March 1877</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>Want to make sure you receive a letter on your trip. <unstress reason="family">What a good day we spent together in
      Amsterdam, I stood there watching the train you left in as long as it was still in sight.
      We’re such old friends, aren’t we? How long we’ve walked together, starting in the black
      fields with the young green wheat at Zundert, where we heard the lark at this time of year
      with Pa.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="family">In the morning I went with Uncle Cor to see Uncle Stricker, where we had a long talk about
      youknowwhat. In the evening at half past six Uncle Cor brought me to the station, it was a
      beautiful evening and in everything there was so much that seemed to speak, the weather was
      still and there was a bit of mist in the streets, as is usually the case in London. Uncle had
      toothache that morning, but fortunately it didn’t last, we went to the flower market too, it’s
      good to love flowers and pine branches and ivy and hedges of hawthorn, we have seen them from
      the very beginning.</unstress> Wrote home about how we had spent our time in Amsterdam and what we talked
      about. Arriving here I found a letter from home at Rijken’s. Pa was unable to preach last
      Sunday and the Rev. Kam stood in for him – <stress reason="career">I know that his heart is burning within him that
      something might happen so that I could give myself over not only almost but altogether to
      following Him, Pa always hoped I would do so, oh! may it come to pass, and may there be a
      blessing on it.</stress> The print that you gave me of ‘Heaven and earth shall pass away, but My words
      shall not pass away’ and the portrait of the Rev. Heldring are already hanging in my room, oh,
      <good_health>I’m so glad to have them, they give me hope.</good_health> Am writing to you offhand about my plans; my idea
      becomes clear and firm by doing so. For the time being I’m thinking of the words ‘it is my
      portion to keep Thy word’, have such a desire to familiarize myself with the treasure of
      biblical scripture, to know all those old stories thoroughly and lovingly, especially to learn
      what we know about Christ. In our family, which is indeed a Christian family in the full sense
      of the word, there has always been a minister of the gospel as far back as one can see, from
      generation to generation. <stress reason="career">Why should that voice not be heard in this and in following
      generations? Why should a member of that family not now feel himself called to that office and
      think, with some reason, that he can and must declare himself and seek the means to achieve
      that goal? It is my prayer and deepest desire that the spirit of my Father and Grandfather may
      rest upon me, and that it may be given me to be a Christian and a Christian labourer, that my
      life may resemble that of them whom I name – the more, the better – for behold, that old wine
      is good and I desire not the new.</stress> Their God shall be my God, and their people my people, that
      this may be my portion: to know Christ in His full worth and to be constrained by His love.
      What that Love is, is so beautifully said in the words ‘as sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing’,
      and in 1 Cor. XIII, it beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth
      all things, it never faileth. It is in my heart today, those words of the pilgrims going to
      Emmaus when evening was come and the sun had gone down, ‘But they constrained Him, saying,
      Abide with us’.</p>
         <p>You like it too, that ‘sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing’, keep it in mind, because they are
      good words and a good cloak in the storm of life, keep it in mind at this time, now that
      you’ve experienced so much lately. And be careful, because even though it’s no small thing
      that you’ve experienced, yet, if I see rightly, there is something greater in store, and you
      too will remember the words of the Lord: I have loved thee with an everlasting Love, I will
      comfort you as one whom his mother comforteth. I shall send you another Comforter, even the
      Spirit of truth, I will make a new covenant with you, be separate, and touch not the unclean
      thing, I will be your God, and you shall be My people, I will be a Father unto you, and you
      shall be My sons and daughters. Hate sin and the places where it resides, and come not nigh,
      it attracts so easily with a false appearance of being something great, and does what the
      devil did to Christ when he showed Him all the kingdoms of the earth and their glory and said,
      ‘All these things will I give Thee, if Thou wilt kneel down and worship me’. There is
      something better than the glory of worldly things: it is the feeling we get when our heart
      burns within us upon hearing His word, it is faith in God, the Love of Christ, faith in
      immortality, in a life after this life. Hold fast to what you have. Theo, old boy, brother
      whom I love, <stress reason="career">I have such a great longing for that thing which you know of, but how shall I
      ever get it? How I wish that I, like Pa, had already done a lot of the difficult work of a
      Christian labourer and minister of the gospel and sower of the word.</stress> You see, Pa can count his
      services and Bible readings and visits to the sick and the poor and his written sermons by the
      thousands, and still he doesn’t look back but goes on doing good. Lift up your eyes for me and
      pray that it may be given to me, just as I now do for you, may He give you the desires of
      thine heart, He who knows us better than we know ourselves and who is able to do above all
      that we ask or think, for His ways are higher than our ways and His thoughts are higher than
      our thoughts, as high as the Heaven is above the earth. And may you continue to think of
      Christ as a Comforter and God as a refuge.</p>
         <p>I wish you well on your trip; write soon, and accept a handshake in thought, adieu, and
      believe me ever</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>
            <stress reason="family">May Pa get better soon, try to be in Etten at Easter, things will be all fine once more when
      we’re together again.</stress>
         </p>
         <p>With many things in the past, also with what you’ve experienced, it could be that ‘thou shalt
      find it after many days’.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Nuenen</location>, Wednesday, <date>30 April 1884</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>Many happy returns of the day.</p>
            <p>It really was important news in your last letter — and I think you’ll be glad that
                  the situation has at least become clearer.</p>
            <p>Am really looking forward to your next letter.</p>
            <p>As regards the work, <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’m doing a fairly large painting of a weaver — the loom
                  straight on from the front — the little figure a dark little silhouette against
                  the white wall.</work> 
            <work stage="middle" origin="existing">And at the same time also the one I started in the winter, a loom
                  on which a piece of red cloth is being woven — there the loom is seen from the
                  side. </work>
            <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’ve also started on two others of effects on the heath. And a thing with
                  Pollard birches.</work>
         </p>
            <p>I’ll have a lot more hard graft on those looms — but in reality the things are such
                  almighty beautiful affairs — all that old oak against a greyish wall — that I
                  certainly believe it’s right that they should be painted. We must make sure that
                  we get them so that the colour and tone match with other Dutch paintings, though.
                 <work stage="planned" origin="new"> I hope to start on two more of weavers soon, where the figure will appear very
                  differently, that’s to say where the weaver isn’t sitting behind it but is
                  arranging the threads for the cloth.</work> I’ve seen them weaving by lamplight in the
                  evening, which creates very Rembrandtesque effects. Nowadays they have a sort of
                  hanging lamp — but I’ve just got a little lamp from a weaverlike the one in The
                  evening by Millet, for instance. This is what they used to work by.</p>
            <p>I recently also saw coloured pieces woven in the evening — where I’ll take you
                  sometime should you come here. When I saw it, they were also just arranging the
                  threads, so dark, bowed figures against the light, which stood out against the
                  colour of the piece. Great shadows cast on the white walls by the laths and beams
                  of the loom.</p>
            <p>Regards — do write soon if you can.</p>
      </body>
      <close> Yours truly, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague,</location> 
         <date>Sunday, 5 November 1882.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
            <p>Your letter and its contents were very welcome. A point that will perhaps be
      raised more and more is the one you refer to. People will be forced to recognize that much of
      what’s new, in which people at first thought they saw progress, is indeed less sound than the
      old, and consequently the need will become apparent for strong men to redress the balance.
      Since I believe arguing about this will make no difference to the matter itself, I think it
      quite unnecessary to write more about it.</p> 
         <p>But for my part I can hardly say that I share your
      idea that you express as follows: ‘in my view it’s in the nature of things that the desired
      change will come’. Just think of how many great men have died or... won’t be with us much
      longer — Millet, Brion, Troyon, Rousseau, Daubigny, Corot — and a host of others — are no
      more. Think further back, I say, Leys, Gavarni, Degroux (to name just a few), or still
      further, Ingres, Delacroix, Géricault, think how old it already is, modern art. Add to them
      many who are aged. Nonetheless, there was still progress up to Millet and Jules Breton in my
      view, but as for surpassing these two men, don’t talk to me of that. Their genius may be
      equalled in past, present or later ages, but to surpass them isn’t possible. If one reaches
      that high zone, one is amid an equality of geniuses, but one can’t climb higher than the top
      of the mountain. Israëls, for example, may equal Millet, but with genius there’s no question
      of surpassing or being inferior.</p> 
         <p>Now, though, the top has been reached in art. In the years to
      come we’ll most certainly see splendid things; something more sublime than what we’ve already
      seen — no. And for my part I fear that in a few years there may be a kind of panic, in this
      form: since Millet we have sunk very low — the word decadence, now whispered or pronounced in
      veiled terms (see Herkomer), will then sound like an alarm bell. Many, like I myself, now keep
      quiet, because they already have the reputation of being awkward customers, and talking about
      it doesn’t help. That — namely, talking — isn’t what one needs to do — one must work, though
      with sorrow in the heart. Those who later cry out the loudest about decadence will themselves
      belong to it the most. I repeat: by this shall ye know them, by their work, and it won’t be
      the most eloquent who say the truest things. See Millet himself, see Herkomer, they’re
      certainly not orators, and speak almost reluctantly.</p> 
         <p>Enough of this, in you I find someone who
      understands much about the great men, and I find it delightful to hear things about them now
      and then that I don’t know, like, for example, what you write to me about Daumier. The series
      of portraits of politicians &amp;c., the painting of the 3rd-class carriage, the Revolution —
      I don’t know any of them. Now I haven’t seen them myself through what you say, but in my
      imagination Daumier’s personality has gained in importance as a result. I would rather hear
      talk about such men than about the latest Salon, for example.</p> 
         <p>Now as for what you write about
      Vie Moderne, or rather about a type of paper that Buhot promised you. This is something that
      interests me very much. Do I understand correctly that this paper is such that when one does a
      drawing on it (I assume in autographic ink), this drawing — without using a second draughtsman
      or engraver or lithographer as an intermediary — can be transferred as it is onto a stone, or
      that a print can be made of it, so that any number of impressions can be obtained, the latter
      then being facsimiles of the original drawing? If this is the case, be so good as to give me
      all the information you can find about how one should work on this paper, and do your best to
      send me some of it on which I can do some trials. If I could do my trials before you come,
      then we could discuss what to do with them at that time.</p> 
         <p>I think it possible that within a
      relatively short time there may be a demand for employees for illustration, more so than at
      present. If for my part I fill my portfolios with studies from the models that I can grab or
      catch, I’ll get something to show so that I’ll be eligible, I hope, to be given employment. To
      keep on illustrating, like for example Morin, Lançon, Renouard, Jules Ferat, Worms in their
      day, one must have plenty of ammunition in the form of various studies in different fields.
      I’m trying to gather these together, as you know, and will see in due course. </p>
         <p> By the way, so
      far I have not yet received the packet of studies which you wrote that you had returned
      through rue Chaptal. Could they already have arrived at the Plaats? If you think they have,
      I’ll have them collected, because they’ll be useful to me in connection with things I’ve been
      doing recently. <work origin="new" stage="sketch">Do you know who I drew this morning? Blok the Jewish bookseller, not David but
      the short one who’s on the Binnenhof.</work> I wish I had more from that family, for they are a true
      type. It’s enormously difficult to get the types one would prefer to have — in the meantime
      I’m content to draw what I can get, without losing sight of the others I would draw if I had
      the choice. I’m very pleased with Blok. He reminds me of things from many years ago. I hope
      he’ll come again some other Sunday morning. Naturally, while working one always feels and
      ought to feel a sort of dissatisfaction with oneself, a desire to be able to do it much
      better, but still it’s delightful and enjoyable to gradually assemble all kinds of figures —
      although the more one makes, the more one realizes one needs.</p> 
         <p> One can’t do everything at once,
      but it will be absolutely necessary for me to do a number of horse studies some day, not just
      scratches on the street but with a model for once. I know of an old white horse, a real nag if
      ever there was one (at the gasworks), but the man, who makes the poor animal do all manner of
      heavy jobs and just wants to get what he can out of it, asked a lot for it, namely three
      guilders to come to me for a morning, a daalder at the very least at his place, provided I
      came on Sunday. And when you consider that for what I need, namely 30 strong studies, say, I
      would have to work quite a few mornings, it would cost me too much. But I’ll find a better
      opportunity sometime. I can get a horse much more easily here and there for a very short time,
      these people are sometimes willing to do that, but in a very short time one cannot do what
      really needs to be done, so that’s little help. I try to work quickly, because otherwise it
      just doesn’t pan out, but a study that’s of some use requires at least half an hour, say, so
      one always comes back to actual posing. At Scheveningen, for instance, I’ve occasionally had a
      boy or a man stand still for a moment, as they say, on the beach. The outcome was always a
      great desire on my part for a longer pose, and standing still for a moment isn’t enough for
      me, neither for a person nor for a horse. If I’m correctly informed, the draughtsmen for The
      Graphic whose turn it was always had models at their disposal in a studio at the offices.
      Dickens has some nice things to say about the painters of his age and their wrong way of
      working, namely slavishly and yet only half sticking to the model. He says: Fellows, do
      understand that your model isn’t your ultimate goal but a means for giving body and vigour to
      your ideas and inspiration.</p> 
         <p>Look at the French (Ary Scheffer, for example) and see how much
      better than you they do it. It’s just as if the English listened to him — they continued
      working with models, but they learnt to see the model in a grander and bolder way, and learnt
      to take better advantage of it for sounder and nobler compositions than those of Dickens’s
      painting contemporaries. Two things that remain eternally true and complement each other, in
      my view are: don’t snuff out your inspiration and power of imagination, don’t become a slave
      to the model; and, the other, take a model and study it, for otherwise your inspiration won’t
      take on material form.</p> 
         <p>
            <stress reason="money">When your letter came there were things I had to pay immediately. I
      hope it won’t inconvenience you to send again no later than 10 Nov.</stress> Understand that the
      question of that process Buhot spoke to you about strikes me as being pretty important. I
      would be very pleased if I could learn it, and would like to do my best at it.</p> 
      </body>
      <close>Adieu, with a handshake.</close> 
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent.</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Do you know the effects one sees here early in the morning
      these days? It’s splendid — it’s what Brion painted in the painting in the Luxembourg, The end
      of the flood, namely that band of red light on the horizon with rain-clouds above. This brings
      me to the landscape painters. Compare those of Brion’s time with now. Is it better now than
      then? I doubt it. I’ll gladly acknowledge that they’re much more productive in that field than
      in the past, but although I can’t help admiring what they make now, the old landscapes in a
      more old-fashioned manner always give me pleasure when I see them. There were a few years when
      I walked past a Schelfhout, for example, and thought something like: that’s not worth the
      effort. Yet the new, although it takes someone in, doesn’t always continue to make the same
      strong, moving impression over time, and a naive painting like a Schelfhout or a Ségé, a Jules
      Bakhuyzen, is seen again with vivid pleasure after one has long been looking at newer things.
      I really didn’t deliberately set out to be somewhat disenchanted as regards progress; on the
      contrary, it began to develop unwittingly in my thoughts very much against my will, because as
      time passed I felt more and more a kind of emptiness which I can’t fill with the things being
      made today. While searching for an example, I think of old woodcuts by Jacque that I saw at
      least 10 years ago at C.M.’s. It was a series, The months. They were done in Jacque’s old
      manner, in the manner of those etchings that appeared in annual series, or even more
      old-fashioned. The local tone is less in them than in his later work, but the draughtsmanship
      and a certain terseness are reminiscent of Millet. You see, with the many croquis in the
      present magazines it seems to me that a not entirely unconventional elegance threatens to
      replace that typical, truly rustic quality of which the croquis by Jacque that I mean are an
      example. Might not the cause of this also lie in the lives and characters of the artists? I
      don’t know what your experience is, but do you find many people these days prepared to go for
      a long walk in grey weather, for example? You would do it gladly, and enjoy it too, as I
      would, but for many it would be a chore. Equally, I was struck by the fact that when one talks
      to painters, in most cases, by far, the conversation is not interesting. When he wants, Mauve
      has the power to say something in words so that one sees it, and most certainly others here
      have that too when they want. Yet, that curious fact that when one talks to a painter one
      immediately has a sense of the open air — is it your impression that that’s as strong as it
      used to be? This week I read in Forster, Life of C. Dickens, all kinds of details about long
      walks on Hampstead Heath &amp;c. outside London, the final goal being, for example, to have
      bacon and eggs at an old inn way out in the country. Those walks were very jolly and cheerful,
      but all the same it was usually the case that serious plans for books were made, or else the
      changes Dickens was to make to one character or another were discussed. <stress reason="environment">The present has
      something hectic and harried about it for which I do not care, and it’s just as if death has
      touched everything.</stress> I’d like your expectation ‘that the desired change will come’ to prove
      true, but in my view it isn’t ‘in the nature of things’. Be this as it may, opposing in words
      is a complete side issue, I believe, and what everyone who considers the matter important
      should do in his own circle is to try to make or help to make something. Have been working
      again on women miners carrying sacks of coal in the snow — watercolour. But above all I’ve
      drawn 12 or so studies of figures for it, and 3 heads, and I’m not yet finished. I’ve got the
      effect in the watercolour, I believe, but it isn’t yet strong enough in character for my
      taste. The reality is like Millet’s The gleaners — austere — so you will understand that one
      shouldn’t turn it into a snow effect, which would only be an impression and have no raison
      d’être unless the landscape is the whole point. I think that I’ll start all over again —
      although the studies I have for now may please you — precisely because I was more successful
      with them than with many others. It would be really suitable, I believe, for the Vie Moderne.
      If I get the paper, I already have one of the figures, for example, to do as a trial. But it
      must become a little troop of women, a small caravan.</p>
      </ps> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague,</location> 
         <date>between about Wednesday, 13 and about Monday, 18 December 1882.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
            <p>Though I’ve nothing special to tell you, I wanted to write to you again. As
      against what I wrote to you, that I’m often heavy-hearted about many things, can’t see
      everything as progress, &amp;c., there’s what I also said on a previous occasion: there are
      things that are worth doing one’s best for, either because they gain approval or because, just
      the opposite, they have their own raison d’être. Blessed is he who has found his work, says
      Carlyle, and that’s absolutely true. And as for me, when I say that I want to make figures
      from the people for the people, then it goes without saying that the course of events will
      influence me only indirectly, that is to the extent that my work is made harder or easier, but
      making the drawings themselves is my main preoccupation. And so, as against a feeling of
      dejection, there’s the fact that it’s a delight to work on something that becomes more
      interesting the deeper you get into it.</p> 
         <p>I said in my last letter that I sometimes had a
      feeling of being in a sort of guardhouse or prison, by which I simply mean that there are many
      things I can’t pursue which I would like to — <stress reason="money">they’d only become possible if I could pay for
      them</stress> — but I don’t at all mean by this that I don’t appreciate the present or am discontented.
      Far from it. It’s precisely by doing what is attainable that one has a chance of working one’s
      way up, so be assured that if you ever know of work I could do for the illustrated magazines
      there, I would be happy to do my best for them. When I write: I don’t think the illustrated
      magazines are going about it the right way, that’s no reason for me not to want to work for
      them. It’s just that I fear what I do wouldn’t suit them. If this is due to genuine mistakes,
      I’ll try to correct them, but if it was because of conception or mood in general, there’s
      little I could do about it. <work origin="new" stage="sketch">You’ll have received the drawing in a smaller format</work>, and I repeat
      once more that if you like I’ll make a series in that size to try it out. </p>
         <p>
            <work origin="new" stage="sketch">I now have two more
      drawings —</work> one is a man reading the Bible and the other is a man saying his prayers before his
      midday meal, which is on the table. Both are most decidedly in what one might call an
      old-fashioned sentiment, they are ditto figures as the old man with his head in his hands. The
      grace is the best, I believe, but they complement each other. In the one there’s a view
      through the window of snow-covered furrows. My intention with these two and with the first old
      man is one and the same, namely to express the special mood of Christmas and New Year. At that
      time, in both Holland and in England, there’s still always a religious element, everywhere in
      fact, at least in Brittany and Alsace too. Leaving aside whether or not one agrees with the
      form, it’s something one respects if it’s sincere, and for my part I can fully share in it and
      even feel a need for it, at least in the sense that, just as much as an old man of that kind,
      I have a feeling of belief in something on high even if I don’t know exactly who or what will
      be there. </p>
         <p>I like what Victor Hugo said: religions pass, but God remains. And Gavarni also said
      a fine thing: the point is to grasp what does not pass in what passes. One of the things that
      will not pass is the something on high and belief in God, even if the forms change, a change
      as necessary as the renewal of greenery in the spring. But you will understand from one thing
      and another that my aim in these drawings is not to pay homage to the form but to show that I
      greatly respect the Christmas and New Year sentiment. And if there’s any sentiment or
      expression in it, that’s because I myself share it.</p> 
         <p>What I feel more and more is that it’s
      difficult to discover the best way to work. There’s so much that is fine on the one side, and
      so much on the other side too, moreover so much that is wrong, that sometimes one doesn’t know
      which way to choose. But at all events one must work. Yet for my part I do not think that I
      couldn’t make a mistake, am too aware of many mistakes to be able to say: this or that is the
      right way, that is the wrong one. This goes without saying. But I’m not indifferent, I believe
      it’s wrong to be so, I believe that it’s a duty — even though one knows that one can’t get
      through the world without making mistakes, without remorse or sorrows — to try to do right. I
      once read somewhere, Some good must come by clinging to the right. What do I know of whether
      I’ll attain this or that goal — how can I know in advance whether or not the difficulties will
      be insuperable? One must work on in silence and await the outcome accordingly. If one prospect
      vanishes another will perhaps open up — there must be a prospect and a future too, even though
      its geography is unknown. The conscience is a man’s compass, and although the needle deviates
      sometimes, although above all one detects inaccuracies in one’s orientation, one must
      nevertheless do one’s best to set one’s course by it. </p>
         <p>I must copy out something for you that I
      had in mind when working on that old man, though it doesn’t apply to it literally, since it
      isn’t nighttime in the drawing, for example. Oft, in the stilly night. Oft in the stilly night,
      Ere slumber’s chain has bound me, Fond memory brings the light Of other days around me; The
      smiles, the tears, Of boyhood’s years, The words of love then spoken; The eyes that shone, Now
      dimm’d and gone, The cheerful hearts now broken! Thus, in the stilly night, Ere slumber’s
      chain hath bound me, Sad memory brings the light Of other days around me. Laurillard after
      Moore. When I remember all The friends, so link’d together, I’ve seen around me fall, Like
      leaves in wintry weather; I feel like one Who treads alone Some banquet-hall deserted, Whose
      lights are fled, Whose garlands dead, And all but he departed! Thus, in the stilly night, Ere
      slumber’s chain hath bound me, Sad memory brings the light Of other days around me. <unstress reason="environment">Well, I
      hope that you too will be able to enjoy something of nature in the coming days, either in the
      appearance of the short winter days or in the winter figures.</unstress> For how very different
      passers-by on the street look in winter and in summer.</p> 
         <p>I’ve studied your information as to the
      Buhot paper sent. If you think it advisable for me to do some work on it, I would need a few
      sheets, and I take it that they’re perhaps made in suitable formats so that I can adapt to
      them. This paper is not obtainable here, otherwise I would already have tried it. After
      reading your explanation I’m also left with the question: if one takes a photograph of the
      drawing, and then transfers the photo to zinc, is it only the drawings done on this particular
      paper that are suitable for this, and isn’t it possible to reproduce all drawings in black and
      white, even if they’re on ordinary paper? Also: doesn’t the photographer then have it in his
      power to reduce the format, should the drawing be larger than desirable for the format of the
      magazine? The latter is certainly what I would deduce from some American reproductions that
      appeared in Scribner’s Magazine.</p>
      </body> 
      <close>Well, adieu, I hope you’ll write again towards the twentieth.
      With a handshake in thought.</close>
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Wednesday, <date>2 September 1885</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
        <p>Thanks for your letter and 150 francs enclosed. I also received the two new Lhermittes
            today. He’s a master of the figure. He’s able to do what he likes with it — conceiving
            the whole neither from the colour nor from the local tone, but rather proceeding from
            the light — as Rembrandt did — there’s something astonishingly masterly in everything he
            does — in modelling, above all things, he utterly satisfies the demands of honesty.</p>
        <p>A great deal is said about — Poussin. Bracquemond talks about him, too. The French call
            Poussin their greatest ever painter among the old masters. Well it’s certain that what’s
            said about Poussin, whom I know so very little about, I find in Lhermitte and in Millet.
            But with this distinction, that it seems to me Poussin is the original grain, the others
            are the full ear. For my part, then, I rate today’s superior.<stress reason="environment">This last fortnight I’ve
            had a great deal of trouble with the reverend gentlemen of the priesthood, who gave me
            to understand — of course with the best of intentions and, no less than others,
            believing that it was their duty to interfere — who gave me to understand that I
            shouldn’t be too familiar with people beneath my station — who, having spoken to me in
            those terms, spoke in a very different tone to the ‘people of lower station’, that’s to
            say with threats that they mustn’t allow themselves to be painted.</stress> This time I simply
            went straight to the burgomaster and told him exactly what had happened, and pointed out
            that this was none of the priests’ business and that they should stick to their own
            province of more abstract things. In any event, I’m not encountering any more opposition
            for the time being, and I think it quite possible that that’s how it will remain. A girl
            I’d often painted was having a child and they thought it was mine, although it wasn’t
            me. However, knowing the facts of the matter from the girl herself and it being a case
            in which a member of the priest’s congregation in Nuenen had behaved extremely badly,
            they can’t get their teeth into me, at least not this time. But you see that it isn’t
            easy to paint people at home and draw them as they go about their business. Anyway —
            they won’t easily win in this case, and this winter I do hope to keep the very same
            models, who are of the old Brabant stock through and through.</p>
        <p>
            <work stage="finished" origin="new">Even so, I have a few more new drawings.</work>
         </p>
        <p>But now, in the last few days, I could not get anyone in the fields. Fortunately for me,
            the priest isn’t yet, but is nonetheless beginning to become, quite unpopular. It’s a
            bad business, though, and if it were to continue I’d probably move. You’ll ask what’s
            the point of being a disagreeable person — sometimes you have to be. If I’d discussed it
            meekly they’d have ground me down without mercy. And when they hinder me in my work,
            sometimes the only way I know is an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth. The priest went
            so far as to promise the people money if they didn’t allow themselves to be painted —
            however, the people replied very pertly that they’d rather earn it from me than go cap
            in hand to him. But you see, they only do it for the sake of earning money and I don’t
            get anything done for nothing around here. You ask me whether Rappard has ever sold
            anything. I know he’s flusher at present than before, that for a long time, for
            instance, he had a nude model day after day, that for the purposes of a painting of a
            brickworks he’s now rented a small house actually on the spot and altered it so that he
            had light from above — I know that he’s been on another trip through Drenthe and that
            he’s also going to Terschelling. That all of this is pretty expensive, and the money for
            it has to come from somewhere. That although he may have money of his own, he must be
            earning as well, because otherwise he couldn’t do what he’s doing. It may be that his
            family is buying or friends, that’s possible, but at any rate somebody must be.</p>
        <p>But this evening I’m much too occupied with Lhermitte’s drawings to go on writing any
            more about other things.</p>
        <p>When I think about Millet or about Lhermitte — then — I find modern art as great — as
            Michelangelo and Rembrandt — the old infinite, the new infinite too — the old genius,
            the new genius. Perhaps someone like Chenavard doesn’t see it like this — but for my
            part I’m convinced — that in this regard one can believe in the present.</p>
        <p>The fact that I have a definite belief as regards art also means that I know what I want
            to get in my own work, and that I’ll try to get it even if I go under in the attempt.
        </p>
      </body>
      <close>Regards.Yours truly,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Ramsgate,</location>
         <date> 12 May 1876</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
        <p>Thanks for your letter; I also like ‘Tell me the old, old story’ very much. I first heard
            it sung in Paris, in the evening in a small church I used to attend sometimes. No. 12 is
            also beautiful. I regret not having gone to hear Moody and Sankey when they were in
            London. There’s such a yearning for Religion among the people in those big cities. Many
            a worker in a factory or shop has had a remarkable, pure, pious youth. But city life
            often takes away ‘the early dew of morning’, yet the yearning for ‘the old, old story’
            remains, the bottom of one’s heart remains the bottom of one’s heart. In one of his
            books, Eliot describes the life of factory workers &amp;c. who have joined a small
            community and hold religious services in a chapel in ‘Lantern Yard’, and he says it is
            ‘God’s Kingdom upon earth’, nothing more nor less.</p>
        <p>And there’s something moving about seeing the thousands now flocking to hear those
            evangelists.</p>
        <p>I think your plan to give Pa and Ma ‘After the departure’ by Sadée is very good; that’s
            agreed, then.</p>
        <p>Willemien may be already there on 21 May. I see from your letter that you’re also
            thinking of going. Do it, old boy, if you can manage it. Sometimes such actions receive
            a special blessing. How it would surprise them.</p>
        <p>
            <stress reason="family">There was something wistful in Ma’s last letter, in which she wrote a word or two about
            the necessity of our being so far from home. And Ma’s eyes are hurting her again.</stress>
         </p>
        <p>Come on, old boy, brighten them up again by being there on that day.</p>
        <p>This afternoon Mr Reid sent me the catalogue of the exhibition in London.</p>
        <p>In thought a handshake, and congratulations on the birthdays of Lies and Cor, and also on
            21 May. Regards to everyone at the Rooses’. In haste.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving brother.</close>
      <sig>Vincent.</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Isleworth</location>
         <date>3 November 1876</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>It’s again high time that you heard something from me. <unstress reason="family">Thank God
        you’re recovering,</unstress> I long so much for Christmas – perhaps that time will come
      before we know it, even though it seems a long way off.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="career">Theo, your brother spoke for the first time in God’s house last
        Sunday, in the place where it is written ‘I will give peace in this place’. I’m copying out
        what it was herewith. May it be the first of many.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">It was a clear autumn day and a lovely walk from here to
        Richmond along the Thames, which reflected the large chestnut trees with their load of
        yellow leaves and the clear blue sky, and between the treetops the part of Richmond that
        lies on the hill, the houses with their red roofs and windows without curtains and green
        gardens, and the grey tower above it all, and below, the large grey bridge with tall poplars
        on either side, with people crossing it who looked like small black figures.</unstress>
            <good_health>When I stood in the pulpit I felt like someone emerging from a dark, underground
        vault into the friendly daylight, and it’s a wonderful thought that from now on, wherever I
        go, I’ll be preaching the gospel – to do that well one must have the gospel in his heart,
        may He bring this about.</good_health> God says, Let there be light: and there is light. He
      speaks, and it is done. He commands, and it stands, and it stands fast. Faithful is He that
      calleth us, who also will do it. You know enough of the world, Theo, to see how a poor
      preacher stands rather alone as far as the world is concerned – but He can awaken in us, more
      and more, awareness and firmness of faith. ‘And yet I am not alone, because the Father is with
      me’.I know in Whom my faith is founded,</p>
         <p>Though day and night change constantly,</p>
         <p>I know the rock on which I’m grounded,</p>
         <p>My Saviour waits, unfailingly.</p>
         <p>When once life’s evening overcomes me,</p>
         <p>Worn down by ills and strife always,</p>
         <p>For every day Thou hast allowed me,</p>
         <p>I’ll bring Thee higher, purer praise.Praise, Christian, there on your left hand,</p>
         <p>And on your right, is God –</p>
         <p>When I have no more strength to stand,</p>
         <p>When anguished, there is God –</p>
         <p>When loving hand of faithful friend</p>
         <p>Helps not, there is God –</p>
         <p>In death and agony at life’s end,</p>
         <p>Yes, everywhere is God.How I long for Christmas and to see all of you, old boy, it seems to
      me that I’ve grown years older in these few months.The panting hart, the hunt escapèd,</p>
         <p>Cries no harder for the pleasure</p>
         <p>Of fresh flowing streams of water</p>
         <p>Than my soul doth long for God.</p>
         <p>Yea, my soul thirsts for the Lord,</p>
         <p>God of life, oh when shall I</p>
         <p>Approach Thy sight, and drawing nigh,</p>
         <p>Give Thee praise in Thine own house.Why art thou cast down, my soul,</p>
         <p>Disquieted in me, oh why?</p>
         <p>Foster again the faith of old,</p>
         <p>Rejoice in praising Him most high.</p>
         <p>Oft hath he taken your distress</p>
         <p>And turned it into happiness.</p>
         <p>Hope in Him, eyes heavenward raised,</p>
         <p>For to my God I still give praise.My boy, if illness and difficulties come to meet us, let us
      thank Him for bringing us into these hours – and let us not forget meekness, for it is
      written: On this man will I look, even on him who is poor and sorrowful and who trembleth at
      My word. Yesterday evening I went to Richmond again, and took a walk there on a large common
      surrounded by trees, and houses around it, above which the tower rose. Dew lay on the grass
      and it was growing dark; on one side the sky was still full of the glow of the sun that had
      just set there, on the other side the moon was rising. An old lady (dressed in black) with
      lovely grey hair was walking beneath the trees. In the middle of the common, some boys had lit
      a big fire, which one saw flickering in the distance; I thought of this: when once life’s
      evening overcomes me, worn down by ills and strife always, for every day Thou hast allowed me,
      I’ll bring Thee higher, purer praise. Adieu, a handshake in thought from</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your most loving brother,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Regards to Mr and Mrs Tersteeg, Haanebeeks, Van Stockums and everyone at the Rooses’ and Van
      Iterson and if you should see someone or other whom I know.Your brother was indeed moved when
      he stood at the foot of the pulpit and bowed his head and prayed ‘Abba, Father, let Thy name
      be our beginning’.On Thursday week I hope to speak at Mr Jones’s church: And the Lord added
      daily to the church such as should be saved, on John and Theagenes. </p>
         <p>Psalm 119:19 I am a stranger in the earth, hide not Thy commandments from me.It is an old
      faith and it is a good faith that our life is a pilgrims progress – that we are strangers in
      the earth, but that though this be so, yet we are not alone for our Father is with us. We are
      pilgrims, our life is a long walk, a journey from earth to heaven.</p>
         <p>The beginning of this life is this. There is one who remembereth no more Her sorrow and Her
      anguish for joy that a man is born into the world. She is our Mother. The end of our
      pilgrimage is the entering in Our Fathers house where are many mansions, where He has gone
      before us to prepare a place for us. The end of this life is what we call death – it is an
      hour in which words are spoken, things are seen and felt that are kept in the secret chambers
      of the hearts of those who stand by, it is so that all of us have such things in our hearts or
      forebodings of such things. There is sorrow in the hour when a man is born into the world, but
      also joy – deep and unspeakable – thankfulness so great that it reacheth the highest Heavens.
      Yes the Angels of God, they smile, they hope and they rejoice when a man is born in the world.
      There is sorrow in the hour of death – but there too is joy unspeakable when it is the hour of
      death of one who has fought a good fight. There is One who has said, I am the resurrection and
      the life, if any man believeth in Me, though he were dead, yet shall he live. There was an
      Apostle who heard a voice from heaven, saying: Blessed are they that die in the Lord for they
      rest from their labour and their works follow them. There is joy when a man is born in the
      world but there is greater joy when a Spirit has passed through great tribulation, when an
      Angel is born in Heaven. Sorrow is better than joy – and even in mirth the heart is sad – and
      it is better to go to the house of mourning than to the house of feasts, for by the sadness of
      the countenance the heart is made better. Our nature is sorrowful but for those who have
      learnt and are learning to look at Jesus Christ there is always reason to rejoice. It is a
      good word, that of St Paul: As being sorrowful yet always rejoicing. For those who believe in
      Jesus Christ there is no death and no sorrow that is not mixed with hope – no despair – there
      is only a constantly being born again, a constantly going from darkness into light. They do
      not mourn as those who have no hope – Christian Faith makes life to evergreen life.We are
      pilgrims in the earth and strangers – we come from afar and we are going far. The journey of
      our life goes from the loving breast of our Mother on earth to the arms of our Father in
      heaven. Everything on earth changes – we have no abiding city here – it is the experience of
      everybody: That it is Gods will that we should part with what we dearest have on earth – we
      ourselves, we change in many respects, we are not what we once were, we shall not remain what
      we are now. From infancy we grow up to boys and girls – young men and young women – and if God
      spares us and helps us – to husbands and wives, Fathers and Mothers in our turn, and then,
      slowly but surely the face that once had the ‘early dew of morning’ gets its wrinkles, the
      eyes that once beamed with youth and gladness speak of a sincere deep and earnest sadness –
      though they may keep the fire of Faith, Hope and Charity – though they may beam with Gods
      spirit. The hair turns grey or we loose it – ah – indeed we only pass through the earth, we
      only pass through life – we are strangers and pilgrims in the earth. The world passes and all
      its glory. Let our later days be nearer to Thee and therefore better than these. Yet we may
      not live on just anyhow – no, we have a strife to strive and a fight to fight. What is it we
      must do: We must love God with all our strength, with all our might, with all our heart, with
      all our soul, we must love our neighbour as ourselves. These two commandments we must keep and
      if we follow after these, if we are devoted to this, we are not alone for our Father in Heaven
      is with us, helps us and guides us, gives us strength day by day, hour by hour. and so we can
      do all things through Christ who gives us might. We are strangers in the earth, hide not Thy
      commandments from us. Open Thou our eyes, that we may behold wondrous things out of Thy law.
      Teach us to do Thy will and influence our hearts that the love of Christ may constrain us and
      that we may be brought to do what we must do to be saved.On the road from earth to Heaven</p>
         <p>Do Thou guide us with Thine eye.We are weak but Thou art mighty</p>
         <p>Hold us with Thy powerful hand.Our life, we might compare it to a journey, we go from the
      place where we were born to a far off haven. Our earlier life might be compared to sailing on
      a river, but very soon the waves become higher, the wind more violent, we are at sea almost
      before we are aware of it – and the prayer from the heart ariseth to God: Protect me o God,
      for my bark is so small and Thy sea is so great. The heart of man is very much like the sea,
      it has its storms, it has its tides and in its depths it has its pearls too. The heart that
      seeks for God and for a Godly life has more storms than any other. Let us see how the Psalmist
      describes a storm at sea, He must have felt the storm in his heart to describe it so. We read
      in the 107th Psalm, They that go down to the sea in ships, that do business in great waters,
      these see the works of the Lord and His wonders in the deep. For He commandeth and raiseth up
      a stormy wind which lifteth up the waves thereof. They mount up to Heaven, they go down again
      to the depth, their soul melteth in them because of their trouble. Then they cry unto the Lord
      in their trouble and He bringeth them out of their distresses, He bringeth them unto their
      desired haven.</p>
         <p>Do we not feel this sometimes on the sea of our lives. Does not everyone of you feel with me
      the storms of life or their forebodings or their recollections?</p>
         <p>And now let us read a description of another storm at sea in the New Testament, as we find it
      in the VIth Chapter of the Gospel according to St John in the 17th to the 21st verse. And the
      disciples entered into a ship and went over the sea toward Capernaum. And the sea arose by
      reason of a great wind that blew. So when they had rowed about five and twenty or thirty
      furlongs, they see Jesus walking on the sea and drawing nigh unto the ship and they were
      afraid. Then they willingly received Him into the ship and immediately the ship was at the
      land whither they went. You who have experienced the great storms of life, you over whom all
      the waves and all the billows of the Lord have gone – have you not heard, when your heart
      failed for fear, the beloved well known voice – with something in its tone that reminded you
      of the voices that charmed your childhood – the voice of Him whose name is Saviour and Prince
      of peace, saying as it were to you personally – mind to you personally ‘It is I, be not
      afraid’. Fear not. Let not your heart be troubled. And we whose lives have been calm up to
      now, calm in comparison of what others have felt – let us not fear the storms of life, amidst
      the high waves of the sea and under the grey clouds of the sky we shall see Him approaching
      for Whom we have so often longed and watched, Him we need so – and we shall hear His voice, It
      is I, be not afraid. And if after an hour or season of anguish or distress or great difficulty
      or pain or sorrow we hear Him ask us ‘Dost Thou love me’ then let us say, Lord Thou knowest
      all things, Thou knowest that I love Thee. And let us keep that heart full of the love of
      Christ and may from thence issue a life which the love of Christ constraineth. Lord Thou
      knowest all things, Thou knowest that I love Thee, when we look back on our past we feel
      sometimes as if we did love Thee, for whatsoever we have loved, we loved in Thy name. Have we
      not often felt as a widow and an orphan – in joy and prosperity as well, and more even than
      under grief – because of the thought of Thee.</p>
         <p>Truly our soul waiteth for Thee more than they that watch for the morning – our eyes are up
      unto Thee, o Thou who dwellest in Heavens. In our days too there can be such a thing as
      seeking the Lord.What is it we ask of God – is it a great thing? Yes it is a great thing,
      peace for the ground of our heart, rest for our soul – give us that one thing and then we want
      not much more, then we can do without many things, then can we suffer great things for Thy
      names sake. We want to know that we are Thine and that Thou art ours, we want to be thine – to
      be Christians. We want a Father, a Fathers love and a Fathers approval. May the experience of
      life make our eye single and fix it on Thee. May we grow better as we go on in life.We have
      spoken of the storms on the journey of life, but now let us speak of the calms and joys of
      Christian life. And yet, my dear friends, let us rather cling to the seasons of difficulty and
      work and sorrow, even for the calms are treacherous often.</p>
         <p>The heart has its storms, has its seasons of drooping but also its calms and even its times
      of exaltation. There is a time of sighing and of praying but there is also a time of answer to
      prayer. Weeping may endure for a night but joy cometh in the morning.The heart that is
      fainting</p>
         <p>May grow full to o’erflowing</p>
         <p>And they that behold it</p>
         <p>Shall wonder and know not</p>
         <p>That God at its fountains</p>
         <p>Far off has been raining.My peace I leave with you – we saw how there is peace even in the
      storm. Thanks be to God who has given us to be born and to live in a Christian country. Has
      any of us forgotten the golden hours of our early days at home, and since we left that home –
      for many of us have had to leave that home and to earn their living and to make their way in
      the world. Has He not brought us thus far, have we lacked anything. We believe Lord, help Thou
      our unbelief. I still feel the rapture, the thrill of joy I felt when for the first time I
      cast a deep look in the lives of my Parents, when I felt by instinct how much they were
      Christians. And I still feel that feeling of eternal youth and enthusiasm wherewith I went to
      God, saying ‘I will be a Christian too’. Are we what we dreamt we should be? No – but still –
      the sorrows of life, the multitude of things of daily life and of daily duties, so much more
      numerous than we expected – the tossing to and fro in the world, they have covered it over –
      but it is not dead, it sleepeth. The old eternal faith and love of Christ, it may sleep in us
      but it is not dead and God can revive it in us. But though to be born again to eternal life,
      to the life of Faith, Hope and Charity – and to an evergreen life – to the life of a Christian
      and of a Christian workman be a gift of God, a work of God – and of God alone – yet let us put
      the hand to the plough on the field of our heart, let us cast out our net once more – let us
      try once more – God knows the intention of the spirit, God knows us better than we know
      ourselves for He made us and not we ourselves. He knows of what things we have need, He knows
      what is good for us. May He give His blessing on the seed of His word that has been sown in
      our hearts.</p>
         <p>God helping us, we shall get through life. With every temptation He will give a way to
      escape.</p>
         <p>Father we pray Thee not that Thou shouldest take us out of the world, but we pray Thee to
      keep us from evil. Give us neither poverty nor riches, feed us with bread convenient for us.
      And let Thy songs be our delight in the houses of our pilgrimage. God of our Fathers be our
      God: may their people be our people, their Faith our faith. We are strangers in the earth,
      hide not Thy commandments from us but may the love of Christ constrain us. Entreat us not to
      leave Thee or to refrain from following after Thee. Thy people shall be our people, Thou shalt
      be our God.Our life is a pilgrims progress. I once saw a very beautiful picture, it was a
      landscape at evening. In the distance on the right hand side a row of hills appearing blue in
      the evening mist. Above those hills the splendour of the sunset, the grey clouds with their
      linings of silver and gold and purple. The landscape is a plain or heath covered with grass
      and heather, here and there the white stem of a birch tree and its yellow leaves, for it was
      in Autumn. Through the landscape a road leads to a high mountain far far away, on the top of
      that mountain a city whereon the setting sun casts a glory. On the road walks a pilgrim, staff
      in hand. He has been walking for a good long while already and he is very tired. And now he
      meets a woman, a figure in black that makes one think of St Pauls word ‘As being sorrowful yet
      always rejoicing’. That Angel of God has been placed there to encourage the pilgrims and to
      answer their questions:And the pilgrim asks her: Does the road go uphill then all the way?</p>
         <p>and the answer is: ‘Yes to the very end’ –</p>
         <p>and he asks again: And will the journey take all day long?</p>
         <p>and the answer is: ‘From morn till night my friend’. And the pilgrim goes on sorrowful yet
      always rejoicing – sorrowful because it is so far off and the road so long. Hopeful as he
      looks up to the eternal city far away, resplendent in the evening glow, and he thinks of two
      old sayings he has heard long ago – the one is:‘There must much strife be striven</p>
         <p>There must much suffering be suffered</p>
         <p>There must much prayer be prayed</p>
         <p>And then the end will be peace.’and the other:The water comes up to the lips</p>
         <p>But higher comes it not.And he says, I shall be more and more tired but also nearer and
      nearer to Thee. Has not man a strife on earth? But there is a consolation from God in this
      life. An angel of God, comforting men – that is the Angel of Charity. Let us not forget Her.
      And when everyone of us goes back to daily things and daily duties, let us not forget – that
      things are not what they seem, that God by the things of daily life teacheth us higher things,
      that our life is a pilgrims progress and that we are strangers in the earth – but that we have
      a God and Father who preserveth strangers, and that we are all bretheren.</p>
         <p>Amen.And now the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, our Father, and the
      fellowship of the Holy Ghost, be with us for evermore.</p>
         <p>Amen.(Reading Scripture Psalm XCI)Tossed with rough winds and faint with fear,</p>
         <p>Above the tempest soft and clear</p>
         <p>What still small accents greet mine ear</p>
         <p>‘’t Is I, be not afraid.’’t Is I, who washed thy spirit white;</p>
         <p>’t Is I, who gave thy blind eyes sight,</p>
         <p>’t Is I, thy Lord, thy life, thy light,</p>
         <p>’t Is I, be not afraid.These raging winds, this surging sea</p>
         <p>Have spent their deadly force on me</p>
         <p>They bear no breath of wrath to Thee</p>
         <p>’t Is I, be not afraid.This bitter cup, I drank it first</p>
         <p>To thee it is no draught accurst</p>
         <p>The hand that gives it thee is pierced</p>
         <p>‘’t Is I, be not afraid’.When on the other side thy feet,</p>
         <p>Shall rest, mid thousand welcomes sweet;</p>
         <p>One well known voice thy heart shall greet –</p>
         <p>’t Is I, be not afraid.Mine eyes are watching by thy bed</p>
         <p>Mine arms are underneath thy head</p>
         <p>My blessing is around Thee shed</p>
         <p>‘’t Is I, be not afraid’.Again, a handshake in thought – yesterday evening I was at Turnham
      Green in place of Mr Jones, who wasn’t well. I walked over there with the oldest boy, 17 years
      old, but he’s as big as I am and has a beard. He’ll go into business later, his father has a
      large factory; he has a good, honest, feeling heart and a great need of religion, it is his
      hope and desire to do good among the workers later on in life, I recommended ‘Felix Holt’ by
      Eliot to him. <good_health>It was lovely in the park with the old elm trees in the moonlight
        and the dew on the grass. It was so good for me to speak in the little church, it is a
        little wooden church.</good_health> Goodbye, Theo. Goodbye, old boy, I hope I’ve written it
      so that you’ll be able to read it. Remain steadfast and do get well soon.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>between Monday, 16 August and Wednesday, 1 September 1875.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Thanks for your last letter and for the poem by Rückert. On Sunday I went
  again to Mr Bersier, his sermon was based on the text ‘It is not lawful for thee’, he concluded
  with ‘Happy are they for whom life has all its thorns’. Here are some words which I know Uncle
  Vincent is very fond of: ‘Rejoice, young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the
  days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know
  thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgement. Remove sorrow from thy heart,
  and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth are vanity. Remember now thy Creator in
  the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say,
  I have no pleasure in them.’ <unstress reason="environment">Yet I find even more beautiful</unstress>: ‘Fear God, and keep his commandments:
  for this is the whole duty of man.’ And ‘Thy will be done’ and ‘Lead us not into temptation, but
  deliver us from evil’.</p> 
         <p>Herewith a note for Mr Tersteeg, asking him if he would frame 2 engravings,
  ‘Good Friday’ and ‘St Augustine’, which you’ll find in the next crate. And will you please be so
  kind as to send them to Helvoirt around 10 Sept. I’d really like them to be from both of us, so
  that you pay 2.50 guilders towards the frames. I told Mr Tersteeg that you’d write and tell me
  what they cost and then I’d send him the money. You can give me the 2.50 guilders when we see each
  other. That probably won’t be before Christmas; I believe it’s better not to ask for any time off
  before then. <unstress reason="friendship">This evening I’m going to dine with Mr Hamman</unstress>.</p>
      </body> 
      <close>Adieu, write again soon, and believe me</close>
      <sig>Your loving brother Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>Monday, 11 October 1875.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Thanks for your letter of this morning. This time I’d like to write to you as
  I seldom do; I’d actually like to tell you in detail about my life here. As you know, I live in
  Montmartre. Also living here is a young Englishman, an employee of the firm, 18 years old, the son
  of an art dealer in London, who will probably enter his father’s firm later on. He had never been
  away from home and was tremendously boorish, especially the first few weeks he was here; he ate,
  for example, mornings, afternoons and evenings 4-6 sous worth of bread (bread, nota bene, is cheap
  here) and supplemented that with pounds of apples and pears &amp;c. In spite of all that he’s as
  lean as a pole, with two strong rows of teeth, large red lips, sparkling eyes, a couple of large,
  usually red, jug-ears, a shorn head (black hair) &amp;c. &amp;c. I assure you, an altogether
  different creature from that lady by Philippe de Champaigne. This young person was ridiculed a lot
  in the beginning, even by me. But I nonetheless warmed to him gradually and now, I assure you, <good_health>I’m
  very glad of his company in the evenings</good_health>. He has a completely naїve and unspoiled heart, and works
  very hard in the firm. <unstress reason="friendship">Every evening we go home together, eat something or other in my room, and
  the rest of the evening I read aloud, usually from the Bible. We intend to read it all the way
  through. In the morning, he’s already there to wake me up, usually between 5 and 6 o’clock; we
  then have breakfast in my room and go to the gallery around 8 o’clock.</unstress>
         </p> 
         <p>Recently he’s begun to eat with more moderation, and he’s started to collect prints, with my help. <unstress reason="environment">Yesterday we went to the
  Luxembourg together and I showed him the paintings I like best there.</unstress> And truthfully, unto babes
  is revealed much that is hidden from the wise. J. Breton, Alone, The blessing of the corn, Calling
  the gleaners Brion, Noah, The pilgrims of St Odile. Bernier, Fields in winter Cabat. The pond and
  Autumnal evening Emile Breton, Winter evening. Bodmer, Fontainebleau Duverger, The labourer and
  his children Millet, The church at Gréville Daubigny, Spring and Autumn Français, The end of
  winter and The cemetery Gleyre, Lost illusions and Hébert, Christ in the Garden of Olives and
  Malaria, also Rosa Bonheur, Ploughing &amp;c. Also a painting by ? (I can’t remember his name), a
  monastery where monks receive a stranger and suddenly notice that it is Jesus. Written on the wall
  of the monastery is L’homme s’agite et Dieu le mène. </p>
         <p>Qui vous reçoit, me recoit et qui Me reçoit, reçoit celui qui m’a envoyé. <unstress reason="environment">
  At the gallery I simply do whatever the hand finds to do, that is our work our whole life long, old boy, may I 
  do it with all my might.</unstress> Have you done what I advised you to do, have you got rid of the books by Michelet, 
  Renan &amp;c? I believe it will give you peace. You certainly won’t forget that page from Michelet about that portrait of a lady by P. de
  Champaigne, and don’t forget Renan either, but still, get rid of them. ‘If you have found honey,
  see to it that you don’t eat too much of it, lest it disagree with you’ it says in Proverbs, or
  something to that effect. Do you know Erckmann-Chatrian, Le conscrit, Waterloo, and especially
  L’ami Fritz and also Madame Thérèse? Read them some time if you can get hold of them.</p> 
         <p>A change of fare whets the appetite (provided we take especial care to eat simply; not for nothing is it
  written ‘Give us this day our daily bread’), and the bow cannot always stay bent. You won’t take
  it amiss if I tell you to do one thing and another. I know you have your wits about you as well.
  Do not think everything good, and learn to distinguish for yourself between relative good and
  evil; and let that feeling show you the right way with guidance from above because, old boy, it’s
  so necessary ‘that God dispose us’.</p>
      </body> 
      <close>Do write again soon with some particulars, give my regards to
  my acquaintances, especially Mr Tersteeg and his family, and I wish you the very best.</close> 
      <sig>Adieu, believe me ever, Your loving brother Vincent</sig> 
   </letter>
   <letter> 
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>Monday, 7 February 1876.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>My hearty congratulations to you on the occasion of Pa’s birthday. It’s a
  beautiful text, the one for 8 February: Faithful is He that calleth you, who also will do it. What
  that it will be for our Father and for us we do not know, but in a sense we can leave that to Him
  whose name is ‘Our Father’ and ‘I am that I am’.</p> 
         <p>Today I received a letter in reply to one of
  mine; they asked whether I could teach French, German and drawing, and also requested a portrait.
  I’ll answer today; if I hear more I’ll write to you directly. Thanks for the little book by
  Andersen, I’m glad to have it. It’s for reading aloud to a Dutchman, <unstress reason="friendship">one of the employees I’ve
  been seeing a lot of lately.</unstress> Yesterday I went to an English church here, it was a nice experience
  to attend such an English service again, which has much that is simple and beautiful. </p>
         <p>The sermon
  was on ‘The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want. He maketh me to lay down in green pastures, He
  leadeth me gently by still waters. He restoreth my soul and leadeth me in the paths of
  righteousness. Though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death I shall fear no evil for
  Thou art with me, Thy rod and Thy staff they comfort me. Surely Goodness and Mercy shall surround
  me all the days of my life, and I shall dwell in the House of the Lord for ever.’ Thanks again for
  the little book by Andersen, and in thought a handshake, and regards to everyone at the Rooses’.</p>
      </body>
      <close>I heard from home that Mr Tersteeg had been in Etten. In haste. </close>
      <sig>Ever,Your loving brother. Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>Wednesday, 2 February 1876.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Would you do me a great favour? You know that 15-cent edition of ‘Andersen’s
  vertellingen van de maan’, translated by the Rev. Ten Kate. Could you send me a copy of it when
  you get the chance? It’s only tomorrow that a crate will be going to The Hague in which I’ll
  enclose the packages in question. The one for Pa can no longer arrive at Etten in time, but send
  it as soon as possible anyway. <stress reason="friendship">I still haven’t had a reply to various letters I wrote in response
  to advertisements. Nor did Uncle Vincent answer me.</stress> I asked Mr Obach whether any people desiring
  information about me could apply to him, and His Hon. replied with a very kind letter. At any
  rate, old boy, we can only continue quietly with our eyes on Him whom we think of when we say ‘Who
  will shew us any good?’</p> 
      </body>
      <close>Adieu, regards to anyone who might ask after me, and ever</close>
      <sig>Your loving brother. Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>Wednesday, 6 October 1875.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Even though I wrote to you only recently, I want to do so again anyway,
  because I know how difficult life can sometimes be. <unstress reason="friendship">Keep your chin up, old boy, after rain comes
  sunshine, just keep hoping for that.</unstress> Rain and sunshine alternate on ‘the road that goes uphill all
  the way, yes to the very end’, and from time to time one also rests on ‘the journey that takes the
  whole day long, from morn till night’. So think now and often after this, that ‘this also will
  pass away’. And especially, you too should ask: Create in me a new heart, O God; and renew a right
  spirit within me.</p>
         <p>Today I had the opportunity to send a package to Anna and Willemien. Among other
  things I sent her L’imitation de Jesus Christ and several books of the Bible, published
  separately, in the same edition as the Psalms I sent you. Read them faithfully. Would you perhaps
  like the 4 Gospels and some of the epistles, printed separately? I also sent Anna several prints –
  including Rembrandt, Reading the Bible and The supper at Emmaus (an old engraving, by De Frey, I
  believe), Philippe de Champaigne, Portrait of a lady, a large, beautiful etching after Chaigneau,
  Shepherdess and sheep, and then Dupré, Evening, Troyon, Morning, Bodmer, Fontainebleau, Français,
  Last fine days, Frère, Seamstresses, and A cooper, Daubigny, After sunset, &amp;c. &amp;c., as
  well as a couple of photos, namely of Delaroche, Gethsemane No. 424, Good Friday and Mater
  Dolorosa and Brion, The farewells. I hope so much that things will continue to go well for Anna
  there. She keeps up her courage, I know so well that she sometimes finds things so difficult. And
  yet ‘one has one’s good days’ as Jules Dupré often said, let’s go on believing that. </p>
         <p>I’d very much like to have the Dutch hymns. When you get the opportunity, do you think you could manage to send
  the cheapest edition that can be found? I have the Psalms. There are also some beautiful English
  hymns, including this one: </p>
         <p>Thy way not mine, o Lord However dark it be, Lead me by thine own hand
  Choose out the path for me. I dare not choose my lot; I would not if I might; Choose Thou for me,
  my God, So shall I walk aright. The kingdom that I seek, Is thine; so let the way That leads to it
  be thine Else I must surely stray. Choose Thou for me my friend My sickness, or my health; Choose
  Thou my cares for me, My poverty my wealth. Not mine, not mine, the choice In things or great or
  small Be Thou my Guide my strength My wisdom and my all and the following: Nearer my God to Thee
  Nearer to Thee! E’en though it be a cross That raiseth me; Still all my song shall be Nearer my
  God to Thee Nearer to Thee. Though like a wanderer, The sun gone down, Darkness come over me My
  rest a stone; Yet in my dreams I’d be Nearer, my God, to Thee Nearer to Thee! There let my way
  appear Steps unto Heaven; All that Thou sendest me In mercy given Angels to beckon me Nearer, my
  God, to Thee Nearer to Thee. Oft in sorrow and in woe Onward, Christians, onward go; Fight the
  fight, maintain the strife, Strengthen’d with the bread of life. Let your drooping hearts be glad;
  March in heavenly armour clad: Fight, nor think the battle long, Soon shall vict’ry tune your song
  Let not sorrow dim your eye, Soon shall ev’ry tear be dry; Let not fear your course impede, Great
  your strength, if great your need!</p>
      </body>
      <close>Give my regards to my acquaintances. How is Caroline van Stockum? Give my special regards to her, and believe me</close>
      <sig>Your most loving brother Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="friendship">Does the road go uphill then all the way? ‘Yes to the very end’. And will the journey take all day long?
  ‘From morn till night, my friend’.</unstress>
         </p> 
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>13 August 1875</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>I had wanted to write to you earlier. I’m glad that Pa has accepted the call
  to Etten; under the circumstances I also think it good that Willemien is going along with Anna.
  I’d also have liked to be with all of you that Sunday at Helvoirt; <unstress reason="friendship"> have I already told you that I
  was with Soek and his family at Ville-d’Avray that day?</unstress> I was surprised to find 3 paintings by
  Corot in the church there. </p>
         <p> On Sunday last and Sunday a fortnight ago I went to Mr Mercier’s church
  and heard him speak on ‘all things work together for good to them that love God’ (in Dutch it says
  ‘for those who love God all things will work together for good’) and on ‘He created man in his own
  image’, <unstress reason="environment">it was glorious and grand.</unstress> You should also go to church every Sunday if you can, even if
  it isn’t so very beautiful; do that, you won’t regret it.</p>
         <p> Have you ever been to hear the Rev.
  Zubli? In the list of what I have hanging in my room I forgot: N. Maes The nativity Hamon ‘If I
  were sombre winter’ Ed. Frère The seamstresses ditto A cooper Français Last fine day Ruipérez The
  imitation of Jesus Christ Bosboom Cantabimus and psallemus I’m doing my best to find another
  engraving of ‘Rembrandt, Reading the Bible’ for you, perhaps I’ll be sending it to you in the
  first crate of paintings.</p> 
         <p>Have I sent you a lithograph of Troyon, Morning effect? Français, Last
  fine days? If not, write and tell me; I have two of each.</p>
      </body>
      <close>And now, I wish you well, do right and
  don’t look back, as much as you can, and believe me ever</close> 
      <sig>Your loving brother Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Please give my regards to Mr and Mrs Tersteeg and Mauve, also my regards to the Van Stockums, 
  Haanebeeks, Aunt Fie, Rooses, &amp;c. What do you think about our Anna?</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles</location>
         <date>18 December 1888</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>Yesterday Gauguin and I went to Montpellier to see the museum there, and especially the
            Bruyas room — there are many portraits of Bruyas, by Delacroix, by Ricard, by Courbet,
            by Cabanel, by Couture, by Verdier, by Tassaert, by others too. After that there are
            paintings by Delacroix, Courbet, Giotto, Paul Potter, Botticelli, T. Rousseau, very
            fine.</p>
         <p>Bruyas was a benefactor to artists, and this is all I’ll say to you: in the Delacroix
            portrait, he’s a gentleman with a beard, red hair, who looks damnably like you or me,
            and who made me think of that poem by Musset... everywhere I touched the earth, an
            unfortunate man dressed in black came to sit beside us, a man who looked at us like a
            brother. It would have the same effect on you, I’m sure.</p>
         <p> I’d really ask you to go and see, at that bookshop where they sell lithographs of ancient
            and modern artists, if you could manage to get the lithograph after Delacroix’s ‘Tasso
            in the madhouse’ without great expense, since it would seem to me that this figure (by
            Delacroix) must have some relationship to this fine Bruyas portrait. </p>
         <p>They have other Delacroixs there, a study of a mulatto woman (which Gauguin once copied),
            the Odalisques, Daniel in the lions’ den.</p>
         <p>By Courbet, first, The village girls, magnificent, a nude woman seen from the back, another
            on the ground, in a landscape. Second, The woman spinning (superb), and a whole load
            more Courbets. Anyway, you must know that this collection exists, or else know people
            who have seen it, and consequently be able to talk about it. So I shan’t insist on the
            museum (except for the Barye drawings and bronzes!)</p>
         <p>Gauguin and I talk a lot about Delacroix, Rembrandt &amp;c.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="friendship">The discussion is excessively electric. We sometimes emerge from it with tired minds, like
            an electric battery after it’s run down.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>We’ve been right in the midst of magic, for as Fromentin says so well, Rembrandt is above
            all a magician and Delacroix a man of God, of God’s thunder and bugger off in the name
            of God. </p>
         <p>I’m writing this to you with reference to our friends, the Dutchmen De Haan and Isaäcson,
            who have so sought and loved Rembrandt, in order to encourage you to pursue the
            researches.</p>
         <p>One mustn’t get discouraged about that. You know the strange and superb portrait of a man
            by Rembrandt at the La Caze gallery, I told Gauguin that, for me, I saw in it a certain
            family or racial resemblance to Delacroix, or to him, Gauguin.</p>
         <p>I don’t know why, but I always call that portrait ‘the traveller’ or ‘the man coming from
            far away’.</p>
         <p>That’s an equivalent and parallel idea to what I’ve already told you, always to look at the
            portrait of old Six. The fine portrait with the glove for your future, and the Rembrandt
            etching, Six reading by a window in a ray of sunlight, for your past and your
            present.</p>
         <p>That’s the stage we’re at.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="friendship">Gauguin said to me this morning, when I asked him how he felt: ‘that he could feel his old
            self coming back’, which gave me great pleasure.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>
            <bad_health>As for me, coming here last winter, tired and almost fainting mentally, I too suffered a
            little inside before I was able to begin to remake myself.</bad_health>
         </p>
         <p>How I’d like you to see that museum in Montpellier some day, there are some really
            beautiful things there!</p>
         <p>Say so to Degas, that Gauguin and I have been to see the portrait of Bruyas by Delacroix at
            Montpellier, for we must boldly believe that what is, is, and the portrait of Bruyas by
            Delacroix resembles you and me like a new brother.</p>
         <p>As regards setting up a life with painters as pals, you see such odd things and I’ll end
            with what you always say, time will tell.</p>
         <p>You can tell all this to our friends Isaäcson and De Haan, and even boldly read them this
            letter, I would already have written to them if I’d felt the necessary electric
            force.</p>
         <p>On behalf of Gauguin as well as myself, a good, hearty handshake to you all.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>If you think that Gauguin or I have a facility in our work, the work isn’t always
            accommodating. And for the Dutchmen not to get discouraged in their difficulties any
            more than we do, that’s what I wish for them, and for you too.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Isleworth</location>
         <date>10 November 1876.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>I feel the need to enclose a few words to you. You’ll be having pleasant days at home, I
      almost envy you, old boy.</p>
         <p>What lovely autumn weather we’re having. You probably see the sun rising in the morning too.
      Which room are you sleeping in?</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">If you can get ‘The imitation of Christ’ one of these days, read some of it, it’s a wonderful
      book, one that’s very enlightening. It describes so beautifully, for the one who wrote the
      book did it himself, how good it is to wage the holy war of devotion to one’s duty, and the
      heartfelt joy that is to be found in doing good deeds and in doing what one does well.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>You must read the letter for Pa and Ma sometime, <unstress reason="environment">I’ve taken such lovely walks recently, which
      were especially good after the anxiety of the first months here.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>It is indeed true that every day has its own evil and its own good, too. But how terrible
      life must be, especially later on – when the evil of each day increases as far as the things
      of the world are concerned – if it isn’t supported and comforted by faith. And in Christ all
      things of the world can improve and become sanctified, as it were. These are beautiful words,
      and happy are those who come across them, ‘Nothing pleaseth me but in Christ, and in Him all
      things please me’. But one doesn’t achieve this all of a sudden. But he that seeketh
      findeth.</p>
         <p>Do write a few words again the next time Pa and Ma write. I hope to go to Richmond again on
      Monday evening and to take the words: But when he was yet a great way off, his Father saw him,
      and had compassion.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="career">Theo, woe is me if I don’t preach the gospel, and if I didn’t have my sight fixed on that and
      didn’t have hope and faith in Christ, then I would only have woe.</unstress>
            <good_health>Now, however, I have a bit
      of spirit as well.</good_health>
         </p>
         <p>I should have liked you to be in the little church at Turnham Green last Thursday evening; I
      walked over there with the oldest boy in the school and told him several of Andersen’s fairy
      tales, including ‘The story of a mother’.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">And now we’re slowly heading towards winter, and many dread it, but Christmas is wonderful,
      it’s like the moss on the roofs and like the pine and the holly and the ivy in the snow.</unstress> How
      I’d like to come with Anna, may she find something soon, I’ll write to her again today.</p>
         <p>Today one of the maids left, they don’t have it easy here and she couldn’t stand it any
      longer – indeed, everyone, richer or poorer, stronger or weaker, has moments when he can go no
      further, when ‘all these things seem to be against us’, when much of what we have built
      collapses.</p>
         <p>
            <good_health>And yet, one mustn’t lose heart, Elijah had to pray all of seven times, and David had ashes
      on his head many a time.</good_health>
         </p>
         <p>There’s a new assistant teacher at the school, because I’ll have to work more at Turnham
      Green from now on. He has never been away from home before, and won’t find it easy in the
      beginning.</p>
         <p>And now a handshake in thought, it’s already late and I’m rather tired. I wish you well. Do
      think now and then of</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your most loving and affectionate brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>

      <head>
         <location>Ramsgate,</location>
         <date> 31 May 1876</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>Bully for you, being in Etten on 21 May, happily there were 4 of the 6 at home. Pa wrote to
      me in detail about everything that happened that day. Thanks, too, for your last letter.</p>
         <p>Have I already written to you about the storm I saw recently? The sea was yellowish,
      especially close to the beach; a streak of light on the horizon and, above this, tremendously
      huge dark grey clouds from which one saw the rain coming down in slanting streaks. The wind
      blew the dust from the small white path on the rocks into the sea and tossed the blossoming
      hawthorn bushes and wallflowers that grow on the rocks.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">On the right, fields of young green wheat, and, in the
        distance, the town with its towers, mills, slate roofs and houses built in Gothic style,
        and, below, the harbour between the 2 jetties running out into the sea, looking like the
        cities Albrecht Dürer used to etch. I also saw the sea last Sunday night, everything was
        dark grey, but day was beginning to break on the horizon. It was still very early, and yet a
        lark was already singing. And the nightingales in the gardens on the seafront. In the
        distance the light of the lighthouse, the guardship &amp;c.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>That same night I looked out of the window of my room onto the roofs of the houses one sees
      from there and the tops of the elms, dark against the night sky. Above those roofs, one single
      star, but a nice, big friendly one. <stress reason="family">And I thought of us all, and I
        thought of the years of my life that had already passed, and of our home, and the words and
        feeling came to me, ‘Keep me from being a son that causeth shame, give me Your blessing, not
        because I deserve it, but for my Mother’s sake. Thou art Love, beareth all things. Without
        your constant blessing we can do nothing.’</stress>
         </p>
         <p>Herewith a little drawing of the view from the school window where the boys stand and watch
      their parents going back to the station after a visit. Many a boy will never forget the view
      from that window. <unstress reason="environment">You should have seen it this week when we had rainy days, especially in the
      twilight when the streetlamps are being lit and their light is reflected in the wet
      street.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>Mr Stokes was sometimes moody during those days, and when the boys were too boisterous for
      him it sometimes happened that they didn’t get their bread and tea in the evening. You should
      have seen them then, standing at the window looking out, it was really rather sad. They have
      so little apart from their food and drink to look forward to and to get them through the day.
      I’d also like you to see them going down the dark stairs and small corridor to table. On that,
      however, the friendly sun shines.</p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">Another extraordinary place is the room with the rotten floor where there are 6 basins at
      which they wash themselves, with only a feeble light falling onto the washstand through a
      window with broken panes. It’s quite a melancholy sight, to be sure. How I’d like to spend or
      to have spent a winter with them, to know what it’s like.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>The youngsters are making an oil stain on your little drawing, forgive them. Herewith a few
      words for Uncle Jan. </p>
         <p>And now goodnight, if anyone should ask after me bid them goodday. Do you still visit
      Borchers once in a while? Give him my regards if you see him, and also Willem Valkis and
      everyone at the Rooses’. A handshake in thought from</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Thursday, <date>6 August 1885</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>
            <stress reason="family">What very much distresses me in our conversation is that when I say that I fear it will be
      tight for you this year, you reply: ‘that you observe that I’d like to see that’, ‘that you
      see very well that you can’t rely on me’, ‘that you know very well that I would be returning
      you no thanks for your pains’. This is not so, and it distresses me that this is how you see
      it.</stress>
            <stress reason="money"/>
         </p>
         <p>My suggestion has been this — don’t regard my little painting business as dead weight and
      don’t treat it harshly, for the reason that it could prove to be a little boat in a disaster
      when the big ship is lost. My suggestion is and remains — let’s at any rate keep that little
      boat in good condition and ready to sail, whether the storm comes or my anxiety proves to be
      unfounded. At the moment I’m a little vessel which you have in tow and once in a while can
      only seem to you to be dead weight. Which, by the way — as dead weight — you can leave behind
      by cutting the rope if you want to. But in this case I, who am the skipper of my small craft,
      ask that far from having the towrope cut, my little craft should be caulked and provisioned so
      that it may do better service in time of need.</p>
         <p>Should you doubt the good faith of this request, then for my part I can do nothing but repeat
      it more emphatically. <stress reason="money">For I notice that on the side of the paint bill, my own little craft is
      springing leaks here and there.</stress>
         </p>
         <p>
            <good_health>I’m plugging these leaks as much as I can, though, and am not yet losing my coolheadedness.
      Am not desperate either.</good_health> But since we’ll perhaps both be in the same storm, I speak
      emphatically and, I believe, in both our interests.</p>
         <p>I can sum up your answer to my question thus: ‘there may be a storm coming but, even in that
      case, don’t count on either caulking or provisions, and be aware that I may be compelled by
      the force of circumstances to cut the towrope’.I can take this answer as a warning, but only
      in so far as it’s not accompanied by suspicion of my good faith.</p>
         <p>But — by means of this letter I cry out to you again that my request for reinforcement may
      prove to be in both our interests, and I’m not doing it just out of selfishness, as you
      assume. <stress reason="money">That in the event of a storm, I in all events am willing but perhaps also able to be
      of some use and service to you, but that this will be impossible in the event that my own
      craft fills with water (which I’m trying to prevent, though) before the moment in question.
      I’m trying to prevent that myself, though, but still I wouldn’t cry out to you without
      necessity. I’m not afraid in the face of danger either, but nonetheless I try to be prepared
      in case disaster strikes.</stress>
         </p>
         <p>If it seems to you unfounded that I urge that we should gradually let my, but I would rather
      say our little painting business become the heart of a business that we could go on to
      undertake together, <unstress reason="career">for my part I insist that it can and will become something if we can
      remain sufficiently united.</unstress>If I don’t have the same ideas as you, don’t suspect me of bad
      faith or base intentions anyway, either towards you or towards those at home. I do nothing to
      those at home that I have no right to do, since I absolutely and always keep out of their
      affairs. Don’t ask for or urge advice, keep entirely to my own territory — and even keep my
      feelings about their affairs to myself too, since we don’t understand one another’s interests
      anyway.</p>
         <p>And to you I speak now, and will go on speaking, as someone whose business is in paintings to
      someone else whose business is in paintings, and I will not intrude on the other
      territory.</p>
         <p>And the question that I started to discuss with you is this: even if the slump is severe, and
      even if we both have to take great trouble, we must see to it that we keep an energetic hand
      on the little painting business that belongs to you as well as to me. I say, it might be a
      boat that could possibly be of service to you in the storm, although I wish for the storm as
      little as you can wish for it.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Regards,Yours truly,</close>
      <sig>Vincent </sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague,</location> 
         <date>on or about Wednesday, 11 April 1883.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>Dear brother,</salutation> 
      <body>
        <p>Thank you for your letter and the 50 francs enclosed, which were very welcome
    as always, both the former and the latter. I read what you write about your patient with
    interest. I understand that you’re in two minds over the matter of posing a certain question —
    which I shan’t further define here — now or later. And the change of circumstances brought about
    by her recovery has a more or less critical side because, and this is what you are actually
    prepared for (and say so yourself), opposition may be aroused — possibly anyway — let’s hope
    not. How odd that last point really is. One sees what one does as simple and natural in itself —
    something self-evident — one is more or less puzzled as to why others don’t find the motives in
    themselves that compel someone to do such a thing. And would almost draw the conclusion that
    some people have cauterized certain sensory nerves in themselves — in particular those
    collectively known as the conscience. Anyway, I pity such people: in my view they travel through
    life without a compass. Love of one’s fellow man is something one would expect to be able to
    take for granted in everyone as the basis of just about everything. But some believe there are
    better foundations. I feel little curiosity about them.</p> 
         <p>This old foundation that has been tested
    and found good for so many centuries is enough for me. Don’t you find this nicely put? — it’s
    from Les misérables: If Caesar had given me Glory and war, And if I was forced to forgo My
    mother’s love, To great Caesar would I say, Take back your sceptre and your chariot, I love my
    mother more, hey!, I love my mother more. In the context in which this (a student song from the
    time of the revolution of ’30) occurs, love of my mother stands for love of the Republic, or
    rather ‘love of mankind’; in other words, quite simply, universal brotherhood. A woman, however
    good and noble she may be by nature, in my view stands in great and immediate danger in today’s
    society of sinking into the maelstrom of prostitution if she has no means and isn’t protected by
    her own family. What is more natural than that one should support such a person? And if there’s
    no other solution when circumstances lead to it, well, then — you must put your heart and soul
    into it and marry her. At least it seems to me that one must make it a principle to continue
    with this protection once offered until rescue is complete, and to protect with one’s own breast
    if necessary. Even without a particular love? Perhaps, yes — in that case it’s a marriage of
    convenience, so be it — but not in the sense of a marriage that one enters into for gain.</p> 
         <p>And
    now, your particular case differs from the more everyday — such as mine, for instance — because
    of the singular circumstance that the person in question has a special charm and that there is,
    I believe, a sympathy of feeling, so that even if the meeting had taken place under entirely
    different and less dramatic circumstances, you might have been in two minds over the question at
    issue. In the above you have my thoughts on the question: ‘How far may one go in becoming
    involved with an unfortunate woman?’ Answer — ‘ad infinitum’. While still emphasizing that
    staying loyal comes first and foremost in all love, I remind you of your own words that
    ‘marrying’ (i.e. civil marriage) ‘is such an odd thing’. These words of yours express exactly
    how it is, and on that point I declare I don’t know which is better or worse, to meddle or not.
    It’s what they call ‘puzzling’. It puzzles me too — and I for my part wish so much that one had
    nothing to do with that. I believe it’s well said that ‘when one marries, one marries not only
    the woman herself but the family too’, which is sometimes more or less fatal and wretched if
    they’re nasty people.</p> 
         <p>But now about the drawings — I’ve done some more with printer’s ink, and
    this week I was investigating how to mix the printer’s ink with white, and found that it can be
    mixed in at least two ways — namely with the white from the tubes of oil paint — and probably
    even better with the ordinary zinc white in powder form that one can even get at any chemist —
    in that case diluting it with turpentine, which doesn’t soak through on this paper or leave
    marks on the reverse like oil — because it dries so quickly and disappears. Printer’s ink has
    much livelier effects than indian ink. How beautiful Jules Dupré’s work is. In the window at
    G&amp;C. I saw a small seascape which you no doubt know, and which I’ve been going to have a
    look at almost every evening — but as regards Dupré and similar art — of which one sees so much
    more in Paris than here — you may be rather spoiled — and not know what an almightily beautiful
    impression it makes here, where one sees so precious little of it.</p> 
         <p>Have got round to reading the
    last part of Les misérables — the figure of Fantine — a prostitute — made a deep impression on
    me — oh, I know as well as anyone that in reality one won’t find an exact Fantine — but all the
    same this character by Hugo — like all his characters for that matter — is true, being the
    essence of what one sees in reality. It is the type — of which one encounters only individuals.
    Should you happen to run into an engraver one of these days, like Girardet or Eichens, for
    example, who make aquatints, you’d be doing me a great favour if you could ask in passing: what
    is normally used for the drawings intended to serve as a guide for the engraving? Perhaps
    they’ll say: printer’s ink. If that’s what they use, what do they dilute that printer’s ink
    with? How do they use it? It seems to me that if you raised this with some engraver or other in
    passing and told me what he said, I would probably find something in what he said that would
    throw light on some questions, even if it wasn’t a direct answer to what printer’s ink is mixed
    with to make it possible to work with it on paper in various ways. No doubt there are other
    kinds of printer’s ink apart from the one I have at the moment, and the question may resolve
    itself in due course. Effects like those in aquatint engravings are produced in the drawings
    when one works with printer’s ink and turpentine, as I tried now. I’ve seen drawings in the past
    by Mottram, say, the English engraver who engraved the Boughtons, and I wish I knew what he
    worked with, for example. It goes without saying that I’m not in a rush to have this
    information, but if you happen to hear something about different methods of drawing, do let me
    know. </p>
         <p>I too know Soek’s wife and her mother (if she still lives with her) — went there in the
    past — they’re still very clear in my memory — and find them two sympathetic people — who remind
    me of the members of my own household — so much so indeed that instinctively I often think of
    them as members of the same family. They’re just like characters from Souvestre, say, or E.
    Frère. One sees more people like that in Paris — everywhere for that matter. Such people always
    remind me of the female figures in the gospel, perhaps because sometimes in their expressions
    there’s something of, for instance, the figures in Delaroche, Good Friday, or in Landelle,
    Blessed are they that mourn. I know, this view isn’t complete, there are other aspects — still
    better than Delaroche — and deeper than he — such as those of Lhermitte and Herkomer. Well, I
    find that in them too, but I can still understand that this movement became popular in the days
    of Souvestre, Delaroche, Frère, Landelle &amp;c., even though compared with Millet and others it
    isn’t entirely correct and true. Is ANKER still alive? I think of his work often, I find it so
    sound and so delicately felt. He’s one of the genuine old sort, like Brion. Old chap, how I
    sometimes long for you to be in the studio again. I sincerely hope you’ll get the money back
    from H. In my case a lot had to be spent right away this time, <stress reason="money">and I have precious little left.</stress>
    Anyway, write as soon as you can when it’s getting towards the 20th. </p>
      </body>
      <close>Adieu, with a handshake.</close>
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Dordrecht,</location>
         <date> 16 March 1877</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>Thanks for your letter, want to make sure you receive a few words in Amsterdam. <unstress reason="family">We’ll see
      each other Sunday, I hope, and it will be good for us to be together again.</unstress>
         </p>
         <p>My hearty congratulations to you on Willemien’s birthday, what a nice girl she’s become. From
      Pa and Ma she’s getting ‘de wijde wijde wereld’, and from me ‘het Kerstfeest aan de pool’ by
      Bungener. I’m glad for you that you left on your trip so soon, that makes for a good
      change.</p>
         <p>
            <good_health>I’m so sad and so alone, you say. ‘And yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me’.
      ‘Lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world’.</good_health>
         </p>
         <p>Holding fast in all places and in all circumstances to the thought of Christ, that is a good
      thing. ‘I set the Lord before me alway, the Lord is my keeper, He is the shade upon my right
      hand’, said David. What a hard life the farmers in Brabant have; Aarssen, for example, where
      does their strength come from? And those poor women, what is the support in their lives? Might
      it not be that image of Christ, the wondrous power and attraction of that name? Might it not
      be what the painter painted in his ‘Light of the world’? I cannot tell you how much I
      sometimes yearn for the Bible. I do read something out of it every day, but I’d so much like
      to know it by heart and to see life in the light of that word of which it is said: Thy word is
      a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path.</p>
         <p>
            <good_health>I believe and trust that my life will still be changed, and that that longing for Him will be
      satisfied.</good_health> 
            <bad_health>I, too, am sometimes sad and alone, especially when I walk around a church or a
      parsonage.</bad_health>
         </p>
         <p>‘A poor man in the kingdom of heaven’, that is a name that attracts a man and is a gospel to
      him. Let us not give up and go on seeking meekness and longsuffering.</p>
         <p>And be true to your own nature and be separate, distinguish between good and evil even if you
      don’t show it. Do it for yourself.</p>
         <p>‘Do not leave this life without having given evidence in one way or other of your love for
      Christ’, says Claudius.</p>
         <p>You’ve had an experience that can make you wise your whole life long, do hold that fast which
      thou hast.</p>
         <p>Feed me with the bread of my tears, truth, teach me. And it also says: ‘The sacrifices of God
      are a broken heart and a broken spirit; a broken heart, O God, thou wilt not despise’. HATE
      sin, be discerning, do you remember how Pa used to pray every morning ‘Preserve us from all
      evil, especially the evil of sin’? And he certainly knows. And it also says: he who hate not,
      yea his own life also, he cannot be My disciple. I’m longing for Sunday, I hope you’ll have a
      good trip, working is always a wonderful thing, and there is something good in all labour.</p>
         <p>
            <good_health>Am still busy until late at night, but glad it’s like this.</good_health>
         </p>
         <p>Be sure to give my regards to Uncle Cor and Aunt. There are storks here already, but I
      haven’t heard any larks yet. It’s often stormy, and then one sees swarms of crows and
      starlings.</p>
         <p>The photograph of Mater Dolorosa that you sent is hanging in my room, how beautiful it is. Do
      you remember it hanging in Pa’s study at Zundert?</p>
         <p>Now Theo, I wish you the very best, we’ll be seeing each other soon, I’m longing to see the
      prints you wrote about, accept a handshake in thought, see you Sunday, adieu, and believe
      me</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Amsterdam</location>, Monday, <date>19 November 1877</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p> I feel the need to write to you again, because I often think of you and long so much for
      Christmas, when we hope to see each other again. Well, the dark days before Christmas are
      already in sight, and behind them lies Christmas, just like the kindly light from the houses
      behind the rocks and the water that breaks against them on a dark evening. </p>
         <p> The Christmas celebration was always a bright spot for us, and may it remain so. </p>
         <p> 
            <stress reason="career">An entrance exam has been held at the university here for the first time — it’s here in the
      city that I’ll sit the exam as well. In addition to the usual 4 subjects of Latin, Greek,
      algebra and geometry, they also tested history, geography and Dutch.</stress> 
         </p>
         <p> Have taken pains to find a teacher of Algebra and Geometry and have succeeded, namely a
      cousin of Mendes, Teixeira de Mattos, a teacher at the Jewish School for the Poor. He gives me
      hope that we’ll have met the requirements by around October of next year. If I should then
      pass the exam, things will have gone very well indeed.<stress reason="career">Because when I started they said that 2
      years would be necessary for the first 4 subjects mentioned, whereas if I should pass in
      October, I’ll have done more in an even shorter time. May God give me the wisdom I need and
      grant me my heart’s desire, namely to complete my studies as soon as possible and to be
      inducted into a living and the practical duties of a minister. Doing that work, and being
      devoted to it, I believe one would be doing what God wants one to do.</stress>  
         </p>
         <p> The preparatory studies (i.e. those preceding the actual theological study and practice in
      preaching and speaking) more or less comes down to the history, languages and geography of
      Greece, Asia Minor (which can be taken to include Palestine) and Italy. <stress reason="career">So I have to study
      these just as diligently as a dog gnaws a bone</stress>, and similarly I should like to know the
      languages, history and geography of the northern countries, i.e. those around the North Sea
      and the English Channel. </p>
         <p> Have finally succeeded in making a map of Asia Minor, Greece and Italy, fairly large (which
      now includes Paul’s travels as well), and also one of England which finally has something of
      what I wanted it to have, at least Mendes sees it in it, namely that it was not drawn without
      feeling and love. (I put in the names from a map in the Atlas Antiquus of SprunerMenke that
      Mendes has, because it’s one to be used for history.) Come on, do your best to take a look at
      that atlas sometime, likewise the one by Stieler in particular. Because it is artistry.
      (SprunerMenke, Atlas Antiquus.)On Sunday I heard the Rev. Ten Kate on John XIV:16 (In my
      Father’s house are many mansions: Whosoever says that, what our Father’s house holds in
      memories for us, what it promises us). He ended with: The hour is coming in which the dead
      shall hear the voice of the Son of the people and shall stand up, they that have done good,
      unto the Resurrection of the Eternal Life. Blessed are the homesick, for they shall come home.
      The church was so packed that I stood. </p>
         <p> Spent two evenings at Uncle Cor’s, once to look at old books (including volumes of
      L’Illustration in which I found many old acquaintances, that is really an interesting
      magazine, among other things an old portrait of Dickens and a woodcut by De Lemud, ‘The cup of
      coffee’, a young man with rather severe and sharp features and a serious expression who looks
      exactly as though he were thinking about that passage from The imitation, On the monastic
      life, or as though he were contemplating some difficult but good work or plan, as only a soul
      in need can. Such work isn’t always the worst, but what one does in sorrow, as it were, lives
      on. Happy the man who is instructed by Truth itself, not by signs and passing words, but as it
      is in itself, are good words). </p>
         <p> Then I was also at Uncle Cor’s on Aunt’s birthday, i.e. last Friday, they played cards that
      evening, and because I can’t I sat there reading A. Gruson, Histoire des croisades (Panthéon
      classique 50 cmes). That’s a very beautiful little book, I would almost say that here and
      there it was written with the sentiment of Thijs Maris (herewith, among other things, a page
      that struck me), such as when he paints an old castle on a rock with autumnal woods at
      twilight, with the black fields with a peasant ploughing with a white horse in the foreground,
      and it also made me think of Michelet and Carlyle. </p>
         <p> I should like so much for Pa to know that etching of A young citizen of the year V. Do you
      approve of giving it on Pa’s birthday or before then, along with some small photos of the
      Revolution, so that it forms a whole from which Pa can see what we often think about? </p>
         <p> Perhaps you already know that there have been sad tidings today from Brussels, that Pa has
      already gone there. Uncle Jan, who received a telegram containing this news from Ma,
      telegraphed Pa and received the answer ‘Condition unchanged don’t come yet I’m here’. Uncle
      Jan and Uncle Cor were already set to go there together, now they’re awaiting further notice
      from faithful Pa. Will there then finally be an end to that long and terrible suffering? </p>
         <p> Goodbye Theo, write soon, old boy, if you can, may God preserve our health and give us the
      clarity of mind and the strength and vigour we need every day. Uncle Jan, Uncle Cor and the
      Stricker family send you their regards, and accept a hearty handshake in thought from </p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p> That news about Uncle Hein comes while I’m writing this.Paul Stricker will in all likelihood
      have to return to Holland because of his health. A good letter from Johan van Gogh, and Willem
      is also doing relatively well, but does have to look after himself and be careful.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Amsterdam</location>, Sunday, <date>15 July 1877</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p> I feel the need to write to you again, let me have a word from you too, if you have time. </p>
         <p> This morning I went to the early sermon, and the text was Eph. 5:14, Awake thou that
      sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall give thee light. <unstress reason="environment">When I left here it was
      raining, and also when leaving the church, though during the sermon the sun had been shining
      brightly through the windows.</unstress> 
         </p>
         <p> Pa had to lead the early service today in Etten, and afterwards Pa had to go to Zundert. </p>
         <p> After that I heard dear Uncle Stricker in the Oudezijdskapel on the words ‘Beware of the
      leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees’, which is a warning not to become too attached
      to outward forms and ceremonies without truly sincere religious feeling of the heart, as
      opposed to a life without belief in the things that are higher than those in this life. There
      were very few people in the church, apart from the orphan boys and orphan girls with their red
      and black clothes, who filled a large part of the little old church nonetheless. If you come
      here again I hope to take you there, that Oudezijdskapel is in a very narrow street, Zeedijk,
      near the part of Buitenkant called ‘the old taryards’ and near Warmoesstraat. It’s a very nice
      part of town and reminds one of the heart of London, like Booksellers’ Row or some such place.
      May it be granted me in time to speak as I have heard so many do, and hear each Sunday again.
      I’m doing my best to become skilled at it with all the power in me. </p>
         <p> Last week I spent an evening at the old Rev. Meijjes’s and met his son there, the Rev.
      Jeremie Meijjes with his wife, a daughter of Professor Tilanus, and two of his sons – one of
      them attends the gymnasium here and the other is training to be an engineer. The latter helped
      to build those roofs here at the dockyard (underneath which the ships are built, where we went
      with Uncle that afternoon you were here), as well as the new Kattenburg bridge. It was a
      pleasant evening and we talked about all kinds of foreign matters. He’s a very gifted man and
      has a pure talent and a great faith, heard him in the Westerkerk. Saw him coming from the
      pulpit and walking through the church after the sermon, and that tall, noble figure and that
      tired, pale face and that noble head, the hair already showing some grey, made a great
      impression on me. To be tired in such a way from that work, that is a blessing. </p>
         <p> Today you’ll perhaps go to Scheveningen, have a good Sunday, how I’d like to visit your
      little room. Heard from home that you’ll probably go to see Mauve again soon in his house in
      the dunes, and will stay overnight, I can imagine you sitting there, and I also know what
      you’ll discuss. Last week Mendes told me about a very interesting part of the city, namely the
      area extending from the Leidsepoort (thus close to Vondelpark) to the Hollandsche Spoor
      station. Went there yesterday, I knew part of it already, and you do too, I think, namely the
      part near the station. There are a great many mills, sawmills, workers’ houses with little
      gardens, old houses too, of all kinds, and very populous, and the area is crisscrossed by all
      kinds of small canals and waterways full of barges, and all kinds of picturesque bridges and
      so on. It must certainly be a wonderful thing to be a minister in such a district. </p>
         <p> This study is difficult, old chap, but I must persevere, and to that end may He help me of
      Whom it is written: If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men
      liberally, and upbraideth not. </p>
         <p> Ma wrote in her last letter something about ‘Anna’s house’, which is a new expression that
      doesn’t sound bad, she’ll perhaps be very happy one of these days, may she have made a good
      choice and one not to be repented of. The best we can do for the time being is, I think,
      simply be very happy about it. </p>
         <p> If you should happen to visit Mauve and Jet one of these days, give them my warm regards and
      spend some pleasant hours together, and bid goodday to the dunes and the sea for me. And tell
      Mauve that the photograph of his drawing, the plough in the field, is hanging in my little
      room and constantly reminds me of him. </p>
         <p> Are you reading something beautiful? I’d like so much to start reading a great many books
      but may not, if you can get hold of John Halifax do read it again, even though we read it with
      nostalgia, still, let us not say ‘that is not for me’, because it’s good to go on believing in
      everything that’s good and noble. I heard that the man whose life and character prompted the
      book to be written died recently, he was called Harper and ran a large bookshop in London. I
      once met the painter Millais on the street in London, <good_health>just after I had been so happy to see
      various of his paintings,</good_health> and that noble figure made me think of John Halifax. Millais once
      painted The lost penny, a young woman looking in the early morning twilight for the penny she
      has lost (there’s an engraving of it, the lost mite) and not the least beautiful of his work
      is an autumn landscape, Chill October. </p>
         <p>Adieu, old chap, accept in thought a hearty handshake, and believe me, after giving my
      regards to your housemates, in haste, because I have to go to church, </p>
      </body>
      <close>Your most loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles</location>, <date>between Tuesday, 17 and Friday, 20 July 1888.</date>
      </head>


      <salutation>My dear Theo</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>Many thanks for your letter, <unstress reason="friendship">which gave me great pleasure</unstress>, coming just at the moment
                  when I was still dazed by the sun and the strain of handling a rather large
                  canvas.<work stage="finished" origin="new"> I have a new drawing of a garden full of flowers</work>; <work stage="finished" origin="new">I also have two painted
                  studies of it</work>. I must send you a rather large new order for canvas and colours.
                  Only it’s not at all urgent. What, if anything, would be urgent would rather be
                  the canvas, seeing that I have a whole lot of stretching frames from which I’ve
                  removed the studies, and on which in the meantime I must put other canvases. </p>




            <p>You’ll see from this croquis the subject of the new studies; there’s one vertical and
                  one horizontal one of the same subject — no. 30 canvases. There’s definitely a
                  subject for a painting among them — as in some other studies that I have. And
                  truly, I don’t know if I’ll ever do tranquil and calmly worked paintings, myself,
                  as it seems to me that it will always remain disjointed. Have you any news from
                  Gauguin? I wrote to him again last week, to know how it was going with his health
                  and his work. No reply from Russell, who’s probably not in Paris, judging by what
                  Macknight was saying, who has come back with Boch. Still icy silence about the
                  work when they come. What you say about Princenhage, it’s true that it’s the same
                  story all over again — but when at long last the fellow isn’t there any more, then
                  for his little circle it will be one more emptiness and desolation. And even the
                  rest of us would feel it, because there’s something heartbreaking in the fact that
                  when we were younger we saw so much of him, and we were even influenced by him. </p>
            <p>So, seeing someone whom one has known as very active reduced to that state of
                  suspicious helplessness and constant suffering, it certainly doesn’t give you an
                  appealing or cheerful notion of human life, and doesn’t add to the joy of living.
                  Our mother in Breda, she must be getting on a bit, too. Without meaning to — is it
                  the effect of nature down here, so Ruisdaelesque? — I quite often think of
                  Holland, and with the double separation of distance and time that has passed,
                  these memories have something heartbreaking about them. What you write about Reid
                  isn’t very cheerful either — at times he used to speak so often of making himself
                  a painter, and of retiring to live with an aunt in the country, that it’s just
                  possible that he’s carrying out this plan now. What does Maria say? But perhaps
                  she’s disappeared too. I believe all the same that the constant wind here must
                  have something to do with the fact that the painted studies have that wild look.
                  Because you also see it in Cézanne. </p>
            <p>What must make it easier for the Japanese to stuff their works of art into drawers
                  and cupboards is that you can roll kakemonos but not our painted studies, which
                  would eventually flake. Nothing would make it easier for us to place our canvases
                  than to get them widely accepted as decorations in bourgeois homes. As in Holland
                  in the old days. And here in the south it would do a hell of a lot of good to see
                  paintings on the white walls. But go and look: big, coloured Julien medallions
                  everywhere — horrors. And alas, we won’t change anything in this state of affairs.
                  However — cafés — perhaps we’ll decorate them later on. More soon, handshake.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles,</location> 
         <date>Sunday, 29 July 1888.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Many thanks for your kind letter. If you recall, mine ended with: we’re
  getting old, that’s what is and the rest is imagination and doesn’t exist. Now, I said that even
  more for myself, than for you. And I said it feeling the absolute necessity for me to act
  accordingly, to work, not more, perhaps, but with a more serious conception. Now you talk about
  the emptiness you sometimes feel; that’s just the same thing that I have, too. Considering, if you
  will, the times in which we live as a true and great revival of art, the moth-eaten and official
  tradition, which is still on its feet, but which is at bottom powerless and bone-idle, <stress reason="environment">the new
  painters, alone, poor, treated like madmen and as a result of this treatment becoming so in fact,
  at least as far as their social life is concerned.</stress> Then remember that you do exactly the same work
  as these primitive painters, since you provide them with money and you sell their canvases for
  them, which enables them to produce others. <stress reason="career">If a painter ruins his character by working hard at
  painting, which makes him sterile for many things, for family life, &amp;c. &amp;c</stress>. If as a
  consequence he paints not only with paint but with self-denial and self-abnegation and a broken
  heart. Not only are you not paid for your own work either, but it costs you exactly the same as
  this effacement of personality, half deliberate, half accidental, costs a painter. This is to say
  that if you do painting indirectly, you’re more productive than me, for example. The more
  completely you become a dealer, the more you become an artist. Just as I very much hope to be in
  the same case... <stress reason="career">The more I become dissipated, ill, a broken pitcher, the more I too become a
  creative artist in that great revival of art of which we’re speaking.</stress> These things are indeed so,
  but this eternally existing art and this revival — this green shoot growing from the roots of the
  old felled trunk — these are things so spiritual that a kind of melancholy remains with us when we
  reflect that at less expense we could have made life instead of making art. You really ought, if
  you can, to make me feel that art is alive, you who perhaps love art more than I do. I say to
  myself that that doesn’t have to do with art, but with me, that the only way for me to regain
  self-confidence and tranquillity is by doing better. And here we are again at the end of my last
  letter — I’m getting old, but it’s only imagination if I were to believe that art is an old, stale
  thing.</p> 
         <p>Now, if you know what a ‘mousmé’ is (you’ll know when you’ve read Loti’s Madame
  Chrysanthème), I’ve just painted one. It took me my whole week, I wasn’t able to do anything else,
  having been not too well again. That’s what annoys me, if I’d been well I’d have knocked off some
  more landscapes in between times. But in order to finish off my mousmé I had to save my mental
  powers. A mousmé is a Japanese girl — Provençale in this case — aged between 12 and 14. That makes
  2 figures, the Zouave, and her, that I have.</p> 
         <p>Look after your health, take baths, especially if
  Gruby recommends that you do. Because you’ll see in 4 years, the years by which I’m older than
  you, how far relative health is necessary in order to be able to work. Now we who work with our
  heads, our only and unique means of avoiding being finished too soon is the artificial
  prolongation of modern hygiene, rigorously followed, as far as we can endure it. Because I for one
  don’t do everything that I should do. And a little good cheer is better than any other remedy.</p> 
         <p>I
  have a letter from Russell. He says that he would have written to me before had it not been that
  his move to Belle-Île had absorbed him. He’s there now, and says that he’d be pleased if sooner or
  later I came to spend some time there. He still wants to do my portrait again. He even says, ‘I
  would have gone to Boussod’s to see the Gauguin, negresses talking, had it not been that I was
  prevented from doing so for the same reason’. In short, he’s not refusing to buy one, but is
  making it understood that he wouldn’t want poorer quality than ours. You see that this is in any
  case better than nothing at all. I’ll write this to Gauguin and will ask him for croquis of
  paintings. We shouldn’t push this business and give up on R. for the time being, but consider the
  thing as an ongoing piece of business that will come off. And the same for Guillaumin, I’d like
  him to buy a figure by G. He says he’s received a very fine bust of his wife from Rodin, and that
  on that occasion he lunched with Claude Monet and that he saw the 10 paintings of Antibes then.
  I’m sending him Geffroy’s article. He makes a very good critique of the Monets, first of all
  liking them very much: the difficulty attacked, the envelope of coloured air, the colour. Now
  after that he says, what must be repeated is that it all lacks construction everywhere, for
  example, with him a tree will have far too much foliage for the size of the trunk, and so always
  and everywhere, from the point of view of the reality of things, from the point of view of a whole
  number of laws of nature, he’s pretty well hopeless. He ends by saying that this quality of
  attacking difficulties is what everyone should have.</p> 
         <p>I’ve received from Bernard 10 croquis like
  his brothel; there are 3 of them that are in the style of Redon; the enthusiasm that he has for
  that I don’t much share myself. But there’s a woman washing herself, very Rembrandtesque, or in
  the style of Goya, and a very strange landscape with figures. He expressly forbids me to send them
  to you, but you’ll receive them by the same post. I think Russell will buy something else from
  Bernard. Now I’ve seen work by this Boch; it’s rigorously Impressionist but not powerful, at this
  moment when this new technique is still preoccupying him too much to allow him to be himself.
  He’ll become stronger and will bring out his individuality, I think. But Macknight does
  watercolours of the power of those by Destrée, you know, that vile Dutchman we knew back in the
  old days. However, he’d washed some small still lifes, yellow jug on purple foreground, red jug on
  green, orange jug on blue: better, but it’s pretty poor. The village where they’re staying is pure
  Millet, small peasants, nothing but that, totally rustic and intimate. That character completely
  escapes them. I believe that Macknight has civilized and converted to civilized Christianity his
  lout of a landlord. At least, when you go there that scoundrel and his worthy spouse shake your
  hand — it’s in a café, of course — when you ask for a drink they have ways of refusing the money,
  ‘Oh, I couldn’t take money from an artiss’ (with two s’s). Anyhow, it’s their own fault that it’s
  appalling, and this Boch must be getting pretty dull-witted with Macknight. I think Macknight has
  money, but not much. So they contaminate the village; if it weren’t for that, I’d go there often
  to work there. What one ought to do there is not talk to civilized people; but they know the
  stationmaster and a score of bloody nuisances, and that’s largely why they don’t do a damned
  thing. I’ve already said that to Mourier, who once used to believe that Macknight got on highly
  intelligently with the ‘man of the fields’. Naturally, these simple and naive people of the fields
  make fun of them, and despise them. On the contrary, if you do your work there without worrying
  about the village idlers with their stiff collars, then you can go into the homes of the peasants,
  enabling them to earn a few sous. And then that bloody Fontvieille would be a treasure to them,
  but the natives are — Zola’s small peasants, innocent and gentle beings, as we know.</p> 
         <p>It’s likely
  that Macknight will shortly do little landscapes with sheep, for boxes of sweets. Not just my
  paintings, but I myself most of all, I had recently become wild-eyed, a bit like Hugo van der Goes
  in the painting by Emile Wauters. But having had all my beard carefully shaved off, I believe that
  I have as much of the very placid abbot in the same painting as of the mad painter so
  intelligently depicted in it. And I’m not unhappy to be somewhere between the two, because you
  have to live. Especially as there’s no getting away from the fact that one day or another there
  could be a crisis if you changed as far as your position with the Boussods was concerned. One more
  reason for maintaining relations with artists on my part as well as on yours. Besides, I believe
  I’ve told the truth, all the same. If I succeeded in bringing back in prices the money spent, I
  would be doing no more than my duty. And the practical thing I can do is the portrait. As far as
  drinking too much goes... I don’t know if it’s bad. But just look at Bismarck, who in any case is
  very practical and very intelligent. His little doctor told him he was drinking too much and that
  he’d overtaxed himself all his life, from his stomach to his brain. B. stopped drinking there and
  then. Since then he’s lost ground and is dragging along. He must really be laughing inside at his
  doctor, whom fortunately for him he didn’t consult too soon.</p> 
      </body>
      <close>Anyway, good handshake.</close> 
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Remember that with Gauguin we should in no way change the idea of coming to his aid if the
  proposal is acceptable as it stands, but we don’t need him. So, as far as working alone goes,
  don’t believe that it bothers me, and don’t press the matter for me, be fully assured of that. <work origin="new" stage="finished">The
  portrait of a young girl</work> is on a white background strongly tinted with Veronese green, the bodice
  is striped blood-red and purple. The skirt is royal blue with large orange-yellow stippling. The
  matt areas of flesh are yellow grey, the hair purplish, the eyebrows black, and the eyelashes, the
  eyes orange and Prussian blue; a sprig of oleander between the fingers, because the 2 hands are
  included.</p>
      </ps> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Sunday, <date>20 July 1884</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>
            <good_health>I was delighted to learn from your letter to Pa and Ma that you plan to go to London</good_health>
                  on 4 Aug. and then to come on here from there. I’m again looking forward very much
                  to your arrival and to finding out what you’ll think of the work that I’ve done
                  since. <work origin="existing" stage="finished">The last things I did are a couple of rather large studies of oxcarts, a
                  black ox and a red and white one.</work>
         </p>
            <p>
            <work origin="new" stage="middle">And have also been working again on the old tower in the fields in the evening; I’ve
                  made a larger study of it than my previous ones — with the wheatfields around
                  it.</work>
         </p>
            <p>Rappard sent me back the little book by Vosmaer that belongs to you — I started to
                  read it but — is it just me? — find it almighty boring and actually written in an
                  academic, sermonizing tone. Perhaps you will too when you look at it again. Have
                  you read Sapho by Daudet? <unstress reason="environment">It’s very beautiful, and so vigorous, and so close to
                  life that the female figure lives, breathes, and one can hear, literally hear the
                  voice, and forgets that one is reading.</unstress>
         </p>
            <p>You’ll also <work stage="finished" origin="new">see a couple more new weavers </work>when you come.</p>
            <p>Nature is certainly pure here — I’m still very pleased with the studio, too.We must
                  visit some farms and weavers together when you come.</p>
            <p>Rappard’s plan is to come back again in October; he’s probably in Drenthe again
                  now.</p>
            <p>Well, I write in some haste because I’m hard at work. <good_health>I work a good deal early in the
                  morning or in the evening, and then sometimes everything is so inexpressibly
                  beautiful.</good_health>
         </p>
            <p>Regards, believe me</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Ramsgate, </location>
         <date>6 May 1876</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
        <p>Herewith you’ll find the 2 books I promised you. I’ve marked a few things in them, but
            you’ll certainly find many beautiful things in addition to these. As I wrote to you
            already, though, one starts to grow especially fond of them when one lives in the
            country itself.</p>
        <p>
            <unstress reason="environment">It’s already Saturday evening again; the weather’s beautiful today: the sea is very calm
            and it’s low tide at the moment, the sky is a delicate whitish blue with a haze in the
            distance. Early this morning it was also beautiful, everything was clear, where now it’s
            more or less hazy</unstress>.</p>
        <p>This town has something very singular, one notices the sea in everything; but you know
            this special quality, too, because one finds it in The Hague and Scheveningen as well.
            Did you know that Anna has received an answer to her advertisements? This week she sent
            me 3 letters she’d received. I’m longing to hear what she’s decided. One of the letters
            came from Amsterdam, a situation as companion to an old lady, another letter was from
            Vaals and yet another from here in England. She may have received even more since
            then.</p>
        <p>She seems awfully eager for an opportunity to come into contact with families; in
            Amsterdam she would find this at once through Uncle Cor and Uncle Stricker.</p>
        <p>Do you still visit Uncle Cor now and then? <stress reason="family">Sometimes I long to see him so much; just
            yesterday I wrote to him.</stress> Keep him as your friend, there can’t be any harm in that.
            Sometime you must tell Mr Tersteeg about the school here. These are really happy days,
            the ones I’m spending here, day after day, and yet it’s a happiness and peacefulness
            that I don’t trust entirely, though one thing can lead to another.</p>
        <p>
            <bad_health>A person isn’t easily satisfied, one moment he finds things far too good and the next
            he’s not satisfied enough. But I’m saying this by the by, we would do better not to talk
            about it, but rather continue quietly on our way.</bad_health> Have a good Sunday morning, and give
            my regards to everyone at the Rooses’, also to Mr and Mrs Tersteeg and Betsy, and in
            thought a handshake from</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Paris,</location> 
         <date>Tuesday, 9 November 1875.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
        <p>It’s time you heard from me again, though this will only be a short note, for
    I haven’t much time. Thanks for what you sent me, <good_health>I’m glad to have it.</good_health> I’m glad that you were in
    Etten on the day of the induction, for Pa and Ma’s sake as well as yours. You must write and
    tell me what it was like. Uncle Vincent and Aunt left yesterday. I went to see them quite often.
    <stress reason="friendship">I’m sorry I didn’t see them at the train yesterday when they left.</stress> 
         </p>
         <p> Herewith a letter, give it to Uncle when you see him, it explains why we didn’t see each other at the station. Autumn is
    really here, you’ll be going for walks fairly often. Do you get up early? I do regularly, it’s
    good to make a habit of it. <unstress reason="environment">It’s precious and already very dear to me, that early morning
    twilight.</unstress> I usually go to bed early in the evening. Every morning my worthy Englishman cooks
    barley porridge; how I’d like you to be here in the morning sometime. Anna seems to get up early
    as well. She doesn’t have it easy, and she certainly makes herself very useful. Well, more soon,
    probably. Do write again soon, and freely.</p>
      </body> 
      <close>I shake your hand in thought, and am ever</close> 
      <sig>Your loving brother Vincent</sig> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head> 
         <location>Auvers-sur-Oise</location>, Wednesday, <date>23 July 1890</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear brother,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>Thanks for your letter of today and for the 50franc note it contained.</p>
            <p>I’d perhaps like to write to you about many things, but first the desire has passed
                  to such a degree, then I sense the pointlessness of it.</p>
            <p>I hope that you’ll have found those gentlemen favourably disposed towards you.</p>
            <p>As regards the state of peace in your household, I’m just as convinced of the
                  possibility of preserving it as of the storms that threaten it. I prefer not to
                  forget the little French I know, and certainly wouldn’t see the point of delving
                  deeper into the rights or wrongs in any discussions on one side or the other. It’s
                  just that this wouldn’t interest me.</p>
            <p>Things go quickly here – aren’t Dries, you and I a little more convinced of that,
                  don’t we feel it a little more than those ladies? So much the better for them –
                  but anyway, talking with rested minds, we can’t even count on that.</p>
            <p>
            <good_health>As for myself, I’m applying myself to my canvases with all my attention, I’m trying
                  to do as well as certain painters whom I’ve liked and admired a great deal.</good_health>
            <stress reason="friendship">What
                  seems to me on my return – is that the painters themselves are increasingly at
                  bay.</stress>
         </p>
            <p>Very well. But has the moment to make them understand the utility of a union not
                  rather passed already? On the other hand a union, if it were formed, would go
                  under if the rest went under. Then you’d perhaps tell me that dealers would unite
                  for the Impressionists; that would be very fleeting. Anyway it seems to me that
                  personal initiative remains ineffective, and having done the experiment, would one
                  begin it again?</p>
            <p>I noted with pleasure that the Gauguin from Brittany that I saw was very beautiful,
                  and it seems to me that the others he’s done there must be too.</p>
            <p>
            <work origin="new" stage="middle">Perhaps you’ll see this croquis of Daubigny’s garden – it’s one of my most deliberate
                  canvases – to it I’m adding a croquis of old thatched roofs and the croquis of 2
                  no. 30 canvases depicting immense stretches of wheat after the rain.</work> Hirschig
                  asked me to ask you please to order the attached list of colours for him from the
                  same colourman you send me. Tasset can send them directly to him, cash on
                  delivery, but then he would have to be given the 20%.</p>
            <p>Which would be simplest.</p>
            <p>Or you’d put them into the consignment of colours for me, adding the invoice or
                  telling me how much they cost, and then he’d send you the money. Here one can’t
                  find anything good in the way of colours.</p>
            <p>I’ve simplified my own order to a very bare minimum.</p>
            <p>Hirschig is beginning to understand a little, it has seemed to me, he’s done the
                  portrait of the old schoolmaster, which he gave him, good – and then he has
                  landscape studies which are a little like the Konings at your place as regards
                  colour. It will become completely like that, perhaps, or like the things by
                  Voerman that we saw together.</p>
            <p>More soon. Look after yourself, and good luck in business . Warm regards to Jo,
                  and handshakes in thought.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Yours truly, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
            <p> Daubigny’s garden </p>
            <p> 
            <work stage="finished" origin="existing">Foreground of green and pink grass, on the left a green and lilac bush and a stem of
                  plants with whitish foliage. In the middle a bed of roses. To the right a hurdle,
                  a wall, and above the wall a hazel tree with violet foliage.</work> 
         </p>
            <p> Then a hedge of lilac, a row of rounded yellow lime trees. The house itself in the
                  background, pink with a roof of bluish tiles. A bench and 3 chairs, a dark figure
                  with a yellow hat, and in the foreground a black cat. Sky pale green.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague,</location> 
         <date>Monday, 25 September 1882.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
        <p>Your latest letter with the enclosure reached me in good order, and I thank
    you right heartily for it. <stress reason="money">I was and even still am in a bit of a spot — that is, with a view to
    painting. There are all kinds of costs involved.</stress> But that’s also partly because many of the
    things that I begin don’t come off, and then one has to start again and the effort comes to
    nothing, except that this is the way to make progress, and that one must persevere.</p> 
         <p>There was no
    answer in your last letter to what I said about sending or not sending painted studies. Perhaps
    it slipped your mind. Now, I decided that it wasn’t a weighty matter after all, and so <work origin="new" stage="finished">today
    I’ve sent you a painted study by post.</work> But, as I said in my last letter, I would of course
    rather you could see them all together sometime, and it goes without saying that you mustn’t
    judge the future by this one, since I haven’t been working with the brush long enough for me not
    to change a great deal. I wanted to send you a different one, <work origin="new" stage="finished">but the others I would rather have
    sent aren’t yet dry enough for me to risk rolling them up.</work> 
         </p>
         <p>Like me, you will no doubt have
    reservations about the background in particular. The only explanation I can offer about this is
    that the study was done as a study of the foreground, namely the tree roots; a lot of work had
    already gone into them, and as usual I wasn’t sitting peacefully because of passers-by, and so
    when I had got the study to the point you see I couldn’t bear it any more. <stress reason="environment">You can’t imagine how
    wearying and irritating it is that people always gather round so close.</stress> 
            <bad_health>It makes me so nervous
    sometimes that I have to give up.</bad_health> Just yesterday morning, although it was very early and I hoped
    to be spared, a study of the chestnut trees on Bezuidenhout (which are so splendid now) was a
    failure because of it. <stress reason="environment">And sometimes they’re so nasty and insolent.</stress>
         </p> 
         <p>Oh well. But it’s not just
    the regrets that one has — there’s also the cost of the paint, etc., which can’t be recovered.
    Of course things like that won’t get on top of me, and I’ll fight my way through them just as
    others do, but I do so feel that I could reach my goal much faster if there were fewer of these
    petty vexations. Now, as regards this study — if it’s the case that, on seeing it and knowing
    that I have many others as well as this one, you don’t regret enabling me to make it, then I’ll
    be content and shall carry on in good heart. If you’re disappointed, remember that I started
    only a short time ago; if you’re pleased, so much the better for me, for I would so much like to
    be able in time to send you something that gave you pleasure.</p>
         <p>Now I must tell you that <unstress reason="love">I had a very unexpected and very pleasing visit from Pa,</unstress> 
    who came to my house and to the studio, which I believe is infinitely better than his only hearing about me through reports 
    from others. If people visit me, then at least their impression is original, but I don’t like opinions based on
    what people say. <good_health>It really gave me great pleasure to see Pa and talk to him.</good_health> I’ve again heard a
    lot about Nuenen — that churchyard there with the old crosses won’t leave me alone, I do so hope
    that in time I’ll get round to doing it. I also heard a lot about your visit, and that you had
    given them that engraving after Israëls, which touched them deeply. <work origin="new" stage="finished"/> — I could send the first, but since then I’ve
    caught the colour of the sea better, and so I’m waiting until a later one is thoroughly dry.
    Recently, though, I’ve painted considerably more than in the original plan we discussed. But
    perhaps it’s necessary to continue doing this if it’s at all possible.</p> 
         <p>I received a letter from Rappard the other day. I wish he lived a little closer. And rest assured that I’m truly glad to
    hear your comments, just as they come into your mind. I often feel a desire and need to seek
    advice from someone on various questions, but after what happened with Mauve I don’t give in to
    that, and I don’t discuss my work with painters. However brilliant someone may be, what good is
    it to me if he argues differently from the way he works? I would rather M. had spoken to me
    about the use of body-colour instead of saying: ‘Above all, you mustn’t use body-colour’, while
    he himself and all the others, so to speak, nearly always use it, and to the best effect. 
    Well, in many cases one can gradually find out things by looking for oneself as well, and I’m doing
    that as best I can.</p> 
         <p>Yes — if it were so that I could do exactly what I wanted, I would take up
    painting on a somewhat larger scale and, above all, work much more with a model. I draw many
    figures in my spare moments. The small figure in this study is actually there simply and solely
    for the size, so that if I do use the study I can find the proportion of any figure, more or
    less. Of course, a proper figure is a very different matter and involves a great deal more. It’s
    also there to provide an accent. Make no mistake, old chap, I send you this because, since you
    said nothing about it, I didn’t know what to do. Of course I intend something very different
    from this, and I’m sending it in the same way that I make a scratch sometimes, to give you an
    idea of what I’m working on.</p>
         <p>Adieu, accept a handshake in thought. I hope that all is as well
    with you as possible, and that your headache isn’t something that lasts or keeps coming back. I
    have it too sometimes, more as a sense of unpleasant dullness than severe pain. Pa and I went
    for a walk on Rijswijkseweg, it’s lovely there too.</p>
      </body> 
      <close>Well, regards again, and believe me</close>
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>If this arrives safely, then this is an easy way of sending you things
    occasionally. I don’t know whether one can send drawings or paintings by post as printed matter.
    Another thing, you understand that I could do some things differently, for example some branches
    &amp;c., if I painted them again — but I think that one shouldn’t tinker with studies if they’re
    to be of any use. They should be hung up in the studio just as they come out of the woods. For
    some they may be less pleasing, but there’s more of his impression in them for the painter
    himself.</p>
      </ps> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague</location>, <date>1 July 1882</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>I’ve been back in my studio for a few hours and am writing to you immediately. <good_health>I
                  can’t tell you how wonderful it is to be better again</good_health>, or <unstress reason="environment">how beautiful everything
                  looked on the road from the hospital to here</unstress>. And how the light seemed brighter
                  and the spaces bigger, and all the objects and figures more important. There’s a
                  ‘but’, though, and that ‘but’ is that I’ll <bad_health>again have a catheter or a thick lead
                  probe in my bladder, for next Tuesday I have to go back to the doctor and tell him
                  how I’ve been getting on, and he has prepared me for the fact that I may then have
                  to go into hospital for another fortnight, possibly longer, possibly shorter,
                  depending on what’s needed</bad_health>. At any rate I would be absolutely delighted if I
                  didn’t have to go in again. As soon as I feel anything wrong I have to go back,
                  and even if I don’t notice anything I’ll go on Tuesday to be examined again. The
                  channel through which the urine passes must gradually be widened, but this can’t
                  be forced or rushed. The probes gradually become thicker, and each time a new one
                  goes in everything is stretched a little further, and that’s painful, but above
                  all extremely unpleasant, particularly because the thing is left in place for a
                  time. Blood comes out when it’s removed, and then you feel relatively free for a
                  few days, while the pain it causes disappears. I’m now here in one of those
                  intervals. Meanwhile I can now pass water quite easily once more,<unstress reason="environment"> which makes me
                  feel on top of the world</unstress>, as if it were something very special. But it must become
                  entirely normal, and that will take time. Yet the sense of getting better makes
                  you forget all the catheters and probes and instillations... until you see the
                  doctor approaching with them again. And that isn’t a very pleasant moment. Well,
                  such are the petty troubles of life. But what one might call a ‘great trouble’ is
                  pregnancy and delivery — <stress reason="friendship">the latest letter from Sien was very melancholy</stress>. She
                  hadn’t yet given birth but was expecting to at any hour, and I feel very worried,
                  because this waiting has been going on for days. It was chiefly to be able to
                  visit her that I asked the doctor to change the walks in the garden into a short
                  leave of absence, if it was at all possible. So tomorrow morning I’m going to see
                  her with her mother and child, Sunday being the only day on which she’s allowed
                  visitors. Her last letter to me wasn’t written by herself but by the nurse, who
                  herself asked that we should come sometime. Yet we may still find that we aren’t
                  allowed in. Poor lass, she’s full of courage and not easily frightened, but
                  according to that last letter there was nothing in particular wrong except for
                  inner frailty. I can’t tell you how I longed for her in the hospital and how I
                  long for her now, and at times I wasn’t sorry that <bad_health>I had to cope with some
                  suffering myself</bad_health>, rather than standing there in excellent health, for then it
                  would have been very unevenly divided. If all goes well, though, Sien will be back
                  this month, may that prove to be the case. But the proverb says ‘A mother’s pains
                  are long-lasting’. This casts a dark shadow over the wonderful feeling of getting
                  better. I’m longing for tomorrow and dreading it at the same time. </p>
            <p>The first person I came across here in Schenkweg was my friend the carpenter, who has
                  helped me on several occasions with one job or another to do with making
                  instruments for perspective. And who’s also the foreman for the owner of the
                  studio I wrote to you about. His boss was just at the yard (the drawing of which
                  you have, with meadows in the distance), and they coaxed me into going along, and
                  showed me how they had left the room that would be the studio unpapered pending my
                  decision. I said I still couldn’t decide. Fine, said the man, but I could choose
                  what I wanted from a batch of wallpapers, then he would put it up and I wouldn’t
                  be under any obligation. And even though I said I didn’t want that, since I had to
                  go back to the hospital, they’ve already started work, because they insist on
                  showing me it before Tuesday. I must say the house is very comfortable and looks
                  really large and smart. The huge, fully panelled attic alone would make a superb
                  studio if need be, although the room facing north was going to be the studio. And
                  the price is unusually low for here; in the city it would be about double. Three
                  guilders a week for a large upstairs flat is very little, even in comparison with
                  neighbourhoods like Noordwal or the Buitensingels. And the location is excellent
                  for a painter. There’s one view from the attic window that’s enchanting. Still, I
                  didn’t want to take a decision <bad_health>because both Sien and I are sick</bad_health>. But I’ll take the
                  matter up again as soon as we’re better. There is air and space, wonderful to work
                  in and keep healthy. Light from the north, and in the other room roughly from the
                  south. There’s a small kitchen I really hope to draw a lot, also with a little
                  window overlooking a sort of courtyard. I mustn’t forget to tell you that, most
                  unexpectedly, I had a visit in the hospital from Mr Tersteeg, <unstress reason="friendship">which gave me great
                  pleasure in one sense</unstress>, although we didn’t talk about anything special, nor is that
                  necessary. But I thought it very kind. Then a few days later Iterson came as well,
                  about which I cared much less.</p>
            <p> And then Johan van Gogh, who I thought was in Helvoirt but turns out to be living in
                  Stationsweg these days. He told me that he, too, had had a bunch of catheters and
                  other musical instruments in his bladder once. Given that he appears to be free of
                  them now, I hope there’ll be an end to it in my case as well. It would be too bad
                  if a person had such adornments for a long time — it would be hard to climb stairs
                  or show yourself in public. If you send me something at the beginning of this
                  month, you should address the letter to the hospital. It will be all right,
                  because the porter has promised me to keep letters if I’m away (this is allowed
                  under hospital rules as long as one isn’t finally discharged and puts in a
                  request). On Tuesday I have to pay for the hospital again, and the rent that I owe
                  as well. <unstress reason="career">But the finest thing of all about getting better is that my drawing is
                  coming back to life</unstress>, together with my feeling for things, which was drugged, so to
                  speak, for a time, and was a great void. I again enjoy everything I see. And then,
                  I haven’t smoked a pipe in about a month — that’s another old friend back. I can’t
                  tell you with what pleasure I sit here again in the studio after spending so long
                  in an environment of chamber-pots &amp;c., even though the hospital is also
                  beautiful, truly beautiful. Especially the garden with all the strollers, men,
                  women, children. I have a few scratches, but as a patient you aren’t free to work
                  as it ought to be done, and not up to it either. Well, adieu, write soon, and
                  believe me, with a handshake</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Monday, <date>17 August 1885</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>I’ve heard from that colourman — who tells me I can send the paintings. But that he wants me
      to send them as soon as possible because there are many strangers in The Hague at present.</p>
         <p>
            <stress reason="money">He’s quite right there. What I want to ask you is that you try to send me enough for me to
      get the crate made and pay the carriage. Deduct it next month, if you like — but I have
      nothing, and it’s important to me to get my consignment off immediately.</stress>
         </p>
         <p>
            <bad_health>Your visit really left me with a less than favourable impression</bad_health> — I believe more than ever
      that more difficulties await you in the next few years than you imagine.</p>
         <p>I continue to insist that it’s somewhat fatal that your energy has evidently taken a
      different direction, rather than working on our getting our heads above water with the
      painting. And yet it’s such a short while ago that you wrote that you now had more confidence
      that my work was good. You take it as though I was doing you wrong or was hostile to you, now
      I most decidedly have rather a lot of remarks to make. And considerable concerns for the
      future. I can’t speak other than I did, can I?</p>
         <p>To my mind you don’t in the least belong among the rising men now. Take this amiss of me — if
      you will — and treat me as you will accordingly. </p>
         <p>I’m willing to take back my remarks should I see very different things in you, but that I
      made them during your visit — Yes. But even though you say today, ‘I’m selling 500,000 francs’
      worth a year’ — this doesn’t make any impression on me at all, since I’m only too convinced of
      the precariousness of it all — you keeping up even a half or a fifth of that and delivering in
      the years ahead. It’s too up in the air for me, too little at ground level.</p>
         <p>And art itself is solid enough, that’s not the trouble.</p>
         <p>But, ‘to be a countinghouse will pass’ was said, not by me, but by someone whose words came
      dreadfully true. And I wish you were, or would become, a painter. I put it bluntly, more
      strongly than before, because I believe so firmly that the largescale art trade is, in many
      respects, too much like tulip mania.</p>
         <p>And the positions in it dependent on chance and whim. Make a miscalculation — make what may
      be an insignificant mistake — and — what’s left of that huge figure you’re turning over now?
      That figure depends on  whim.</p>
         <p>And KNOWLEDGE of art, stripped bare, is related, more closely than you think, to the practice
      of art. TRADE in paintings is something very different when one is on one’s own from when one
      works for large distributors. And it’s the same with other things, too. Anyway — work hard —
      but — try to work sensibly too.</p>
         <p>The trouble you’ve taken together with me — for providing money is also taking trouble and
      there’s absolutely no getting away from it — this trouble has at least been an act of personal
      initiative, and of personal will and energy — but what am I to think or say of it if, little
      by little, with the decided weakening of the financial aid, something else weren’t to be put
      in its place? And now, above all, to my mind at any rate, it’s the time to try to push ahead
      with my work.</p>
         <p>I’ve also been looking for addresses in Antwerp, and will hear more precisely about them
      before long. Then I can probably send things there, too. But if you want these things, help me
      to bring them about. You said to me yourself, Where there is a will there is a way; well then,
      <stress reason="money">I’ll take you at your word a little as to whether you’re really seeking for us to make
      progress. If I were to ask for extravagant things and you refused, then so be it — but where
      they’re the most essential, the very simplest necessities, and the lack just becomes more and
      more, and worse and worse, then I think you’re taking economy too far, and in this respect
      it’s very far from being useful.</stress>
         </p>
      </body>
      <close>Regards.Yours truly,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Just a word about Serret and about Portier.<stress reason="money"> Tell them as it is, that is that I did have
      studies ready, but that I had to pay a colourman who was making it difficult for me just now.</stress>
      That in order to put a stop to it, I wrote to tell him that I put his paint in my studies, and
      that I asked him to take the trouble to sell something for me instead of nagging. That I’ll go
      through with it, and have to send him things.</p>
         <p>That as to the drawings which I said I’d show Serret, since I’m in a hurry to do things, I
      need them myself. But I do still think it’s of some importance that at any rate he knows that
      I really did have them when you came, and that you tell him that you saw them at my place, and
      then also tell him exactly what you think. I won’t influence your own opinion. That I’m sad
      about your thinking that this is all right, though, yes — that is so.</p>
         <p>But I don’t refuse to take such measures — and even if one of these colourmen wanted to sell
      off my bits and pieces, he would be welcome to go to those lengths. It’s certain that the
      paintdealing gentlemen wouldn’t blush to do it.</p>
         <p>However, I’m fed up with talking about it; I’ve said what I had to say — and you — you can
      deal with my suggestion as you see fit. </p>
         <p>
            <stress reason="money">And if these fellows want to attack me and sell me up, since they expressly threatened me
      with collection, and that over matters of less than 30 guilders, then I won’t be able to
      resist them and will let them do as they please, but it will be as if it happens before your
      very eyes, since you’ve just been here.</stress> That I can’t stop the work at the level I now am,
      that’s true. <stress reason="career">I need paint every day. I must make progress,</stress> and <stress reason="money">if I want to pay for
      what I need today, then an outstanding bill from yesterday will have to wait.</stress> For your
      information, this is how it is with me for the rest of the year, precisely and in detail — <stress reason="money">I
      have to pay:three suppliers who are all pestering me, one 45 guilders, the other 25 guilders, the other
      30 guilders. These are the exact sums outstanding on accounts which have of course been much
      higher over the course of the year, but which I pay off in cash, as much as I possibly can
      with the utmost effort.deficit therefore 100 guilders</stress>
         </p>
         <p>
            <stress reason="money">Add to this rent in November 25 ,, _________ 125 guilders = 250 francs</stress>
         </p>
         <p>Suppose I get 4 x 150 francs from you for Sept. Oct. Nov. Dec.= 600 francs. That then leaves
      350 francs to last from now until New Year. And then bear in mind that I have literally
      nothing left this month, and that I also have to live this month.</p>
         <p>So that from Aug. – 1 January, in other words almost 5 months, I have to live and paint on
      350 francs. Which I can do on 150 francs a month, but not easily, but anyway it’s possible as
      a minimum.</p>
         <p>
            <stress reason="career">However, if in the course of 4 months 250 francs has to be deducted to pay for paint and
      rent, well then, the work is hampered and obstructed so much that one doesn’t know what to do,
      and would rather say to the fellows sell my things then!</stress> 
            <stress reason="career">But let me work! Without hesitation
      I’ve just thrown this month in to calm the fellows down. But the hardship that’s caused is bad
      enough.</stress>
         </p>
         <p>And my last word on the subject is that if my work were weak and awful, I would agree with
      you if you said — ‘I can’t do anything about it’.</p>
         <p>Well — since larger and smaller painted studies as well as new drawings were able to make you
      understand that we’re making progress with it, I’m not so sure whether ‘I can’t do anything
      about it’ should be your final word. Talk to Serret, talk to Portier about it — and say how
      much I want to keep working and how little opportunity I have myself to find art lovers, since
      painting the peasants means that once and for all the countryside, not the city is my place of
      work.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague</location>, <date>Thursday, 10 and Friday, 11 August 1882.</date>
      </head>


      <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
      <body>
            <p>In the days since you left I’ve done some experimenting with painting. And thought
                  you might be curious to know how I’m getting on. I do wish that you could be back
                  in the studio for just an hour — that would be the best way to tell you how it
                  turned out. Since that is, of course, impossible, I just want to say that I have 3
                  painted studies. One of a row of pollard willows in the meadow (behind the
                  Geestbrug), then a study of the cinder road close to my neighbourhood — and today
                  I was again in the vegetable gardens in Laan van Meerdervoort, where I found a
                  potato field with a ditch. A man in a blue smock and a woman were gathering up the
                  potatoes, and I put their figures in. The field was white, sandy ground — half dug
                  over, half still covered by rows of dried stalks — with green weeds in between. In
                  the distance dark green and a few roofs. I took the greatest pleasure in doing the
                  last study in particular. I must say that painting is not as alien to me as you
                  might think. On the contrary, I find it very appealing on account of it being a
                  powerful means of expression. </p>
            <p>And at the same time one can say delicate things with it too — let a soft grey or
                  green speak in the midst of roughness. I’m very glad that I have the necessary
                  equipment, because in the past I often had to restrain myself. It opens up a much
                  broader horizon. Now I would like quietly to amass a good number of painted
                  studies to hang in my studio without referring to this as a change. And should
                  anyone express surprise at seeing painted work by me, to say: Well, did you think
                  I had no feeling for that or couldn’t do it? But I’ve put a lot of work into
                  drawing and will continue to do so, because it’s the backbone of painting, the
                  skeleton supporting everything else.<unstress reason="career"> I’m enjoying it so much</unstress>, Theo, that I’ll have
                  to restrain rather than push myself because of the costs. These studies are of
                  medium size, though slightly larger than the lid of an ordinary painting box,
                  because I don’t work in the lid, but instead pin the painting paper for the study
                  to a frame with canvas stretched across it, which is easy to carry. Before I paint
                  bigger things, I’ll draw them bigger. Or, if I can find out the technique — I’ll
                  look into it — make what they call grisailles of them. </p>
            <p> It becomes too expensive a business if you’re not sparing with the paint. But, old
                  chap, it’s wonderful for me that I’ve once again been given so many good tools —
                  thanks again for everything. I’ll do my best to ensure that you need have no
                  regrets, but rather the satisfaction of seeing the progress made. I’m writing now
                  just for the time being to say that I’ve made a start. It goes without saying that
                  the studies must become more beautiful — and that certainly they have their
                  shortcomings too — but I believe that even in these first ones you’ll already see
                  that there’s something of the open air in them, something that proves I have a
                  feeling for nature and the heart of a painter. Herewith a small scratch of Laan
                  van Meerdervoort. The vegetable gardens there have a sort of Old Dutch cachet that
                  always appeals to me. Well, good-night, it’s late, with a handshake. </p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
            <p>I’m busy with Zola’s ‘La curée’. </p>

            <p>When I’d written this letter, I realized that it lacked something. I thought — I must
                  ensure that I can write to him that I’ve tackled a piece of sand, sea and sky like
                  we saw together at Scheveningen. Then I kept my letter back and marched off to the
                  beach this morning, and have just got back with a fairly large painted study of
                  sand, sea and sky, and a few fishing-boats and men on the beach. There’s still
                  dune sand in it, and I assure you this won’t be the last one. I thought you’d be
                  pleased that I’ve tackled this. </p>


            <p>As said, I want to make sure that when you come again, in six months or a few months
                  or a year, the studio has become a painter’s studio. These scratches were done in
                  great haste, as you can see. Now that it’s going well, I’ll try to strike while
                  the iron’s hot and carry on painting for a little. <stress reason="money">If you can send the usual
                  towards the 20th, there’s no question but that I’ll be able to occupy myself
                  exclusively with it for a while</stress>. I believe that after a month of regular painting
                  the studio will look completely different. Hoping that this will please you, I
                  shake your hand again, and warmly wish you good fortune in everything. </p>

      </ps>

   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Nuenen</location>, on or about Monday, <date>2 March 1885</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
        <p>
            <unstress reason="money">Thanks for the prompt dispatch of the money for this month, arriving promptly like that
            actually helps me more.</unstress> Thanks, too, for the splendid woodcut after Lhermitte — one of
            the few things by him that I know, for I saw only these — a troop of girls in the wheat
            — an old woman in church — and a miner or some such in a little bar, and Harvest by him,
            and otherwise never anything, and nothing ever as much reflecting his actual manner as
            these woodcutters.</p>
        <p>If Le Monde Illustré prints a composition by him every month — this is part of a series
            of ‘Rural months’ — it would give me mighty great pleasure to collect this whole series,
            and I’d really like you to send them every time.</p>
        <p>Because obviously I never see anything here, and after all I do need to see something
            really beautiful now and then, and so another time feel free to keep back 20 francs,
            say, but send me things like this when they appear in the illustrated magazines.Now as
            to when you write that if I had something ready that I thought was good, you would try
            to enter it for the Salon — I appreciate your wanting to do this. </p>
        <p>This in the first place — and then further that if I’d known it 6 weeks earlier, I would
            have tried to send you something for this purpose.</p>
        <p>Now, though, I don’t have anything that I would care to send in. Recently, as you know,
            <work origin="existing" stage="finished">I’ve painted heads almost exclusively. And they are studies in the true meaning of the
            word — that is, they’re meant for the studio.</work>
         </p>
        <p>Nonetheless, this very day I’ve started to make some that I’ll send you. </p>
        <p>Because I think it possible that it might be of use, when you meet a good many people on
            the occasion of the Salon, if you had something you could show — albeit only studies.So
            you’ll receive heads of an old and a young woman, and probably more than one of these
            two models. Given what you write of your feelings about various conceptions of heads, I
            think that these, which come straight out of a cottage with a mossgrown thatched roof,
            won’t appear to you to be absolutely inappropriate, although they’re studies and nothing
            else. If I’d known 6 weeks earlier, I would have made a woman spinning or spooling yarn
            — full length — of them.</p>
        <p>To return for a moment to that question of the female heads in the Jacquet genre, not the
            earlier ones but of the present day. The reaction against them — certainly with a motive
            — by people who paint heads of girls like our sisters, for instance — I can well
            understand that there are painters who do such things — Whistler did it well several
            times — Millais, Boughton — to mention only people by whom I saw something of the sort
            in the past. I know little by FantinLatour, but what I saw I thought very good.
            Chardinesque. And that’s a lot. For my part, though, I’m not the sort of character who
            has much chance of getting on a sufficiently intimate footing with girls of that sort
            that they’re willing to pose. Particularly not with my own sisters. And am possibly also
            prejudiced against women who wear dresses. And my province is more those who wear
            jackets and skirts.</p>
        <p>Though I think what you say about it is true — namely that it’s perfectly possible to
            paint them — and it has a raison d’être as a reaction against the presentday Jacquets
            and Van Beers.</p>
        <p>Just this, though — Chardin (let’s sum up the aim of the reaction in his name,
            FantinLatour, at least, would approve), Chardin was a Frenchman and painted French
            women. And in my view, respectable Dutch women like our sisters really do
            extraordinarily often lack the charm that the French frequently have.</p>
        <p>Consequently, the socalled respectable element among Dutch women isn’t really so very
            attractive — to paint or to think about. But certain common servant girls, on the other
            hand, are very Chardinesque.</p>
        <p>
            <stress reason="career">At present I’m painting not just as long as there’s light, but even in the evening by
            lamplight in the cottages, if I can somehow make things out on my palette, in order to
            capture if possible something of the singular effects of lighting at night, for instance
            with a large shadow cast on the wall.</stress>
         </p>
        <p>I’ve certainly not seen anything in the last few years as fine as those woodcutters by
            Lhermitte.</p>
        <p>How his little figures in that composition are felt and wanted.</p>
        <p>Thanks again for it.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Yours truly,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
        <p>The Chardinesque is, it seems to me, a singular expression of simplicity and of goodness
            — both through and through, and I find it a little hard to believe that one would find
            it in our sisters, say, either one of them. But if Wil were a Frenchwoman rather than a
            minister’s daughter, she could have it. But as good as always sails to the opposite
            point of the compass.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles,</location> 
         <date>on or about Monday, 10 September 1888.</date>
      </head> 
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Enclosed herewith letter from Gauguin,
  which arrived at the same time as a letter from Bernard. <stress reason="money">At last, it’s the cry of distress.... my
  debt is increasing from day to day.</stress> I won’t dwell on what he has to do. You offer him hospitality
  here, and you accept the only means of payment he has, his paintings. But if in addition to and
  apart from that, he demanded that you pay for his journey, he’s going a bit far, and at least he
  should very openly offer you some of his paintings, and appeal to you as well as to me in terms
  less vague than ‘my debt increasing from day to day, my journey is becoming more and more
  unlikely’. He would have a better sense of things if he said, I prefer to leave all my paintings
  in your hands, because you’re kind to me, and to run up debts with you, who are fond of me, rather
  than living with my landlord. But he has a stomach-ache, and when you have a stomach-ache, you
  don’t have free will.</p> 
         <p>Now I don’t have a stomach-ache, at present. <good_health>And as a result I feel my head
  freer, and I should hope more lucid.</good_health> I find it absolutely unfair that you, who’ve just sent the
  money that you yourself have had to borrow for furnishing the house, should also have to bear the
  expense of the journey, and especially when this journey is complicated by the payment of the
  debt. Unless Gauguin, sharing absolutely everything, were to give you the whole of his work. In
  such a way that, ceasing to keep count, we’d share absolutely everything. If we shared expenses
  and made common cause, I myself believe that everyone would profit from it after some years’
  working in common. Because, if the association is created under these conditions, you will feel, I
  don’t say happier, but more of an artist and more productive than with me alone. For him, as for
  me, we’ll feel very clearly that we must succeed, because the honour of all three of us is
  involved there, and because we’re not working just for ourselves. That seems to me to be the case.
  And I say to myself that even if we must tumble into the inevitability of things, we should still
  do it that way. </p>
         <p>But increasingly I’m dismissing the idea of that tumble when I think of the
  serenity that we see on faces in Frans Halses and Rembrandts, as in the portrait of old Six, as in
  his own, as in those Frans Halses that we know so well in Haarlem, of old men and old women.It’s
  better to have serenity than to be too fearful. Why, then, make such a noise on the subject of
  this affair with Gauguin? If he comes with the two of us he’ll do well, and we really want him to
  come. But neither he nor we should be crushed. Anyway, there’s a beautiful calm in his letter all
  the same. Although he leaves his intentions towards us unexplained. But if we wish to do this
  thing well, it will require loyalty on his part. I’m quite curious to know what he’ll write to you
  himself; I’ll reply to him exactly as I feel, but I don’t want to say melancholy or sad or mean
  things to so great an artist. But from the point of view of money, the affair is taking on serious
  proportions; there’s the journey, there’s the debt, and there’s the fact that the furnishing isn’t
  complete. Only it’s already complete enough that if Gauguin were to drop in here unexpectedly there
  would be a way to manage while waiting to get our breath back. Gauguin is married, and it’s very
  important to be aware beforehand that in the long run it’s not certain that different interests
  will be compatible. Now that’s why, in the case of some sort of association, we have to have the
  conditions settled well and clearly, precisely so that we don’t fall out later. If all goes well
  for Gauguin, you’ll see at this point that he’ll go back to his wife and children. Certainly I’d
  wish that for him. Ah well, we must therefore have more confidence in the value of his paintings
  than his landlord does, but he mustn’t calculate them to be so expensive to you that instead of
  your having some benefit from the association, you’d have nothing but responsibilities and costs.
  That must not be, and anyway, will not be. But you must have from him the best of what he has.</p>
         <p>I
  must warn you that I plan to keep several studies here at the studio, instead of sending them to
  you. I believe that if I very firmly continue this project of turning the house here into
  something that’s a little bit truly artistic, later on you’ll have a series of studies that will
  hold together. Russell replied, by the way — negatively as far as buying a Gauguin is concerned,
  but he invites me to spend some time with him, which would start and finish with costing the money
  for the journey. I’m not saying, though, that he won’t buy a Gauguin, because he himself will feel
  that he’s not being very helpful at present. But after all, by building himself a house, as long
  as he puts people up there, he’s doing the very thing that’s needed from the moment our landlords
  kick us out.</p> 
      </body>
      <close>More soon, and good handshake.</close> 
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Amsterdam</location>, Sunday,<date> 9 December 1877</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p> I feel the need to write to you without waiting too long, the reason being first of all that
      I must thank you for three things. <good_health>First of all, for your excellent fourpage letter, with
      which you gave me the greatest pleasure</good_health>, because it does one good to feel that a brother of
      his also walks and lives on earth, <stress reason="career">when one has a lot of things to think about and a lot to
      do, one sometimes gets the feeling, where am I? what am I doing? where am I going?</stress> — and one
      starts to grow dizzy — but then such a familiar voice, or rather familiar handwriting, makes
      one feel firm ground beneath one’s feet again, as it were. </p>
         <p> T<good_health>hen I must thank you for an issue of the Galerie Contemporaine about E. Frère. It’s very
      interesting and I’m happy to have something by him.</good_health> And I also thank you for the 10 postage
      stamps, it really is too much and you shouldn’t have done so much. A hearty handshake for
      everything. </p>
         <p> Now I have a few things to tell you about St Nicholas; I received a good letter from Etten
      with a money order for a pair of gloves enclosed. </p>
         <p> I already had some, however, so I bought something else with the money, namely another map
      by Stieler, namely Scotland alone. At present I can get them singly at Seyffardt’s, but there
      probably won’t always be that opportunity. I’ve drawn that map and so have it double, and
      because I did want to give Harry Gladwell a Christmas present I hope to send it to you for
      him, to enclose when a crate goes to Paris. one must build one’s house upon a rock, Scotland,
      Normandy and Brittany are really rather rocky, just take a look at that large map of Scotland
      when you get it. If I compare the work of studying to the building of a house, and these
      months to its foundation, then rocks accordingly lie at its base. </p>
         <p> But all of this by the by, now more about the evening in question. From Uncle Cor I received
      Bossuet, Or<good_health>aisons funèbres, in a very good and handy edition, very complete, it includes,
      among other things, the fine sermon about Paul on the text ‘for when I am weak, then am I
      strong’. It’s a noble book, you’ll see it at Christmas, I was so happy with it that until
      today I’ve been carrying it around in my pocket,</good_health> though it’s time I stopped that because
      something might happen to it. From Mendes I received the works of Claudius, also a good, solid
      book; I had sent him Thomae Kempensis de imitatione Christi and written in the front, There is
      neither Jew nor Greek in Him, neither bond nor free, neither male nor female: but Christ is
      all, and in all. From Uncle Stricker a box of cigars, you know what I did with them, they’re
      always so friendly at the Rooses’ and I’d already been wondering if I had anything to send
      when that box of cigars arrived as a godsend. And in the evening I found a letter from Uncle
      Jan lying on my table. Was then briefly at Vos and Kee’s, where Uncle and Aunt Stricker were
      as well, but couldn’t stay because I had a lesson from 810 with Teixeira. Uncle Jan spent the
      evening at Uncle Cor’s.Was at Uncle Stricker’s service this morning, i.e. in the Eilandskerk,
      Uncle Cor was there too. The text was ‘by Thy light shall we see light’. It’s always a nice
      walk to that Eilandskerk. This afternoon I took another walk around the little English church
      with those maps of those rocky countries, because I had a feeling that they were connected
      with that little church. </p>
         <p> ‘The Church of God stands on a rock’, those words were in this morning’s hymn, and that’s
      how Ruisdael painted it too, and Millet in the painting in the Luxembourg. </p>
         <p> It’s a good plan of yours to write those names etc. on the map of Brittany. Bring it along
      at Christmas, you know that I did that on the one I drew, then we can compare them. Be sure
      and do it, for that is good. </p>
         <p> You talk about my coming to The Hague again on my way to Etten, I should really like to,
      would it be possible to stay a night at the Rooses’? If so, then you do not have to write,
      then I’ll count on it being possible if necessary. I should like to see your room again and
      the tree with ivy, I hope that will be possible and that I can leave here early enough. </p>
         <p> I can’t tell you how much I long for Christmas. And may Pa be satisfied with what I’ve done. </p>
         <p>
            <unstress reason="environment"> It was such wonderful weather today, and so beautiful among those thornhedges by the little
      church when night began to fall.</unstress> 
         </p>
         <p> Had a talk with Mendes this week, or rather last week, about ‘He who hate not, even his own
      life also, he cannot be my disciple’. He declared that expression too strong, but I maintained
      that it was the simple truth, and doesn’t Thomas a Kempis say it when he talks about knowing
      oneself and despising oneself? </p>
         <p> 
            <bad_health>If we look at others who have done more and are better than we are, then soon enough we come
      to hate our own life because it’s not as good as that of others.</bad_health> Just look at a man like
      Thomas a Kempis, constrained by the love of Christ to write that little book, sincere and
      simple and true as few others were, either before or since. Or in another sphere, just take a
      look at the work of a Millet or that of a Stieler or The large oaks by Jules Dupré. They did
      it: ‘let your light shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your
      Father which is in heaven’, and Pa is such a man too; and however much we can do, you see, the
      best thing is to keep our sights on such people and to seek whether we too may perhaps find
      something. And to believe that it’s true what Pa said, that if someone asks ‘Lord, I should so
      much like to be earnest’, that it will be heard and granted by God. </p>
         <p> Have a good Sunday today, how I’d like to be with you, Uncle Jan has gone to Haarlem so I’m
      alone this evening, but still have to do as much as I possibly can. You have really given me
      such pleasure with that magazine on E. Frère. I once saw him myself at Goupil’s, he has
      something very unpretentious about him. ‘At last, he triumphed’ it says in his biography, may
      it be so with us one day — that can happen and it is good to say: I never despair. </p>
         <p> A person doesn’t get it all at once, and most of those who have become something very good
      have gone through a long, difficult period of preparation that was the rock upon which their
      house was founded. </p>
         <p> Man is depraved by nature, at best a thief — but — with God’s guidance and blessing he can
      become something of higher worth, as there came for Paul a day on which he could say with
      frankness and trust to Herod, I would to God, that not only thou, but also all that hear me
      this day, were such as I am, except these bonds. </p>
         <p> Thanks for what you write about the lithographs. Something else — <good_health>you also sent 2 pairs of
      Christus Consolator and pendant, I was very glad to get them.</good_health> It could do no harm if you also
      had that map of Scotland, then you would have three things from that atlas, and the proverb
      says: all good things come in threes. So count on getting that one too, and by no means buy it
      yourself, had first wanted to send you this one that is now going to Gladwell, but I consider
      it my duty to let him hear from me now and again. I hope he’ll be able to go to Lewisham at
      Christmas. You know that painting by Cuyp in the museum here, an old Dutch family, when he saw
      that he stood looking at it for a long time and then spoke of ‘the house built on the rock’
      and of his home in Lewisham. I, too, have memories of his father’s house and will not easily
      forget it. Much and strong and great love lives there under that roof, and its fire is in him
      still, it is not dead, but sleepeth. </p>
         <p> 
            <stress reason="career">Now I have to hurry, for I have to get to work.</stress> So in all likelihood I’ll be coming to The
      Hague next week for a day, Thursday say, possibly later, I have to see how it fits in best
      with my work. From The Hague I hope to go to Dordrecht, and if it turns out that you can leave
      Saturday evening, we’ll meet each other at the station in Dordrecht. </p>
         <p> In that case I would even spend two nights at the Rooses’, if I’m going to The Hague anyway,
      it can’t hurt to stay a bit longer and call on some people. </p>
         <p> A pity, in a way, that Mauve is going to move, I hope that we’ll go there again together,
      like that evening last spring, it was really pleasant then. </p>
         <p> Now make sure they don’t go to any trouble at the Rooses’. If I can’t stay there you’ll know
      it without asking them and can write to me, and I’ll take it into account; if I can, tell them
      only the day before. </p>
         <p> I wish you the very best and blessings in your work. You’ll be busy, but actually one should
      be grateful for pressure and effort and all suchlike things more than for anything else, for
      it is only by long training in that that one develops. I sincerely hope that you’ll be able to
      leave Saturday, because at home they’d surely like us to be in Etten the Sunday before
      Christmas. So goodbye for now, if I hear nothing more from you I’ll come on Thursday or
      Friday, 20 or 21 December. </p>
         <p> I finally decided to hang up that page again from Bargue’s Cours de dessin, Anne of
      Brittany, yes, man is depraved by nature and at best a thief, but in the battle of life he can
      become a being of higher worth; a being of higher worth, those words sprang to mind when I had
      been looking for a long time at the expression on the face of that beautiful woman Anne of
      Brittany, the expression which explains why she also recalls the words ‘one of Sorrows and
      acquainted with grief; sorrowful yet always rejoicing’. </p>
         <p>Adieu, give my regards to your housemates, and believe me</p>
      </body>
      <close> Your most loving brother </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Amsterdam</location>, Friday, <date>27 July 1877</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p> Thanks for your last letter, I heard from home that you’ve already been to Mauve’s, that was
      undoubtedly a good day, I’ll certainly hear about it sometime, when the opportunity arises.
      Herewith a contribution for your collection, namely three lithographs after Bosboom and two by
      J. Weissenbruch, found them this morning at a Jewish bookseller’s. Is that one after Bosboom
      the church in Scheveningen? The other is the Grote Kerk in Breda, the third after his painting
      that was at the large exhibition in Paris. <good_health>Those two after Weissenbruch moved me</good_health> – perhaps you
      already have them, but then again possibly not. Do go on collecting such prints, and books
      too. </p>
         <p> I’m now collecting Latin and Greek themes and all kinds of writings on history and so on. <work origin="new" stage="middle">Am
      working on one on the Reformation that’s getting rather long. </work>
         </p>
         <p> 
            <stress reason="career">Recently spoke to a young man who had just done his entrance examination for the Leiden
      college with a good result – it isn’t easy, he told me what they asked him, but I do keep up
      my courage, and with God’s help I’ll pass them,</stress> and the following examinations as well. Mendes
      has given me every reason to believe that at the end of three months we’ll be as far as he
      imagined we would be if everything went well. Still, Greek lessons in the heart of Amsterdam,
      in the heart of the Jewish quarter on a very warm and oppressive summer afternoon, with the
      feeling hanging over me that many difficult examinations will have to be taken, set by very
      learned and cunning professors, are rather more oppressive than a walk on the beach or in the
      Brabant wheatfields, which will certainly be beautiful now, on a day like that. But we must
      ‘strive on’ through everything, as Uncle Jan says. </p>
         <p> A couple of days ago a couple of children fell into the water near the Kattenburg bridge.
      Uncle saw it and commandeered the sloop of the Makasser that is in dock here. A little boy was
      pulled out; I went along with two ship’s doctors whom Uncle had sent over, and the men
      carrying the boy into a chemist’s shop made every effort to resuscitate the child, but to no
      avail. In the meantime it was recognized by the father, who’s a stoker at the dockyard, and
      the little body was taken home in a woollen blanket. The search went on for an hour and a
      half, as it was thought that a girl had fallen in as well, though happily that seems not to be
      the case. In the evening I went back to see the people, it was then already dark in the house,
      the little body lay so still on a bed in a side room, he was such a sweet little boy. <bad_health>There
      was great sorrow, that child was the light of that house, as it were, and that light had now
      been put out. Even though coarse people express their grief in a coarse way and without
      dignity, as the mother did, among others, still, one feels a great deal in such a house of
      mourning, and the impression stayed with me the whole evening when I took a walk.</bad_health> 
         </p>
         <p> 
            <unstress reason="environment">Last Sunday morning I made a nice excursion, namely first to the early sermon, the Rev.
      Posthumus Meijjes in the Noorderkerk, then to Bickerseiland, where I walked on the dyke along
      the IJ until it was time for church again, and then to the Eilandskerk where Uncle Stricker
      preached.</unstress> Thus the time passes, and quickly too, already we’re almost at the end of the week
      again.How are you, old chap? So very often, daily, do I think of you. </p>
         <p> God help us, struggling, to stay on top, it is good that you associate with good artists; I,
      too, still cling to the memory of many of them. Overcome evil with good, it is written, and
      one can seek to do it – and to this end God can help and make our days bearable with much good
      in the meantime, and preserve us from too much selfreproach. </p>
         <p> When Uncle Jan commandeered the sloop and the doctors to go and help on the afternoon that
      accident happened, I saw him in his element. </p>
         <p> Now I must get to work, though I still have to fill this page. Anna is in Leiden, as you
      surely know, and will come here one of these days with our future brotherinlaw, am looking
      forward to seeing them very much, Pa wrote so cheerfully about last Sunday when they were in
      Etten and everything was good in his eyes, and they see rightly, <good_health>so let us view what has
      happened to our sister as a blessing on our house, in which we all share; if one member be
      glad, let all the members be glad with her.</good_health> 
         </p>
         <p> Next week, or perhaps even tomorrow, Uncle and Aunt Pompe are coming to stay here, and also
      Fanny and Bet ’s Graeuwen, it’s been a long time since I’ve seen any of them. </p>
         <p> Am quite often up rather early in the morning, and when the sun rises over the yard and the
      workers come a while later it’s a wonderful sight from the window, and I should wish to have
      you here. <work origin="new" stage="planned">Will I later be working on such a morning on a sermon on ‘He maketh His sun to rise
      on the evil and on the good’, or on ‘Awake thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and
      Christ shall give thee light’, or on ‘It is a good thing to praise the Lord in the morning’
      and ‘It is a pleasant thing for the eyes to behold the sun’</work> – I hope so. </p>
         <p> All the same, <unstress reason="environment">it seems that the sun never shines so beautifully as it does in a parsonage or
      in a church. It’s wonderful to work on ‘the writings’ early in the morning.</unstress> 
         </p>
         <p>If you have the time and a stamp and paper, then write again soon. Uncle Jan sends you his
      regards, that evening you described there in the dunes must have been pleasant. <unstress reason="environment">In Uncle Cor’s
      shop I recently saw The Gospels by Bida, how beautiful it is, </unstress>how wonderful it must be to be a
      Christian labourer like that, but it’s impossible to put into words how beautiful it is,
      that’s it again, there is much in that work that reminds one of Rembrandt. And now a handshake
      in thought, and I sincerely wish you the best, and believe me ever</p>
      </body>
      <close> Your most loving brother </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles,</location> 
         <date>Sunday, 23 or Monday, 24 September 1888.</date>
      </head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>The fine weather of these past few
  days has disappeared and has been replaced by mud and rain. But it will surely return before the
  winter. Only it’ll be a matter of taking advantage of it because —the fine days — are short
  —Especially for painting. <work origin="new" stage="planned">I plan to do a lot of drawing this winter.</work> If only I could draw figures
  from memory, I’d always have something to do, but — take a figure by the most skilful of all the
  artists who sketch from life — Hokusai, Daumier, for me this figure is never what the figure
  painted from the model by these same masters would be, or other master portraitists. Ah well — if
  inevitably we’re too often faced with a shortage of models, and especially of intelligent models,
  we mustn’t despair or grow weary of the struggle for that reason.</p> 
         <p>I’ve arranged all the Japanese
  prints in the studio, and the Daumiers and the Delacroixs and the Géricault. If you come across
  the Delacroix Pietà, or the Géricault, I urge you to buy as many of them as you can. Another thing
  that I’d very much like to have in the studio is Millet’s Labours of the fields — and Lerat’s
  etching of his Sower that Durand-Ruel is selling for 1.25 francs. And lastly the little etching by
  Jacquemart after Meissonier, The reader. A Meissonier that I’ve always found admirable. I can’t
  help liking Meissoniers.</p> 
         <p>I’m reading an article on Tolstoy in the Revue des Deux Mondes — it
  appears that Tolstoy takes an enormous interest in his people’s religion. Like George Eliot in
  England. There’s said to be a religious book by Tolstoy, I believe it’s called ‘Ma religion’; it
  must be very beautiful. From what I gather from that article, in it he’s searching for what will
  remain eternally true in the religion of Christ, and what all religions have in common; it appears
  that he admits of neither the resurrection of the body nor even that of the soul, but says like
  the nihilists that after death there’s nothing more, but when a man’s dead, and well and truly
  dead, living humanity remains for ever. Anyway, not having read the book itself, I couldn’t say
  exactly how he conceives of the matter, but I believe that his religion cannot be cruel and
  increase our sufferings, but on the contrary, it must be very consoling and must inspire serenity,
  and energy, and the courage to live, and a whole lot of things.</p>
         <p>Among Bing’s reproductions I find
  the drawing of the blade of grass, and the carnations, and the Hokusai admirable. But whatever one
  may say, for me the more ordinary Japanese prints, coloured in flat tones, are admirable for the
  same reason as Rubens and Veronese. I know perfectly well that this isn’t primitive art. But the
  fact that the primitives are admirable isn’t in the very least a reason for me to say, as is
  becoming a habit, ‘when I go to the Louvre I can’t go beyond the primitives’. Supposing one were
  to say to a serious collector of Japanese art — to Lévy himself — sir, I cannot help finding these
  5-sous Japanese prints admirable — It’s more than likely that that person would be a bit shocked
  and would pity my ignorance and my bad taste. Exactly as in the past it was in bad taste to like
  Rubens, Jordaens, Veronese. <stress reason="environment">I believe that eventually I’ll stop feeling lonely in the house,</stress> and
  that on days of bad winter weather, for example, and in the long evenings, I’ll find an occupation
  that will absorb me completely. A weaver, a basket-maker, often spends entire seasons alone, or
  almost alone, with his work as his only pastime. But what makes those people stay where they are
  is precisely the feeling of the house, the reassuring, familiar look of things. Of course I’d like
  company, but if I don’t have it I won’t be unhappy on that account, and then, above all, the time
  will come when I’ll have someone. I have little doubt about that.</p>
         <p>Now in your home too, I believe
  that if one is willing to put people up one can find plenty among artists, for whom the matter of
  somewhere to stay is a very serious problem. And for me, I believe that it’s my absolute duty to
  try to earn money with my work, and so I see my work quite clearly ahead of me. Ah, if only all
  artists had enough to live on — enough to work on — but that not being so, <work origin="new" stage="planned">I wish to produce, and
  to produce a great deal, and with intense effort and determination.</work> And perhaps the day will come
  when we can expand our business and be more influential for others. But that’s a long way off, and
  there’s a great deal of work to be got through first. If we were living in wartime we’d possibly
  have to fight, we’d regret it, we’d bemoan not living in peacetime, but at all events, the
  necessity being there — we’d fight. And in the same way, we surely have the right to wish for a
  state of affairs in which money wouldn’t be needed in order to live. However, since everything’s
  done with money now, we must think hard about making some while we spend it. But I have a better
  chance of earning from painting than from drawing. In short, there are many more people who can
  skilfully make a croquis than people who can paint freely and who grasp nature from the point of
  view of colour. That will always be rarer, and whether or not the paintings are slow to be
  appreciated, they’ll find their collector one day. But I believe that as for the paintings with
  rather thick impasto, they’ll have to dry longer here. I’ve read that Rubenses in Spain have
  remained infinitely richer in colour than those in the north. Ruins, even exposed to the open air,
  remain white here, whereas in the north they turn grey, dirty, black, &amp;c. You can be sure that
  if the Monticellis had dried in Paris they’d now be very much duller.</p> 
         <p>I’m beginning now to see
  better the beauty of the women here, and so always, always I think again of Monticelli. Colour
  plays an immense part in the beauty of the women here — I’m not saying that their forms aren’t
  beautiful, but that’s not where the local charm lies. It’s the broad lines of the colourful
  costume, worn well, and it’s the tone of the flesh more than the form. But I’ll have trouble
  before I’ll be able to do them in the way I’m beginning to feel it. But what I’m certain of is
  making progress while staying here. And a certain skilfulness isn’t enough to make a painting that
  would be truly of the south. It’s looking at things for a long time that matures you and makes you
  understand more deeply. I hadn’t thought when leaving Paris that I would have found Monticelli and
  Delacroix so true. It’s only now, after months and more months, that I’m beginning to realize that
  they didn’t imagine anything. And I think that next year you’ll see the same subjects again:
  orchards, the harvest, but — with a different colour and above all, altered execution. And that
  will still continue, these changes and these variations. Even while working, I feel that I needn’t
  rush. After all, what would it do to put into practice the old saying that one should study for
  ten years or so, and then produce a few figure paintings? That’s what Monticelli did, though.
  Think of several hundred of his paintings as no more than studies. Then, however, figures the way
  the yellow woman was, the way the woman with the parasol is, the small one that you have, the
  lovers that Reid had, those are complete figures, in which as far as the drawing goes there’s
  absolutely nothing to do but to admire it. Because there Monticelli achieves a way of drawing
  that’s as rich and superb as Daumier and Delacroix. Certainly, at the prices Monticellis are at,
  it would be an excellent speculation to buy some. The day will come when his fine drawn figures
  will be valued as very great art. I believe that the town of Arles was once infinitely more
  glorious for the beauty of its women, for the beauty of its traditional dress. Now it all looks
  sickly and faded as far as character goes. But if you look at it for a long time, the old charm
  reveals itself. And that’s why I understand that I’m losing absolutely nothing by staying where I
  am, and contenting myself with watching things go by, the way a spider in its web waits for flies.
  I can’t force anything, and as I’m settled now I can take advantage of all the fine days, all the
  opportunities to catch a real painting from time to time.</p>
         <p>Milliet’s lucky, he has all the
  Arlésiennes he wants, but there you are, he can’t paint them, and if he was a painter he wouldn’t
  have any. I must bide my time now, without rushing anything. I’ve read an article on Wagner —
  L’amour dans la musique, by the same author who wrote the book on Wagner, I believe. What a need
  we have of the same thing in painting! It seems that in the book Ma religion, Tolstoy suggests
  that whatever may occur in the way of a violent revolution, there will also be a private, secret
  revolution in people, from which a new religion, or rather, something altogether new, will be
  reborn, which will have no name but which will have the same effect of consoling, of making life
  possible, that the Christian religion once had. It seems to me that that book must be very
  interesting. We’ll eventually have enough of cynicism, scepticism, mockery, and we’ll want to live
  — more musically. How will that come about, and what will we find? It would be curious to be able
  to predict it, but it’s even better to have a feeling of what it will be, instead of seeing in the
  future absolutely nothing but disasters, which will nevertheless be sure to fall into the modern
  world and civilization like so many terrible thunderbolts, through a revolution or a war or the
  bankruptcy of moth-eaten governments. If we study Japanese art, then we see a man, undoubtedly
  wise and a philosopher and intelligent, who spends his time — on what? — studying the distance
  from the earth to the moon? — no; studying Bismarck’s politics? — no, he studies a single blade of
  grass. But this blade of grass leads him to draw all the plants — then the seasons, the broad
  features of landscapes, finally animals, and then the human figure. He spends his life like that,
  and life is too short to do everything. Just think of that; isn’t it almost a new religion that
  these Japanese teach us, who are so simple and live in nature as if they themselves were flowers?
  And we wouldn’t be able to study Japanese art, it seems to me, without becoming much happier and
  more cheerful, and it makes us return to nature, despite our education and our work in a world of
  convention. Isn’t it saddening that up to now Monticellis have never been reproduced in fine
  lithographs or vibrant etchings? I’d like to see what artists would say if an engraver like the
  one who engraved the work of Velázquez were to do a fine etching of them. Be that as it may, I
  believe it’s still more our duty to try to admire and to know things for ourselves than to teach
  them to others. But the two things can go together. I envy the Japanese the extreme clarity that
  everything in their work has. It’s never dull, and never appears to be done too hastily. Their
  work is as simple as breathing, and they do a figure with a few confident strokes with the same
  ease as if it was as simple as buttoning your waistcoat. Ah, I must manage to do a figure with a
  few strokes. That will keep me busy all winter. Once I have that, I’ll be able to do people
  strolling along the boulevards, the streets, a host of new subjects. While I’ve been writing you
  this letter, I’ve drawn a good dozen of them. I’m on the track of finding it. But it’s very
  complicated, because what I’m after is that in a few strokes the figure of a man, a woman, a kid,
  a horse, a dog, will have a head, a body, legs, arms that will fit together.</p>
      </body>
      <close>More soon, and good handshake.</close>
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</location>, on or about Friday, <date>2 May 1890</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p>
            <good_health>Once again I’m writing to you to say that I’m staying well</good_health>, yet<stress reason="environment"> I feel a little worn
                  out by this long crisis, </stress>and I dare believe that the planned move will refresh my
                  ideas more.</p>
            <p>I think that it’ll be best for me to go myself to see this doctor in the country as
                  soon as possible; then we can soon decide if I’m going to lodge with him or
                  temporarily at the inn; and thus we’ll avoid an overlong stay in Paris, a thing
                  that I would fear. You remember that 6 months ago I told you after a crisis that
                  if it happened again I would ask you to let me move? <bad_health>We’re at that point –
                  although I don’t feel capable of passing judgement on the way they have of dealing
                  with the patients here – it’s enough that I feel that what remains to me of reason
                  and capacity for work is absolutely in danger. </bad_health>While, on the contrary, I’m
                  confident that I can prove to this doctor you speak of that I still know how to
                  work logically, and he’ll treat me accordingly, and since he likes painting
                  there’s sufficient chance that a solid friendship will result from it.</p>
            <p>I don’t think Mr Peyron will oppose a very prompt departure. Besides, I tell myself
                  that the pleasure of spending a few days with you will do me a lot of good. And
                  from that moment on we can really count on a period of relative health. So don’t
                  delay in taking the necessary steps so that this doesn’t drag on. Once I’m there I
                  can send for my bed, which is in Arles.</p>
            <p>
            <stress reason="environment">Besides, I would move anyway, preferring to be in an asylum where the patients worked
                  to this awful idleness here, which really seems to me quite simply a crime.</stress>
                  Anyway, you’ll tell me that this is seen more or less everywhere, and that there’s
                  even plenty of it in Paris. Whatever the case, I hope that we’ll see each other
                  again very soon.</p>
            <p>The etchings you sent me are really beautiful. Opposite this I’ve scribbled a croquis
                  after a painting I’ve done of three figures which are in the background of the
                  Lazarus etching.</p>
            <p>
            <work origin="new" stage="finished">The dead man and his two sisters.The cave and the corpse are violet, yellow, white.
                  The woman who is taking the handkerchief from the resurrected man’s face has a
                  green dress and orange hair, the other has black hair and a striped garment. Green
                  and pink. Behind a countryside, blue hills, a yellow rising sun. The combination
                  of colours would thus itself speak of the same thing expressed by the chiaroscuro
                  of the etching.</work> If I were still to have at my disposal the model who posed for the
                  Berceuse and the other whose portrait you’ve just received after Gauguin’s
                  drawing, then certainly I’d try to execute it in a large size, this canvas, the
                  personalities being what I would have dreamed of as characters. But leaving aside
                  subjects of this kind, there will still remain the study from life of peasants and
                  landscapes when I’m back in the north.</p>
            <p>As regards the order for colours. Should I remain here for another few days, please
                  send off part of it at once. If, however, I leave in the next few days – which I
                  hope – you can keep it in Paris.</p>
            <p>In any event, write to me in the next few days; I hope that you’ll have received the
                  canvases in good order. <work stage="finished" origin="new">I’ve done another one of a nook of greenery which seems to
                  me to have some freshness.</work> 
            <work origin="new" stage="middle">I’ve also attempted a copy of Delacroix’s Good
                  Samaritan. </work>I think from a note in Le Figaro that père Quost must have a darned
                  good painting in the Salon.</p>
            <p>Warm regards to your wife, I’m very much looking forward to making her acquaintance
                  at last, and good handshake in thought.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>The Hague</location>, Sunday, <date>29 September 1872</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear brother </salutation>
      <body>
        <p>After a last discussion with Mr Peyron I obtained permission to pack my trunk, which I’ve
            sent by goods train. The 30 kilos of luggage one is allowed to take will allow me to
            take a few frames, easel and some stretching frames.</p>
        <p>I’ll leave as soon as you’ve written to Mr Peyron,<good_health> I feel calm enough, and I don’t think
            that a mental upset could easily happen to me in the state I’m in.</good_health>
         </p>
        <p>In any event, I hope to be in Paris before Sunday to spend the day, which you will have
            off, quietly with all of you. I really hope to see André Bonger too at the first
            opportunity.</p>
        <p>I’ve also just finished a canvas of pink roses against yellowgreen background in a green
            vase.I hope that the canvases of the last few days will compensate us for the expenses
            of travel.</p>
        <p>This morning, as I’d been to have my trunk stamped, I saw the countryside again – very
            fresh after the rain and covered in flowers – how many more things I would have
            done.</p>
        <p>I’ve also written to Arles for them to send the two beds and the bed linen by goods
            train. I estimate that this can only cost a good ten francs in transport charges, and
            it’s still something gained from the debacle. For it’ll certainly be useful to me in the
            country.</p>
        <p>If you haven’t yet replied to Mr Peyron’s letter, please send him a telegram, in such a
            way that I may make the journey on Friday or Saturday at the latest to spend Sunday with
            you. In doing so I’ll also lose the least time for my work, which is finished here for
            the moment.</p>
        <p>In Paris, if I feel up to it, <work origin="new" stage="planned">I’d immediately very much like to do a painting of a yellow
            bookshop (gas effect), which I’ve had in my mind for so long. You’ll see that I’ll be at
            work right from the day after my arrival. </work>
            <good_health>I tell you, as regards work, my mind feels
            absolutely serene and the brushstrokes come to me and follow each other very
            logically.</good_health>
         </p>
        <p>Anyway until Sunday AT THE LATEST, I shake your hand firmly in the meantime, warm regards
            to Jo.</p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours,</close>
      <sig>Vincent.</sig>
      <ps>
        <p>Probably the answer to Mr Peyron will already have left, which I hope. I was a little
            vexed that there were a few days’ delay, because that seems to me to be of no use for
            anything. For either I’d plunge into new works here, or it’s now that I have the leisure
            for the journey. <stress reason="environment">Spending days doing nothing, here or elsewhere, that’s what would make
            me miserable in my current state of mind. </stress>
            <unstress reason="friendship">Besides, Mr P. isn’t opposed to it, but
            naturally when you leave, your position is a little difficult with the rest of the
            administration. But it’s going well, and we’ll part amicably.</unstress> 
         </p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles,</location> 
         <date>Tuesday, 18 September 1888.</date>
      </head> 
      <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
      <body>
            <p>Many thanks
      for your letter and for the 50-franc note it contained. I’ve also received Maurin’s drawing,
      which is superb. That man’s a great artist. Last night I slept in the house, and although
      there are still things to be done, <good_health>I feel very happy there.</good_health> Besides, I feel that I can make
      something of it that will last, and from which someone else will also be able to benefit. Now
      money spent will no longer be money wasted, and I believe it won’t be long before you see the
      difference there. At present it makes me think of Bosboom’s interiors, with the red tiles, the
      white walls, the furniture in deal or walnut, the patches of intense blue sky and greenery
      visible through the windows. Now the surroundings, with the public garden, the night cafés,
      the grocer’s shop, aren’t Millet, of course, but failing that, it’s pure Daumier, pure Zola.
      Now that’s quite enough to find ideas in, isn’t it? </p>
         <p> I already wrote to you yesterday that, if
      I count the two beds at 300 francs, the price can’t be reduced any further. If, however, I’ve
      already bought more than that, it’s because, if I already put half of last week’s money into
      it, yesterday I had to pay another 10 francs to the lodging-house keeper and 30 francs for a
      palliasse. At the moment I have 5 francs left in my pocket. So I’m going to ask you to send me
      another louis, depending on what you can manage — but by return of post — to see me through
      the week, or 50 francs, if it’s possible. One way or another, this month I’d like to be able
      to count on receiving 100 instead of 50, again, over the whole month, as I asked you in my
      letter yesterday. If I save 50 francs over the month myself, if I add to that the other 50, it
      means that in total I’ll have spent 400 francs on furniture. <unstress reason="environment">My dear Theo, here we are, at
      last, more on the right road!</unstress> It’s true that it doesn’t matter not having hearth nor home as
      long as you’re young, and living like a traveller, in cafés, but that was becoming intolerable
      to me now, and most of all, it wasn’t compatible with thoughtful work. So my plan is all
      worked out. I’ll try to do painting for what you send me every month, and then I want to do
      painting for the house. What I do for the house will be to reimburse you for previous
      expenditure. I’m still something of a tradesman, in fact, in the sense that I’m anxious to
      prove that I pay my debts, and know what I want for the merchandise that the lousy trade of a
      poor painter forces me to labour at.</p> 
         <p>Ah well, I feel more or less sure of succeeding in making
      a decoration that will be worth 10 thousand francs in time. Let me say — If here we set up a
      studio-refuge for one or other of our pals who are broke, no one will ever be able to reproach
      us, neither you nor me, with living and spending for ourselves alone. Now to set up such a
      studio you need a working capital; now it’s I who have eaten it up in the course of my
      unproductive years, and I’ll pay it back now that I’m beginning to produce. I assure you that,
      for you as well as for me, I judge it to be indispensable, but what’s more our right, always
      to have a louis or a few louis in our pocket, and a certain stock of merchandise to handle.
      But my idea would be that in the end we’d have set up and would leave to posterity a studio in
      which a successor could live. I don’t know if I’m expressing myself clearly enough, but in
      other words: we’re working at an art, at matters that won’t be of our times only but which may
      also be continued by others after us. You’re doing that in your business; it’s undeniable that
      it will increase in future, even though you have many vexations at present. But for me, I
      foresee that other artists will wish to see colour under a stronger sun and in a more Japanese
      clarity. Now if I set up a studio-refuge right at the entrance to the south, that’s not so
      silly. And precisely that means that we can work calmly. Ah, if others say, it’s too far from
      Paris &amp;c.? Let them, too bad for them. Why did the greatest colourist of all, Eugène
      Delacroix, judge it indispensable to go to the south, and as far as Africa? Obviously because
      not only in Africa but even from Arles onwards you’ll naturally find fine contrasts between
      reds and greens, blues and oranges, sulphur and lilac. And all true colourists will have to
      come to admit that there exists another coloration than that of the north. And I don’t doubt
      that if Gauguin came, he would love this part of the country; if Gauguin didn’t come, it’s
      because he has already had this experience of more colourful countries, and he’d still be one
      of our friends and in agreement in principle. And another one of them would come in his place.
      If what we’re doing looks out toward the infinite, if we see our work having its raison d’être
      and continuing on beyond, we work with more serenity. Now you have that twice over. </p>
         <p>You’re kind
      to painters, and be sure that the more I think about it the more I feel that there’s nothing
      more genuinely artistic than to love people. You’ll say to me that then we’d do well to do
      without art and artists. That’s true on the face of it, but after all, the Greeks and the
      French and the old Dutchmen accepted art, and we see art always recover after inevitable
      periods of decline — and I don’t believe that we’d be more virtuous for this reason, that we
      had a horror of artists and their art. At present I don’t yet find my paintings good enough
      for the benefits I’ve had from you. But once they’re good enough, I assure you that you will
      have created them just as much as I, and the fact is that we make them together. But I won’t
      labour the point, because it will become as clear as daylight to you if I succeed in doing
      things a little more seriously. <work origin="new" stage="middle"> moment I have another no. 30 square canvas on the go,</work> a
      garden again, or rather a walk under plane trees, with green turf and black clumps of pines.
      You did very well to order the colours and the canvas, because the weather is superb, superb.
      The mistral is still there, but there are intervals of calm, and then it’s wonderful. If we
      had less mistral, this part of the country would really be as beautiful, and would lend itself
      as much to art, as Japan. As I write, very kind letter from Bernard, who’s thinking of coming
      to Arles this winter — whim — but then, perhaps it’s also that Gauguin is sending him to me as
      a substitute, and would himself prefer to stay in the north. We’ll know soon, because I’m sure
      that he’ll write to you one way or another. Bernard’s letter speaks of Gauguin with great
      respect and sympathy, and I’m convinced that they have mutually understood one another. And I
      certainly believe that Gauguin has done Bernard good. Whether Gauguin comes or not, he’ll
      still be one of our friends, and if he doesn’t come now he’ll come at another time. I
      instinctively feel that Gauguin is a calculating person, who, seeing himself at the bottom of
      the social ladder, wishes to regain a position by means that will be honest, to be sure, but
      which will be very shrewd. Gauguin has little idea that I’m able to take account of all that.
      And he perhaps doesn’t know that he must at all costs gain time, and that he’ll gain it with
      us, if he were to gain nothing else thereby. Now if one of these days he does a bunk from
      Pont-Aven with Laval or Maurin without paying his debt, in my opinion he would still be in the
      right in his case, just like any animal at bay. I don’t believe that it’s wise to offer
      Bernard 150 francs for one painting a month immediately, as we’ve offered Gauguin. And isn’t
      Bernard, who has clearly talked at length with Gauguin about the whole business, rather
      counting on replacing Gauguin? I believe that it’ll be necessary to be very firm and very
      categorical in all of this. And without giving our reasons, to speak very clearly. I can’t
      blame Gauguin — speculator, stockbroker — if he wishes to risk something in business, only I
      myself wouldn’t be part of it, I’d a thousand times sooner continue with you, whether you’re
      with the Goupils or not. And the new dealers are, as you know full well, exactly the same as
      the old ones in my opinion. In principle, in theory, I’m for an association of artists
      protecting their livelihood and their work, but in principle and in theory I’m equally against
      attempts to destroy old firms, once established. Just let them rot in peace and die a natural
      death. It’s pure presumption to try to revive the trade. Have nothing to do with it, protect
      your livelihoods among yourselves, live as a family, as brothers and companions; splendid;
      even in a case where that didn’t succeed, I’d like to be part of it, but I’ll never be part of
      a manoeuvre against other dealers.</p>
      </body> 
      <close>I shake your hand firmly; I hope that what I’m forced to
      ask of you won’t cause you too much financial trouble. But I didn’t want to delay going to
      sleep at my house. And if you’re in financial difficulties yourself, I’ll get through the week
      with 20 francs more, but that will be urgent. </close>
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>The letter that Gauguin will
      send you shortly will, I’m inclined to believe, clear the matter up. I myself don’t blame an
      artist of his merit for saying, you’ll pay my journey and my debt if you wish me to come,
      because I don’t have any — any money. But on the other hand, in that case he’d have to be very
      generous with his paintings. Then — but we’d still have to have the money — I wouldn’t see any
      harm in the thing. But these paintings, which will be sold one day, will tie up the interest
      on what they cost, perhaps for many years to come. And in fact, a painting for which we pay
      400 francs today and which we sell for 1,000 francs ten years later is still sold at cost
      price, because it has sat there doing nothing. But you know this better than I do. I shouldn’t
      be surprised if little by little you regain a love of business, or at least that you’ll be
      reconciled with your present position when you’ll feel that those who invent new things in
      business don’t know how to make a great revolution in it. You’re kind to artists, you are, in
      fact, right at the heart of the trade, you do what you can, you’re damned right. Only take
      care of your health if you can, and don’t get upset about nothing. That will come quite of its
      own accord now, if it must come. I only want to emphasize this, that it seems to me that
      Gauguin, by giving you alone his paintings on deposit, and quietly waiting for his moment
      while working here with me and repaying our advances with his work, would be pursuing a policy
      that I would respect more than any other position he could take.For Bernard, if Bernard wished
      to come here, it wouldn’t be on the same conditions as Gauguin — it would seem to me. If there
      was a benefit in living together, there’s nothing to prevent you agreeing to buy something
      from him from time to time, if it’s possible. But no sort of contract with him, he’s too
      changeable. If Gauguin doesn’t come, he’ll succeed all the same, but he won’t succeed through
      his contrivance, but through the real merit of his canvases. As long as he keeps the time and
      the money and the freedom needed to do them, that’s all. I can assure you that I would
      certainly not be a better dealer than you; in the given circumstances you do perfectly well,
      and I’d only wish to send you better paintings. I’m trying to do that, and I’ll continue to
      try to do so. I expect to return to my garden canvas again soon. It’s an immense advantage
      that I have, not to be short of canvases and colours, and so it’s certainly my duty to work
      without respite. If Gauguin came, I’m inclined to believe that we’d make our colours at home
      ourselves; I daren’t do it on my own, because I fear that it would discourage me if it didn’t
      work straightaway. I’m very curious to know what Tanguy will charge for his tubes. Did you
      read an article in the number of Le Courrier Français that you sent, ‘la truie bleue’? Very
      good, and it reminds you precisely of La Segatori. You’ll enjoy reading that article. I’ll see
      Milliet today, I think. Thank you in advance for the Japanese prints. I’m keeping all Bernard’s
      letters, they’re sometimes really interesting; you’ll read them some day or other; they
      already make quite a bundle.This firmness I was speaking of, that it will be necessary to have
      with Gauguin, it’s solely because we already made our position clear when he described his
      plan of action in Paris. You replied well then without committing yourself, but also without
      wounding him in his amour propre. And it’s the same thing that could be necessary again.</p>
      </ps> 
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Arles,</location> 
         <date>Sunday, 26 August 1888.</date>
      </head> 
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation> 
      <body>
         <p>Many thanks for your letter and for the 50-franc note
  it contained. Certainly, it isn’t impossible that our sister will come later and live with us.
  It’s a good sign as far as her taste goes that she likes sculpture; that really did please me.
  Painting as it is now promises to become more subtle — more music and less sculpture — in fact, it
  promises colour. As long as it keeps this promise. <work origin="existing" stage="middle">The sunflowers are progressing; there’s a new
  bouquet of 14 flowers on a green-yellow background, so it’s exactly the same effect — but in
  larger format,</work> no. 30 canvas — as a still life of quinces and lemons that you already have, but in
  the sunflowers the painting is much simpler.</p> 
         <p>Do you remember that one day at the Hôtel Drouot we
  saw a bouquet of peonies by Manet? Pink flowers, very green leaves, painted in thick impasto and
  not glazed, like Jeannin’s. Standing out against a simple white background, I believe. Now there’s
  something that was really healthy. As for stippling, making halos or other things, I find that a
  real discovery, but it can already be foreseen that this technique won’t become a universal dogma
  any more than another. Another reason why Seurat’s La Grande Jatte, Signac’s landscapes with
  coarse stippling, Anquetin’s boat, will in time become even more personal, even more original.</p>
         <p>As
  far as my clothes are concerned, they were certainly starting to suffer — but only last week I
  bought a black velvet jacket of quite good quality for 20 francs, and a new hat, so that’s not at
  all urgent. <work origin="new" stage="finished">But I consulted this postman whom I painted,</work> who has very often set up his little
  household and dismantled it again, moving house for roughly the price of the indispensable pieces
  of furniture, and he says that here you can’t get a good bed that will last, for less than 150
  francs, if you want to have something solid, of course. However, that hardly upsets the
  calculation that by saving the money for lodgings, at the end of a year you find you own furniture
  without having spent any more during the year. And as soon as I’m able, I won’t hesitate to do
  that. If we were to refrain from setting ourselves up like that, Gauguin and I could drag on from
  year to year in small lodgings where one can’t fail to become dull-witted. I’m more or less that
  way already, because it goes back a long, long way. <stress reason="environment">And at present that has even ceased to be a
  source of pain, and perhaps at first I won’t feel at home in my own home.</stress> Never mind.</p> 
         <p>However,
  let’s not forget Bouvard et Pécuchet, let’s not forget À vau l’eau, because all of that is very,
  very profoundly true. Au bonheur des dames and Bel-ami, that’s no less true, however. It’s ways of
  seeing things — now, with the first one, we’re less in danger of behaving like Don Quixote; it’s
  possible, and with the last idea we go the whole hog. Now I have the old peasant again this week.
  Ah — Macknight has cleared off at last — I don’t regret it in the least. His pal the Belgian
  didn’t seem greatly saddened by it either when he came yesterday to tell me about it, and we spent
  the evening together. He’s very reasonable in his ideas, and knows what he wants, at least. At the
  moment he’s doing timid Impressionism, but very much by the rules, very exact. And I told him that
  it was the best thing he could do, although he would lose 2 years on it perhaps, delaying his
  originality, but after all, I told him, it’s as necessary now to pass through Impressionism
  properly as it once was to go through a Paris studio. He accepted that absolutely in its entirety,
  precisely because that way you shock nobody, and you can’t later be accused of not being abreast
  of things. He’s thinking seriously of going to paint the coal-miners in the Borinage, and if he’s
  still here when Gauguin comes, not impossible then that we’ll ask him to do for us in the north
  what we’d do for him in the south — do our utmost to enable him to live more cheaply than on his
  own.</p>
      </body>
      <close>More soon.</close>
      <sig>Ever yours, Vincent</sig>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location>Amsterdam</location>, Tuesday, <date>30 October 1877</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
         <p>Thanks for your last letter, which I was glad to get. Yes, old boy, that etching after Jules
      Goupil is beautiful and forms, with all that’s associated with it, a fine and good whole that
      is a thing to keep in one’s heart. I rather envy your having read Carlyle, ‘French
      Revolution’, it’s not unknown to me but didn’t read all of it, I found parts of it in another
      book, namely by Taine. </p>
         <p> 
            <work origin="new" stage="middle">Am busy making an extract from Motley, including capture of Den Briel and siege of Haarlem,
      Alkmaar and Leiden, have drawn a map to go with it,</work> so as to complete it. <work origin="new" stage="finished">Have also finished
      an extract from Bunyan’s Pilgrim’s progress.</work> 
            <stress reason="career">Am working all the time, day in, day out, so some
      things do get done.</stress> 
         </p>
         <p> I keep my work together, everything <stress reason="career">aimed at getting through the exams</stress>, I consult Mendes on
      everything, and model my studies on what he has done, for that is how I’d like to do it too.
      That history of the 80 Years’ War is really wonderful, anyone would do well to make such a
      good fight of his life. <stress reason="career">Truly life is a fight, and one must defend oneself and resist and make
      plans and calculations with a cheerful and alert mind in order to make it through and get
      ahead. It becomes no easier the further one gets in life</stress>, and it has been rightly said: </p>
         <p>Does the road go uphill then all the way? ‘Yes to the very end’ And will the journey take all
      day long? ‘From morn till night, my friend.’</p>
         <p>
            <good_health>But by fighting the difficulties in which one finds oneself, an inner strength develops from
      within our heart,</good_health> which improves in life’s fight (one matures in the storm), if we always
      endeavour to keep that heart out of which are the issues of life, good and simple and rich
      toward God, to restore that and make it thus more and more, and to bear in mind the words that
      we must have a good conscience before God and before people. </p>
         <p> As we regard others so are we regarded by many eyes. It is from the conscience — God’s
      finest gift, and the proof that His eye is upon us, allseeing and allknowing, and also the
      assurance that He be not far from every one of us, but as our shade upon our right hand, and
      that He keeps us from the evil — that our light comes in the darkness of life and of the
      world. And if we feel an eye watching us, as it were, then it is good to gaze upward sometimes
      as though seeing Him who is invisible.I know that life of Frederick the Great illustrated by
      Menzel, that’s a good acquisition, do go on with that collection; I also know that woodcut
      after Jacque, The sheepfold, do bring those things home with you at Christmas. </p>
         <p> Have bought from the Jew that lithograph after L. Steffens of which you once showed me the
      painting, an old and a young priest conversing in a garden, it’s a good lithograph. The scene
      reminds me of a painting by Jacquand, photographed in the cartes de visite, it’s called ‘The
      new vicar’, I believe, it has the same sentiment, and also of The novice by G. Doré. </p>
         <p> 
            <stress reason="career">Old boy, Latin and Greek and studying are difficult</stress>, but a<good_health>ll the same I feel very happy with
      it and am doing the things I have longed for.</good_health> I’m no longer allowed to sit up late in the
      evenings, Uncle has very strictly forbidden it — yet the words written below the etching by
      Rembrandt stick in my mind, In medio noctis vim suam lux exerit (In the middle of the night
      the light diffuses its strength) and I make sure that a small gaslight goes on burning the
      whole night, and lie looking at it often in medio noctis, <good_health>thinking about my plan for work the
      following day and considering how to go about that studying as well as possible.</good_health> Hope in the
      winter to light the fire early in the morning (and while obeying Uncle yet letting the light
      shine in the night and darkness once in a while). The winter mornings have something special
      about them, Frère painted that in that workman, ‘A cooper’ (the etching is hanging in your
      room, I believe), among other things. </p>
         <p> Fill my soul with a holy bitterness that shall be agreeable to Thee, and I shall humbly
      spend all the years of my life in Thy service, in the bitterness of my soul, yea, even in Thy
      Service, O Man of sorrows and acquainted with grief. That is certainly a good prayer, and I
      thought of it when I told you in simplicity that it was good to steep oneself in coffee in
      everyday life. </p>
         <p> A person has needs, and requires strength and fortification to be able to work. And one must
      make do with what one has and fight with such weapons as are within one’s reach, and use the
      means at one’s disposal to make the most of it and gain from it. </p>
         <p> (You can see from my handwriting that it had grown dark, but now the lamp is on.) Ate
      hotchpot at Uncle Stricker’s one afternoon, and it occurred to me on that occasion to make
      that extract from Motley, I’ll show it to you at Christmas. Because here in town I’ve seen and
      walked over so awfully many doorsteps and church floors and flights of steps up to houses, it
      occurred to me to make those maps of rocky Scotland, and while colouring them in (green and
      red) I thought of those pickles that Uncle is so fond of and I’ve grown fond of too. A
      person’s soul is a singularly strange thing, and it is good, I think, to have one like a map
      of England made with love and to have in it as much as possible of that love which is holy and
      beareth all things and believeth all things and hopeth all things and endureth all things and
      never faileth.<good_health> That Love is the Light of the world, the true life that is the light of men.
      The knowledge of languages is certainly a good thing to have, and I follow after in the hope
      that I might also grasp something of it.</good_health> 
         </p>
         <p> When one eats a crust of black rye bread it’s certainly good to think of the words ‘Tunc
      justi fulgebunt ut sol in regnum Patris sui’ (Then shall the righteous shine forth as the Sun
      in the Kingdom of their Father), or also when one very often has muddy boots or wet, dirty
      clothes. May we all at sometime enter into that kingdom which is not of this world, where they
      do not marry and are not given in marriage, where the sun shall be no more thy light by day,
      neither for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee, but the Lord shall be an
      Everlasting Light, and God our glory, where the sun shall no more go down, neither shall the
      moon withdraw itself, for the Lord shall be thine Everlasting Light, and the days of mourning
      shall be ended and God shall wipe away all tears from the eyes. And so we can be leavened with
      the leaven of ‘sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing’, being what we are through God’s grace, having
      in the secret recesses of the heart the words ‘I never despair’ because we have faith in God.
      And then ‘Set your face as a flint’ are really good words in many circumstances, and also ‘be
      like an iron pillar or like an old oak tree’. It’s also good to love thorns, such as the
      thornhedges around the little English church or the roses in the cemetery, they’re so
      beautiful these days, yes, if one could make oneself a crown of the thorns of life, not for
      the people but with which one is seen by God, then one would do well. </p>
         <p> I imagine you know the woodcuts by Swain, he’s a clever man, his studio is in such a nice
      part of London, not far from that part of the Strand where the offices of the illustrated
      magazines are (Ill. Lond. News, The Graphic, Seeley), not far from Booksellers’ Row either,
      full of all kinds of bookstalls and shops where one sees all kinds of things, from the
      etchings of Rembrandt to the Household edition of Dickens and Chandos classics, everything
      there has a green cast (especially in foggy weather in the autumn, or during the dark days
      before Christmas), and it’s a place that immediately reminds one of Ephesus, as it is
      described with such singular simplicity in Acts. (Similarly, the bookshops in Paris are also
      so interesting, in the Faubourg St Germain, for instance.) </p>
         <p> 
            <stress reason="career">Old boy, how inexpressibly happy I’ll be if I manage to pass my exams, if I conquer the
      difficulties it will be done in singleness of heart,</stress> but also with prayer to God, for I so
      often pray fervently to Him for the wisdom I’m in need of, and that He may one day grant that
      I write and deliver many sermons, the more like our Father’s the better, and to complete a
      Work in my life to which end all things work together for good. </p>
         <p> I was at Uncle Cor’s on Monday evening, and also saw Aunt and the whole family, all send you
      their warm regards. Stayed rather a long time because I hadn’t seen Aunt for a long time and
      one offends so easily without meaning to by giving the impression of not appreciating and of
      neglecting people. Looked through that book at Uncle’s, the engraved oeuvre of C. Daubigny.
      Went from there to Uncle Stricker’s, Uncle was out but a son of the Rev. Meyboom was visiting
      (brother of Margreet), an officer in the Navy, and his girlfriend and a young man, Middelbeek,
      who has been in London for a while and is going back there.At 10 o’clock Uncle came home
      soaking wet, for it was raining quite a lot that evening, and I had a long talk with him and
      Aunt, because Mendes had paid them a visit a couple of days ago (one shouldn’t utter the word
      genius lightly, even if one believes that there is more of it in the world than many people
      think, but Mendes certainly is a very remarkable person, and I’m happy and grateful for my
      contact with him) and hadn’t given them a bad report, fortunately, but <stress reason="career">Uncle asked me if it
      wasn’t difficult, and I admitted that it was very difficult and that I was doing my best to
      bear up and to be alert in all kinds of ways.</stress> He gave me encouragement, however. But now
      there’s still that terrible algebra and geometry, anyway, we’ll see — after Christmas I have
      to have lessons in those as well, there’s nothing for it. </p>
         <p> I also cling to the church and to the bookshops, if I can think of an errand to do there I
      do it. Today, for instance, I was at Schalekamp’s and at C.L. Brinkman’s in Hartestraat (that
      shop of Schalekamp’s is an interesting sight) and bought a couple of maps from the Teachers’
      Society, of which there are around 100 at a stuiver apiece, including the Netherlands in every
      possible historical period. (So often, in the past as well, a visit to a bookshop has cheered
      me up and reminded me that there are good things in the world.) </p>
         <p> 
            <unstress reason="environment">Sunday morning I went to the early service and afterwards to the French church, where I
      heard an outstanding sermon from the Rev. Gagnebin</unstress>: the house at Bethany. ‘One thing is
      needful and Mary hath chosen that good part’. That Rev. Gagnebin has a pleasant appearance and
      a worthy head, and his face has something of the Peace of God which passeth all understanding.
      He does have something, I think, either of that priest in The last victims of the terror or of
      that humble and faithful manservant one sees in ‘The women of the boardinghouse’. </p>
         <p> That painting by Israëls you describe must be beautiful, I can picture it from your clear
      description. Saw a small painting of his at C.M.’s, also one by Mauve, very beautiful,
      shepherd with flock of sheep in the dunes. </p>
         <p> A good cheerful letter from home too, fortunately things seem to be going better in
      Princenhage. I’m longing not a little for Christmas, do bring one thing and another with you,
      as much as possible, it’s good for all of us. Don’t be in a hurry to send the tobacco; still
      have some, it’s a good and necessary aid to study. </p>
         <p> Wrote a long letter to Harry Gladwell that went off today, also sent your regards. If you
      have the time and the opportunity, think of Michelet, you know what, and J. Breton, but you
      know what it’s for and that there’s no hurry, and if necessary Christmas is soon enough. Now,
      I must get to work and the sheet of paper is nearly full, I wish you well, write if possible,
      I gave Uncle the receipt enclosed in your letter. Uncle sends you his regards, also Uncle and
      Aunt Stricker. Bid your housemates goodday from me, and should the opportunity arise also
      Mauve and his wife and the Tersteegs and Van Stockums (how is she?) and Haanebeeks, and
      Borchers if you run into him. Blessings on everything you do, I wish you strength and vigour
      in these autumn days, and let it be Christmas again with us together again before we know it,
      as it were, adieu, a handshake in thought, and believe me ever </p>
      </body>
      <close>Your most loving brother</close>
      <sig>Vincent.</sig>
      <ps>
         <p>Saw 2 photos of Gabriel Max, the raising of Jairus’ daughter and a nun in a convent garden,
      the first one, in particular, was beautiful.Do you know an engraving after Landseer? It’s
      called The highlander, I believe, a highlander in a snowstorm on top of a mountain holding an
      eagle he’s shot.</p>
      </ps>
   </letter>
   <letter>
      <head>
         <location> The Hague </location>
         <date>26 July 1882. Wednesday morning</date>
      </head>

      <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
      <body>
         <p>It matters greatly to me that you shouldn’t get the idea that I’m in a dejected or abnormal
      mood. That’s why I wrote to you already about work in my last letter, and since I have a few
      more things to ask in that connection I haven’t waited long before writing again. By the time
      you come I’ll do my best to have several watercolours done in different ways ready for you to
      see, then we can discuss which seems best to you.</p>
         <p>So I’ll work regularly on <work origin="new" stage="middle"> this every day, and continue to do so until you come. I now have 3
      of Scheveningen — again the Fish-drying barn you know — drawn in as much detail — only now
      there’s colour as well</work>. As you well know, Theo, it isn’t harder to work in colour than in
      black and white, the opposite perhaps, but as far as I can see 3/4 comes down to the original
      sketch, and almost the whole watercolour depends on its quality. It isn’t enough to give an
      approximation, and my aim has been and still is to make it more intense. I believe that’s
      already evident in the black-and-white fish-drying barns, because there you can follow
      everything and see how it all fits together, and look, I think this is why I now work much
      more fluently in watercolour, because for such a long time I did my best to draw more
      correctly. </p>
         <p>Tersteeg said that what I was doing was a waste of time; soon you’ll see that I’ve saved a
      great deal of time. I already feel that, and you’ll see it for yourself when you come. </p>
         <p> This evening I went from one shop to another searching for thick Ingres, but in vain. They
      have the thin, but the dense or double is nowhere to be found. At the time I bought all that
      Stam had left, and it was wonderfully mature. Before you come, oh do your best to find some
      once more. And if you can’t get any, try asking for ‘papier de la forme’. That is with a
      yellowish tint — stiff — and you can use wash on it. I believe it’s also much cheaper than
      Harding or Whatman,<unstress reason="money"> so that in the end there’s quite a saving</unstress>. When you come I know of a few
      lovely paths through the meadows where it’s so quiet and peaceful that you’ll be delighted.
      I’ve discovered old and new labourer’s cottages there, and other houses that are distinctive,
      with small gardens lining the banks of the ditch — really charming. I’m going to draw there
      early tomorrow morning. It’s a path through the meadows from Schenkweg to Enthoven’s factory
      or Het Zieke. I saw a dead pollard willow there, just the thing for Barye, for example. It
      hung over a pond with reeds, all alone and melancholy, and its bark was scaled and mossy, as
      it were, and spotted and marbled in various tones — something like the skin of a snake,
      greenish, yellowish, mostly dull black. With white flaking spots and stumpy branches. I’m
      going to attack it tomorrow morning. I’ve also done a bleaching ground at Scheveningen, on the
      spot in one go, entirely in wash almost without preparation, on a very coarse piece of
      torchon. <work stage="sketch" origin="new">Here are a couple of small sketches of it.</work> I’ll make sure that several things are
      ready by the time you come. I think you’ll like the Fish-drying barn now that it’s with
      colours. </p>
         <p>Make no mistake, old chap, I’m fully back into my normal routine, and rest assured that
      everything else depends on work, and I see everything as directly related to that. The new
      studio makes a huge difference compared to the previous one in that it’s more pleasant to work
      in; for posing, especially, it’s a great improvement because one can stand further back. I’m
      sure it will be well worth the extra rent. I have one request for you, though. I would
      entirely understand and would find it quite natural if, instead of sending the money on 1
      August, you were to give it to me yourself when you arrive on, say, 7 August. As soon as I
      received your last letter, however, I made some purchases of paper and paint and brushes, and
      by 1 August I’ll certainly need some more things. So I want to ask you to be so kind as to
      send something all the same just before 1 August, if possible, even though you’ll be coming
      soon afterwards, because I’ve worked it out exactly, exactly, and after the first few days of
    <stress reason="money">  August I’ll certainly be absolutely broke</stress>. I hope this won’t inconvenience you: of course,
      more is not the intention; it’s the time that matters, namely 1 August, if possible, and
      otherwise only a few days later. I also have a second of the Rijswijk meadows in which the
      same subject takes on an entirely different aspect through being seen from a different height
      and viewpoint. As you see, I’ve become very caught up in landscapes. The reason is that Sien
      can’t pose yet, but otherwise the figure must remain the chief concern. </p>
         <p>When you come I’ll take care to be close to home as long as you’re in the city and that you
      know where I am, and otherwise I’ll carry on with my normal routine while you do your business
      and pay visits. I can find you wherever you suggest a meeting, but for various reasons I
      believe it’s better for both of us if I don’t go with you to the Plaats, say, or to Mauve, for
      example. I’m so used to my working clothes, in which I can sit or lie in the sand or grass as
      I please (for in the dunes, for example, I hardly ever use a chair, except perhaps an old fish
      basket), that my outfit is rather too Robinson Crusoe-like for me to accompany you much on
      your rounds. I say this in advance so that you’ll know I won’t be an embarrassment to you, but
      otherwise you understand that I long for every half hour you can spare. I think we’ll be more
      at ease if we’re completely taken up by painting and drawing, and talk mainly about that.
      Unless you’re not bored or embarrassed by other matters, if not, then of course I have no
      secrets from you, and you have my complete confidence in everything. I also long to show you
      the woodcuts. I have another splendid one, a drawing by Fildes, ‘Dickens’s empty chair’ from
      The Graphic of 70. I could have bought 3 etchings by Meryon for 2 guilders for all three, but
      I let them go. They were good though, but I have so few etchings and want to concentrate on
      woodcuts if I buy anything else. But I wanted to tell you about them — Blok has them, and I
      don’t know if all Meryons are rare and valuable. They’re from an old volume of L’Artiste. I’m
      still under the spell of Zola’s books. How painted those Halles are. <good_health>My health is good</good_health>, though
      I still feel the odd thing and will probably continue to do so, at least for some time yet.
      Sien and the child are also well; they’re getting stronger and <unstress reason="love">I love them dearly</unstress>. I must have
      another go at the cradle (when it’s a rainy day and I can’t go outside), entirely in
      watercolour. But for the rest, when you come I want to show you — landscape watercolours —
      nearer winter I hope to have figure watercolours, that is, after I’ve been here a year. First
      I’ll have to draw more nudes and a lot more in black and white, it seems to me. We’ll discuss
      all that, and I don’t doubt that your visit will be a great help in keeping things in order
      and making work go smoothly. Adieu, with a handshake. </p>
      </body>
      <close>Ever yours, </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>






      <ps>

         <p>By quietly carrying on with my work I have every hope I’ll gradually acquire a new circle of
      friends to make up for the <stress reason="friendship">loss of the friendliness of Mauve, HGT and others</stress>. But I’ll take no
      steps to bring that about, none at all, for it must come through the work. What has happened
      to me with H.G.T. is nothing out of the ordinary; everyone experiences things like that in
      life. It’s impossible to say exactly what the cause is. But in the case of H.G.T. it’s an old
      grievance. I know now with near certainty that he said things about me long ago which did much
      to cast me in a bad light. However, I needn’t be concerned about that — what could hurt me in
      the past can’t do so now. When you come to the studio you’ll see for yourself how utterly
      absurd it is for him to say: oh, your drawing will never amount to anything. But it’s
      difficult to counter a pronouncement like that, because as soon as one does so it’s seen as
      conceit, and people cite the very greatest names and say: he thinks he’s so-and-so or
      so-and-so. </p>
         <p>But, again, anyone who works with love and with intelligence has a kind of armour against
      people’s opinion in the sincerity of his love for nature and art. Nature is severe and hard,
      so to speak, but never deceives and always helps you to go forward. So I don’t count it a
      misfortune if I find myself out of favour with HGT or anyone else, however much I regret it.
      That can’t be the direct cause of unhappiness — if I felt no love for nature and my work, then
      I would be unhappy. But the less I get on with people the more I learn to trust nature and to
      concentrate on it. All these things make me fresher and fresher inside — you’ll also see that
      I’m not afraid of a fresh green or a soft blue and the thousand different greys, for there’s
      hardly any colour that isn’t a grey: red-grey, yellow-grey, green-grey, blue-grey. This is
      what all colour mixing comes down to. When I went back to the Fish-drying barn, a luxuriant
      and indescribably fresh green from a wild vegetable or oilseed had shot up in the baskets
      filled with sand in the foreground that serve to stop the sand of the dunes blowing about. Two
      months ago it was all barren except for a bit of grass in the small garden, and now that
      rough, wild, luxuriantly sprouting green produced a most pleasant effect as a contrast to the
      bareness of the rest. I hope you’ll like that drawing. The vista — the view over the roofs of
      the village with the small church tower and the dunes — was so attractive. I can’t tell you
      with how much pleasure I drew it. So come soon — I believe you’ll be completely content with
      the change of studio when you see how infinitely better it is for my work — more space, better
      light, greater distance. </p>





         <p>Yesterday evening I got a parcel from home. Among other things, it contained a sort of
      demi-saison which is very useful. It was very kind of them. And there were tobacco and cigars,
      a cake and underwear. In short, a whole package. Don’t you think that’s kind? It’s more that
      I’m pleased by it showing their warm feelings than by anything else. I’ve also had another
      letter from Rappard.<unstress reason="friendship"> I take enormous pleasure in the fact that that chap is so fascinated by
      his English woodcuts.</unstress> I got him going in the beginning, but now he needs no further
      encouragement; <unstress reason="environment">now he’s almost as enthusiastic as I am. </unstress>
         </p>
         <p>When you come I’ll show you a few prints which, once seen, won’t lightly fade from memory.
      Among them there are things very different from the school of Boughton, say, although he’s
      certainly one of the leaders. I mean things remarkable at once for their reality and their
      style, drawn like Albrecht Dürer but with lots of local colour and chiaroscuro. You don’t
      often see those prints any more these days; for you have to look for them in magazines of 10
      or 15 years ago. For example, during the war of 70-71. </p>
      </ps>
   </letter>