

<letter>
    <salutation> Dear brother and sister,</salutation>
    <p>Jo’s letter was really like a gospel for me, a deliverance from anguish which I was caused by
        the rather difficult and laborious hours for us all that I shared with you. It’s no small
        thing when all together we feel the daily bread in danger, no small thing when for other
        causes than that we also feel our existence to be fragile. </p>
    <p> Once back here I too still felt very saddened, and had continued to feel the storm that
        threatens you also weighing upon me. What can be done – you see I usually try to be quite
        good-humoured, but my life, too, is attacked at the very root, my step also is faltering. I
        feared – not completely – but a little nonetheless – that I was a danger to you, living at
        your expense – but Jo’s letter clearly proves to me that you really feel that for my part I
        am working and suffering like you.</p>
    <p>There – once back here I set to work again – the brush however almost falling from my hands
        and – knowing clearly what I wanted I’ve painted another three large canvases since then.
        They’re <work origin="new" completion="done">immense stretches of wheatfields under
            turbulent skies</work>, and I made a point of trying to express sadness, extreme
        loneliness. You’ll see this soon, I hope – for I hope to bring them to you in Paris as soon
        as possible, since I’d almost believe that these canvases will tell you what I can’t say in
        words, what I consider healthy and fortifying about the countryside. </p>
    <p>Now the third canvas is <work origin = "new" completion ="done">Daubigny’s garden</work>, a painting I’d been thinking about
        ever since I’ve been here. I hope with all my heart that the planned journey may provide you
        with a little distraction.</p>
    <p>I often think of the little one, I believe that certainly it’s better to bring up children
        than to expend all one’s nervous energy in making paintings, but what can you do, I myself
        am now, at least I feel I am, too old to retrace my steps or to desire something else. This
        desire has left me, although the moral pain of it remains. </p>
    <p>I very much regret not having seen Guillaumin again, but it pleases me that he’s seen my
        canvases.</p>
    <p>If I’d waited for him I would probably have stayed to talk with him in such a way as to miss
        my train.</p>
    <p>Wishing you luck and good heart and relative prosperity, please tell Mother and Sister
        sometime that I think of them very often, besides this morning I have a letter from them and
        will reply shortly. Handshakes in thought. </p>
    <close>Ever yours, </close>
    <sig>Vincent</sig>

</letter>
