<?xml-model href="../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
    <head>Arles, Tuesday, 5 or Wednesday, 6 June 1888.</head>


    <salutation>My dear Theo —</salutation>
    <body>
        <p>If Gauguin wants to accept, and if the only obstacle to going into business would be the
            travel, it’s better not to keep him waiting. So I’ve written, although I hardly had the
            time, having two canvases on the easel. If you think the letter’s clear enough, send it,
            if not, it would be better for us, too, to abstain when in doubt. And the things you
            would do for him shouldn’t upset the plan to bring our sisters over, and especially not
            our needs, yours and mine. Because if we ourselves don’t keep ourselves in a state of
            vigour, how can we claim the right to get involved in other people’s troubles? But at
            present we’re on the way to remaining vigorous, and so let’s do the possible, what’s
            right in front of us.<work stage="sketch" origin = "new"> I’m sending you enclosed herewith canvas sample for Tasset</work>;
            however, I don’t know if we should go on with his canvas.</p>
        <p>If you send me the next letter by Sunday morning, I’ll probably go off to Saintes-Maries
            again at 1 o’clock that day and spend the week there. I’m reading a book about Wagner
            which I’ll send you afterwards — what an artist — one like that in painting, now that
            would be something. It will come. Do you know that at 6 rue Coëtlogon, rue de Rennes, on
            7 and 8 June from 1 to 7 o’clock there’s an exhibition of paintings and drawings by
            Régamey that could be very interesting; now there’s two who’ve travelled all over the
            place, he and his brother.</p>
        <p>Handshake.</p>
    </body>

    <close>Ever yours, </close>
    <sig>Vincent.</sig>


    <ps>
        <p>I believe in the victory of Gauguin and other artists — but — between then and now
            there’s a long time, and even if he had the good fortune to sell one or two canvases —
            it would be the same story. While waiting, Gauguin could peg out like Meryon,
            discouraged. It’s bad that he’s not working — well, we’ll see his reply. </p>
    </ps>
</letter>
