<?xml-model href="../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
      <head><location>Paris</location>,<date> 6 July 1875 </date></head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo, </salutation>
      <body>
            <p>Thanks for writing, yes, old boy, I thought so. You must write and tell me sometime
                  how your English is, have you done anything about it? If not, it’s not such a
                  great disaster. I’ve rented a small room in Montmartre which you’d like; it’s
                  small, but overlooks a little garden full of ivy and Virginia creeper. I want to
                  tell you which prints I have on the wall.</p>

            <p>Ruisdael The bush ditto Bleaching fields Rembrandt Reading the Bible (a large, old
                  Dutch room, (in the evening, a candle on the table) in which a young mother sits
                  beside her child’s cradle reading the Bible; an old woman listens, it’s something
                  that recalls: Verily I say unto you, ‘for where 2 or 3 are gathered together in my
                  name, there am I in the midst of them’, it’s an old copper engraving, as large as
                  ‘The bush’, superb). </p>
            <p>P. de Champaigne Portrait of a lady Corot Evening ditto ditto Bodmer Fontainebleau
                  Bonington A road Troyon Morning Jules Dupré Evening (resting place) Maris
                  Washerwoman ditto A baptism Millet The four times of the day (woodcuts, 4 prints)
                  Van der Maaten Funeral in the cornfield Daubigny Dawn (cock crowing) Charlet
                  Hospitality. Farmhouse surrounded by fir trees, winter scene with snow. A peasant
                  and a soldier before a door. Ed. Frère Seamstressesditto A cooper</p>


            <p>Well, old boy, keep well, you know it, longsuffering and meek, as much as possible.
                  Let us remain good friends. </p>
      </body>
      <close>Adieu</close>

      <sig>Vincent</sig>
</letter>
