
<?xml-model href="../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
      <head><location>Amsterdam</location>, Sunday, <date>10 February 1878</date>.</head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body>
            <p> It’s Sunday evening, and I want to write a few words again, for I also really long
                  to get another letter from you, do write again soon, I am with you so often in
                  thought. I sincerely hope that you’ve had a good Sunday. </p>
            <p> <good_health>As you know, Pa was here and I’m very glad of it, we went together to Mendes, Uncle
                  Stricker, Uncle Cor, Vos and Kee and both Meijjes families, and the most pleasant
                  memory of Pa’s visit is that morning we spent together in my study, looking over
                  my work and talking about all sorts of things.</good_health> You can imagine that those days
                  flew by and when, after bringing Pa to the station and watching the train or even
                  only the smoke for as long as it was in sight, <bad_health>I came back to my room and Pa’s
                  chair was standing there by the little desk on which the books and notebooks were
                  still lying from the day before, even though I know that we’ll see each other
                  again quite soon, I broke down and cried like a child.</bad_health> </p>
            <p> You’ll already have heard that Mendes made a favourable impression on Pa as well. In
                  the evening, at Uncle Cor’s, we saw drawings and books, including Doré’s Bible and
                  Bida’s Le livre de Ruth and Histoire de Joseph. </p>
            <p> <unstress reason="friendship">Was in the English church this morning and met Wierda upon leaving the church, who
                  had been there too. We went for a walk together and he asked me if I’d like to
                  come and see his room,</unstress> he lives in Weteringstraat, about 10 minutes from
                  Leidsestraat. I told him that for a long time I had wanted to see his room and
                  where and how he lived, so <unstress reason="friendship">I went along and after drinking coffee I stayed till
                  around 3 o’clock and saw his books and heard a thing or two about his life, where
                  he had been previously and so on</unstress>, first he was in Bolsward, then in Haarlem and
                  then here. He has worked hard in his life and will probably continue to do so and
                  not give it up easily. Afterwards, at home, translated a passage from Caesar, and
                  this afternoon to Uncle Stricker’s, I go there rather often now that Uncle is out
                  of town and now that it’s lonely again here in the house since Pa left. This
                  evening they went to see Vos, who isn’t any better. </p>
            <p> I still have to congratulate you on Pa’s birthday, even though it’s already been and
                  gone, it will have been a good day, with Anna there too, I’m longing for a letter
                  from home to hear how they celebrated that day. Anna was slightly indisposed and
                  hadn’t yet recovered completely, she wrote in a letter that Pa received here.
                  Perhaps Pa read Ma’s letter aloud to you, which she wrote while Pa was here, it
                  told about a visit to a sick person which sounded like something out of Adam
                  Bede.It’s foggy here today, fortunately Pa had good weather so that we could walk
                  quite a lot. </p>
            <p> I’m reminding you of that piece by Jules Breton, not that there’s any hurry, but try
                  and remember it sometime. </p>
            <p> Because in March you’ll probably make the trip again, won’t you, and also come here
                  again? </p>
            <p> Uncle Jan will most likely come back on Tuesday. </p>
            <p> You’ll certainly have a lot to do at the beginning of the year, like most people.
                  Wierda, too, unburdened himself on that score this morning. </p>
            <p> <stress reason="career">For me, too, things are beginning to get more and more serious as the exam
                  approaches.</stress> <good_health>I’ll be glad when it grows light a bit earlier in the morning and
                  we’re already beginning to get used to it.</good_health> </p>
            <p> Did Pa remember to give you the photograph of the Maris? The woodcut after Van
                  Goyen, Dordrecht, is hanging in its place. Went recently to see that painting
                  again here in the museum, it is good through and through. The next time you come
                  here I’d like to look through the etchings by Dürer here in the museum again, as
                  we did with Rembrandt’s last time. </p>
            <p> It’s no doubt beautiful in Scheveningen on these grey days, do you still go there
                  quite often? Perhaps it’s like that painting by Ruisdael in the museum in The
                  Hague. Do you have the lithograph of it that was once in the Kunstkronijk? It’s
                  really good. </p>
            <p> How are things going at Mauve’s? Very well, I hope. Have you been there recently? </p>
            <p> I’m currently taking lessons from Uncle Stricker once or twice a week, that is a
                  bonus. Uncle is an expert in it, and I’m glad he could find the time to do it. </p>
            <p> Now, old boy, a hearty handshake in thought, I’ll set to work, give my regards to
                  your housemates, and also to Mauve if you run into him, I wish you the very best,
                  write soon, also congratulations on Anna’s birthday, even though it’s still to
                  come, and believe me ever</p>
      </body>
      <close>Your loving brother </close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps>
            <p>Goodnight, old boy, I sat up writing till 12 o’clock, a handshake in thought.</p>
      </ps>
</letter>
