<?xml-model href="../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
      <head><location>Arles</location><date>18 December 1888</date></head>
      <salutation>My dear Theo,</salutation>
      <body><p>Yesterday Gauguin and I went to Montpellier to see the museum there, and especially the
            Bruyas room — there are many portraits of Bruyas, by Delacroix, by Ricard, by Courbet,
            by Cabanel, by Couture, by Verdier, by Tassaert, by others too. After that there are
            paintings by Delacroix, Courbet, Giotto, Paul Potter, Botticelli, T. Rousseau, very
            fine.</p>
      <p>Bruyas was a benefactor to artists, and this is all I’ll say to you: in the Delacroix
            portrait, he’s a gentleman with a beard, red hair, who looks damnably like you or me,
            and who made me think of that poem by Musset... everywhere I touched the earth, an
            unfortunate man dressed in black came to sit beside us, a man who looked at us like a
            brother. It would have the same effect on you, I’m sure.</p>
      <p> I’d really ask you to go and see, at that bookshop where they sell lithographs of ancient
            and modern artists, if you could manage to get the lithograph after Delacroix’s ‘Tasso
            in the madhouse’ without great expense, since it would seem to me that this figure (by
            Delacroix) must have some relationship to this fine Bruyas portrait. </p>
      <p>They have other Delacroixs there, a study of a mulatto woman (which Gauguin once copied),
            the Odalisques, Daniel in the lions’ den.</p>
      <p>By Courbet, first, The village girls, magnificent, a nude woman seen from the back, another
            on the ground, in a landscape. Second, The woman spinning (superb), and a whole load
            more Courbets. Anyway, you must know that this collection exists, or else know people
            who have seen it, and consequently be able to talk about it. So I shan’t insist on the
            museum (except for the Barye drawings and bronzes!)</p>
      <p>Gauguin and I talk a lot about Delacroix, Rembrandt &amp;c.</p>
      <p><unstress reason="friendship">The discussion is excessively electric. We sometimes emerge from it with tired minds, like
            an electric battery after it’s run down.</unstress></p>
      <p>We’ve been right in the midst of magic, for as Fromentin says so well, Rembrandt is above
            all a magician and Delacroix a man of God, of God’s thunder and bugger off in the name
            of God. </p>
      <p>I’m writing this to you with reference to our friends, the Dutchmen De Haan and Isaäcson,
            who have so sought and loved Rembrandt, in order to encourage you to pursue the
            researches.</p>
      <p>One mustn’t get discouraged about that. You know the strange and superb portrait of a man
            by Rembrandt at the La Caze gallery, I told Gauguin that, for me, I saw in it a certain
            family or racial resemblance to Delacroix, or to him, Gauguin.</p>
      <p>I don’t know why, but I always call that portrait ‘the traveller’ or ‘the man coming from
            far away’.</p>
      <p>That’s an equivalent and parallel idea to what I’ve already told you, always to look at the
            portrait of old Six. The fine portrait with the glove for your future, and the Rembrandt
            etching, Six reading by a window in a ray of sunlight, for your past and your
            present.</p>
      <p>That’s the stage we’re at.</p>
      <p><unstress reason="friendship">Gauguin said to me this morning, when I asked him how he felt: ‘that he could feel his old
            self coming back’, which gave me great pleasure.</unstress></p>
      <p><bad_health>As for me, coming here last winter, tired and almost fainting mentally, I too suffered a
            little inside before I was able to begin to remake myself.</bad_health></p>
      <p>How I’d like you to see that museum in Montpellier some day, there are some really
            beautiful things there!</p>
      <p>Say so to Degas, that Gauguin and I have been to see the portrait of Bruyas by Delacroix at
            Montpellier, for we must boldly believe that what is, is, and the portrait of Bruyas by
            Delacroix resembles you and me like a new brother.</p>
      <p>As regards setting up a life with painters as pals, you see such odd things and I’ll end
            with what you always say, time will tell.</p>
      <p>You can tell all this to our friends Isaäcson and De Haan, and even boldly read them this
            letter, I would already have written to them if I’d felt the necessary electric
            force.</p>
      <p>On behalf of Gauguin as well as myself, a good, hearty handshake to you all.</p></body>
      <close>Ever yours,</close>
      <sig>Vincent</sig>
      <ps><p>If you think that Gauguin or I have a facility in our work, the work isn’t always
            accommodating. And for the Dutchmen not to get discouraged in their difficulties any
            more than we do, that’s what I wish for them, and for you too.</p></ps>
</letter>
