<?xml-model href="../../letter_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
    <head>The Hague, Sunday, 29 September 1872.</head>
    <salutation>My dear brother </salutation>
    <body>
        <p>After a last discussion with Mr Peyron I obtained permission to pack my trunk, which I’ve
            sent by goods train. The 30 kilos of luggage one is allowed to take will allow me to
            take a few frames, easel and some stretching frames.</p>
        <p>I’ll leave as soon as you’ve written to Mr Peyron,<good_health> I feel calm enough, and I don’t think
            that a mental upset could easily happen to me in the state I’m in.</good_health></p>
        <p>In any event, I hope to be in Paris before Sunday to spend the day, which you will have
            off, quietly with all of you. I really hope to see André Bonger too at the first
            opportunity.</p>
        <p>I’ve also just finished a canvas of pink roses against yellowgreen background in a green
            vase.I hope that the canvases of the last few days will compensate us for the expenses
            of travel.</p>
        <p>This morning, as I’d been to have my trunk stamped, I saw the countryside again – very
            fresh after the rain and covered in flowers – how many more things I would have
            done.</p>
        <p>I’ve also written to Arles for them to send the two beds and the bed linen by goods
            train. I estimate that this can only cost a good ten francs in transport charges, and
            it’s still something gained from the debacle. For it’ll certainly be useful to me in the
            country.</p>
        <p>If you haven’t yet replied to Mr Peyron’s letter, please send him a telegram, in such a
            way that I may make the journey on Friday or Saturday at the latest to spend Sunday with
            you. In doing so I’ll also lose the least time for my work, which is finished here for
            the moment.</p>
        <p>In Paris, if I feel up to it, <work origin="new" stage="planned">I’d immediately very much like to do a painting of a yellow
            bookshop (gas effect), which I’ve had in my mind for so long. You’ll see that I’ll be at
            work right from the day after my arrival. </work><good_health>I tell you, as regards work, my mind feels
            absolutely serene and the brushstrokes come to me and follow each other very
            logically.</good_health></p>
        <p>Anyway until Sunday AT THE LATEST, I shake your hand firmly in the meantime, warm regards
            to Jo.</p>
    </body>
    <close>Ever yours,</close>
    <sig>Vincent.</sig>
    <ps>
        <p>Probably the answer to Mr Peyron will already have left, which I hope. I was a little
            vexed that there were a few days’ delay, because that seems to me to be of no use for
            anything. For either I’d plunge into new works here, or it’s now that I have the leisure
            for the journey. <stress reason="environment">Spending days doing nothing, here or elsewhere, that’s what would make
            me miserable in my current state of mind. </stress><unstress reason="friendship">Besides, Mr P. isn’t opposed to it, but
            naturally when you leave, your position is a little difficult with the rest of the
            administration. But it’s going well, and we’ll part amicably.</unstress> </p>
    </ps>
</letter>
